Endnotes

Tradition holds that these were the words spoken by Ānanda when reciting the Suttapiṭaka at the First Council following the Buddha’s death. In fact it is a tag signifying that the text has been passed down through oral tradition and the speaker was not present at the events (DN 5:21.10, MN 127:17.4). | This sutta with its commentary was translated by Bhikkhu Bodhi in his The All-Embracing Net of Views. ↩

By convention, suttas do not specify the date, so we have scant internal chronology. | Walk about fifteen kilometers north from Rājagaha (modern Rajgir) to reach Nāḷandā. | “Mendicant” is a literal translation of bhikkhu, one who goes for alms. ↩

A “wanderer” (paribbājaka) was a homeless religious renunciate—male or female—who wandered seeking alms. Kauṭilya describes their lifestyle as “mastery of the senses, abstaining from ritual activities, living without possessions, abandoning attachments, practicing mendicancy, residing in the wilderness but not in a single place, and purifying himself internally and externally” (Arthaśāstra 1.3.12, Olivelle’s translation). | “Resident pupil” (or elsewhere just “pupil”) is antevāsi, a live-in apprentice of a master. | “Student” (māṇava) is a young man who was learning the Vedas from a master. ↩

Today these are called the Triple Gem that makes up the Buddhist religion; however they are not known by that term in the early texts. ↩

While the disagreement of student and teacher signifies their confusion, it also represents the diversity of views within the brahmanical caste and the openness with which a student could disagree with their teacher. ↩

Ambalaṭṭhikā means “place of mango saplings”. It was a rest-house set up by the king of Rājagaha about a day’s journey from the capital. It must have been sizable. ↩

Saṅkhiyadhamma is a unique term. The commentary glosses it as kathādhamma, following which it has been translated as “conversation” or “trend of conversation”. But saṅkhā means “appraisal, assessment, evaluation, measuring, calculating”, and here the subject of discussion is the different ways the two parties assess or judge the Buddha, Dhamma, and Saṅgha. Compare the “appraisal” of the Buddha at DN 19:19.2. ↩

Adhimutti is something that has been decided, a conviction or belief. ↩

This would have been an open air pavilion in the rest-house. By convention, when a teacher or other respected person is to sit, a sitting mat is spread out or made ready for them. ↩

The very first words of the Buddha in the Suttapiṭaka: he asks to hear what others are saying. ↩

Here and in similar passages the Pali repeats all and I abbreviate. ↩

The phrasing here is somewhat unusual and specific. They “should not do” what creates bitterness (i.e. judging others). Compare MN 22, where the same phrases are used. In the Buddha’s case, it has the neutral hoti, while for the mendicants it uses karaṇīya, as here. ↩

Complaining about others does not hurt them, only the one who gets upset. ↩

Equanimity is a prerequisite for evaluating facts. ↩

Ethics (or morality or virtue, sīla) is important, but it pales in comparison with the higher dimensions of the Buddha’s path. For an example of this kind of praise see MN 77:8.1. | The Buddha often referred to himself as “the Realized One” (tathāgata). ↩

Here the Buddha lays out in detail the ethical conduct for mendicant followers. ↩

The first and most important precept. It is not just the negative injunction to avoid killing, but also the positive injunction to have compassion for all creatures. | The Buddha is called “the ascetic Gotama” by non-Buddhists. ↩

An “ordinary person” (puthujjana) is anyone who has not, at minimum, entered the path to stream-entry. ↩

“Chastity” is brahmacariya, literally “divine conduct”. Here it is used in the narrow sense of refraining from sex, but more commonly it has a broader sense of “spiritual life” (SN 42.7:2.6). ↩

This is the first of the four kinds of right speech. Just as the precept of not killing implies the positive injunction to live with compassion, the precepts on speech enjoin a positive and constructive use of speech. ↩

“Harmony” (or “unanimity”, samagga) does not excuse untrue, bigoted, or otherwise harmful speech. True harmony is only achieved in the presence of the Dhamma. ↩

Attha is a polyvalent term, here taking the senses “meaningful” and “beneficial”. Elsewhere it means “goal”, “need”, “purpose”, “lawsuit”, or “ending”, and the senses are not always easy to untangle. ↩

Buddhists generally do not regard plants as sentient, but value them as part of the ecosystem that supports all life. ↩

From MN 66:6.4 and MN 70:4.8 we can see that “at night” means after dark, while “at the wrong time” means in the afternoon. More explicitly, these are the “wrong time at night” and the “wrong time in the day”, in which case they are both the “wrong time”. ↩

Such sensual entertainments distract and excite the mind. This and the next three precepts encourage peace of mind for meditation. ↩

This was ignored by the Buddha’s cousin, Nanda (SN 21.8:1.2). ↩

To avoid sleeping too much. ↩

Literally “gold and silver” (jātarūparajata), but rajata is explained in Bu NP 18:2.8 as currency of any kind. ↩

Mendicants receive only the day’s meal and do not store or cook food. ↩

According to ancient Indian law (Arthaśāstra 3.13), a person in a time of trouble may bind themselves in service for a fee. Such bondservants were protected against cruelty, sexual abuse, and unfair work. After earning back the fee of their indenture they were freed, retaining their original inheritance and status. ↩

These are animals raised for food. ↩

Land for a monastery may be accepted by the Saṅgha as a community, but not by individual mendicants. ↩

These items are discussed in detail below. | Acting as a go-between for lay business was tempting due to the mendicants’ wandering lifestyle. However, it exposes them to risk if the message is not delivered or if it is bad news. ↩

For example, trading in monastery property. ↩

This section expands some of the former section in further detail. | The “middle” and “large” sections on ethics are not found in briefer presentations such as MN 27:14.1. ↩

That these are not five “kinds of seeds” but five kinds of “plants grown from seeds” is clear from the Vinaya and its commentary (Bu Pc 11: Bhūtagāmo nāma pañca bījajātāni). ↩

For storing up food as a sign of decline, see DN 27:17.5. ↩

Sobhanaka (“beauty pageant”) is explained by the commentary as the movement (or “sprinkling”) of dancers, or their beautification and painting. The PTS reading sobha-nagarakaṁ, supported by an unrelated reference to a gandhabba city of that name, is spurious. | Caṇḍālaṁ vaṁsaṁ dhovanaṁ should be a compound, as shown by the prose to Ja 498, where it is a performance by corpse-workers (caṇḍāla) in Ujjenī. Vaṁsa is the bamboo used by caṇḍāla acrobats (SN 47.19). Dhovana is referred by the commentary to AN 10.107, where it is a southern ceremony accompanied by drink and dance. The commentaries to AN and DN say it was the ritual washing of the bones of the buried dead after the decomposition of the flesh. Such “second funeral” rites have been observed world-wide. From the Jātaka it appears that the tradition had declined to a mere display for passers-by, perhaps featuring naked tribal girls. | Uyodhika is sometimes said to be “sham fights”, but at AN 10.30 it is not a sham. And the definition at Bu Pc 50 says “where strife is seen”. ↩

See too DN 31:11.1. ↩

“Checkers” (aṭṭhapada) was presumably the ancestor of the Gupta period caturaṅga and hence modern chess. | Yathāvajja is explained in the commentary as “mimicking deformities”, but I cannot find support elsewhere in Pali or Sanskrit for vajja in this sense. More likely it refers to musical instruments (Sanskrit vādya). ↩

In Pali, ajinappaveṇi appears as a compound, but it is hard to see how antelope hide could be a “weave”. In Sanskrit sources they are separate, and regarded as fit offerings for a brahmin (Mahābhārata 15.34.13a, Brahmāṇḍa Purāṇa 2.16.33). ↩

Tiracchānakathā literally means “animal talk”. The Pali word for animal, tiracchāna has the sense of “moving horizontally”, and “low talk” is that which does not elevate. ↩

Bhavābhava does not mean “existence and non-existence” but is a distributive compound, “this or that state of existence”. Indian religious texts are full of discussions about different heavens and hells. | The visikhā was a street where gold was exchanged and diversions were to be found, i.e. a “street market” (DN 31:9.1, Arthaśāstra 1.1.4c, 2.13.2). | The kumbhaṭṭhāna was a place where water pots were set up for public drinking water. ↩

The folly of disputatiousness is a consistent theme in the suttas, but is a special focus of the Aṭṭhakavagga of the Suttanipāta. ↩

“Rulers” (raññaṁ, genitive plural) include hereditary kings as well as the elected joint leaders of republican states such as the Sakyans or Vajjis. ↩

Some renunciants like to butter up potential donors, or make ostentatious displays to prompt further donations. | “Using material possessions to chase after other material possessions” includes trading monastery property for profit. ↩

This section focuses on practices that are wrong livelihood for a mendicant, though not for lay people. The Vinaya explains “low lore” as whatever is non-Buddhist or useless (Bi Pc 49), while the commentary says it leads not to emancipation but to heaven. Most of the items in this and the following sections are detailed in later astrological texts such as Varāhamihira’s Bṛhatsaṁhitā. There are too many correspondences to cite, so I’ll only mention those that impact the translation. ↩

The list has both aṅga and aṅgavijjā, and it’s hard to disambiguate them; the commentary tries, unpersuasively. Bṛhatsaṁhitā 50 has aṅgavidyā, which is various kinds of “limb-reading” (compare modern “palmistry”) but no equivalent to aṅga. Perhaps it is a misspelling of the less-familiar aṅka, “mark, sign”, hence “augury”. | “Portents” (uppāta are discussed at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 45. | Lakkhaṇa is detailed at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 67–69 as a thorough assessment of the features of men and women, including physical marks, character, voice, gait, and so on. | Read khattavijjā (“political science”) per variant as khettavijjā (“geomancy”). | Sara in saraparitta means “sound” not “arrow”; compare with sarabhañña “chanting”. | Migacakka is explained in the commentary, supported by Bṛhatsaṁhitā, as interpretation of the cries and behaviors of wild animals. Here the suffix -cakka refers to the field of study. See also Mil 5.3.7:6.1: sācakkaṁ migacakkaṁ antaracakkaṁ (“divining omens from dogs, wild animals, and the directions around”), terms which are also found at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 2.17. ↩

The commentary oddly has “earrings or house-gables” for kaṇṇika (“eared one”), but it must be “rabbit”, for which see sasakaṇṇikā at Ja 535:76.6. ↩

Despite this, astrology is commonly practiced today among Buddhist mendicants. | (Up)pathagamana can hardly mean that the sun, moon, and stars will “go astray”. Rather, patha here has the sense of “range”, so it means “come within range”, which describes an astrological conjunction. | For “fiery sky” (disāḍāha), i.e. a glow on the horizon, as an omen, see diśāṁ dāhe at Manusmṛti 4.115 and digdāha in Bṛhatsaṁhitā 31. ↩

“Cosmology” (lokāyata) in early Buddhist texts is not, as it later became known, the heterodox school of materialism. Rather, it was a branch of worldly knowledge within regular Vedic studies concerned with the nature and extent of the world and how this may be known (AN 9.38, SN 12.48; cf. Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 3.3.1). ↩

The commentary has saṅkiraṇa and vikiraṇa as “saving and spending” (cp. Snp 1.6:23.1), but it seems unlikely. Vikiraṇa means “scattering” food or sand, while Sanskrit vikira is the ritual scattering of rice. Given the context, I think it refers to the custom of scattering rice at a wedding. | For viruddhagabbhakaraṇa, viruddha means “obstructed”. The commentary here, in general agreement with the Niddesa on gabbhakaraṇa at Snp 4.14, explains as giving treatments for the survival of the fetus. | I omit hanujappana as it is absent from the commentary and seems to have just arisen by confusion. ↩

Medicine is right livelihood, but a mendicant should not make a living from it. They may treat fellow mendicants, family members, or those close to the monastery. | Santikamma is the Sanskrit śāntikakarman, a rite for averting evil. | For vassakamma and vossakamma, the commentary has “fertile and infertile men” (vassoti puriso, vossoti paṇḍako), taking “rain” as a metaphor for semen. Such usages do have precedent elsewhere. But in context I take vassa simply as “rain” and vossa as equivalent to Sanskrit vyavasya in the sense of making a settlement for land. | I take paṭimokkho in the sense of “binding”; see pratimuñcate at Rig Veda 4.53.2, 5.81.2; paṭimokka at Ja 524:10.2; paṭimukka at MN 38:41.11, Ja 513:6.2 etc., rather than the commentary’s “release” (from the effects of caustic medicines; cf. Tha Ap 25:5.4). ↩

One meaning of dhamma is “principle” in the sense of a natural law as well as a moral value. | Here begins the famous exposition of the sixty-two views. The subtlety of the analysis lies in how, rather than refuting the details of the views, the Buddha traces them all back to their fundamental psychology. | Pubbanta and aparanta (literally “prior end” and “posterior end”) are technical terms found exclusively in Buddhism and only used in the context of speculative views. It seems the Buddha had a contextual reason to avoid the generic words for “past” (atīta) and “future” (anāgata), and I reflect that in my translation. Pubbanta is semantically identical with pubbakoti, the “first point” of existence or transmigration (SN 48.50:5.3). This is emphasized by Nāgarjuna, who introduces the terms pubbanta and aparanta immediately after discussing the “first point” of transmigration, and associates them with the “extremes” (anta) of eternalism and annihilationism (Mūlamadhyamakakārikā 25.20–23). Thus such talk is not merely about the past as in what happened yesterday, or the future as in what I’ll do next week, but unmoored speculations about the “first beginning” and the “final end”. ↩

“Hypothesis” is adhimuttipada, literally “statement of conviction”. We sometimes find adhivuttipada, which appears to be a variant spelling (MN 102:2.1, AN 10.22:2.1). ↩

In such contexts, the “self” (attā) is a postulated metaphysical entity rather than a simple psychological sense of personal identity. The nature of this “self” or “soul” was endlessly debated. The Buddha rejected all theories of a “self”, and elsewhere it is said that “identity view” underlies all sixty-two views of the Brahmajāla (SN 41.3:4.13). | The “cosmos” is the loka, otherwise translated as “world”. This sometimes refers to the simple physical realm, sometimes to the world of experience, or else, as here, the vast universe as conceived in ancient Indian thought. ↩

“Immersion” (samādhi) is deep meditative stillness. The word conveys the sense of “gathered”, “collected”, with a secondary sense of “ignited”, “illuminated”. The practice of samādhi (or jhāna, “absorption”) has never been regarded as uniquely Buddhist. However, right meditation begins with right view. Since these meditators begin with wrong view, their samādhi is “wrong” because it merely reinforces their error. | These are those who rely on the “known” (viññāta) in the epistemic tetrad (MN 1:19.1). ↩

The recollection of past lives is specific, detailed, and confident as it is based on the clear mind of deep immersion. ↩

This is the Upaniṣadic view of the eternal ātman that is the immanent soul of the world or cosmos, loka. Elsewhere in the suttas such theorists assert that the self and the cosmos are identical (SN 24.3:1.3: so attā so loko). ↩

The eternal “self” is contrasted with the ephemeral lives of beings. | The famous word saṁsara is often understood as a “cycle” of rebirths, but the meaning is, rather, to “wander on” or “transmigrate”. | For the phrase sassatisamaṁ (“lasting forever and ever”), compare Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 5.10.1: “He reaches that world free of sorrow and snow, where he lives forever and ever” (sa lokam āgacchaty aśokam ahimam | tasmin vasati śāśvatīḥ samāḥ). ↩

Their meditative experience revealed a process of transient and changing lives, yet from that they infer that there must be an eternal self. ↩

This differs only in the length of time, which is now up to ten eons. A single eon (kappa) lasts longer than it would take to wear away a huge mountain by stroking it with a cloth once a century SN 15.5, while the number of eons is greater than the sands in the Ganges River SN 15.8. The vast time periods envisaged in early Buddhist texts are comparable with those of modern cosmology in physics. ↩

These theorists used a process of logic (takka) and inquiry (vīmaṁsā), otherwise called “thought” (muta) in the epistemic tetrad (MN 1:19.1). They arrive at the same conclusion as the meditators. Different groups of ascetic philosophers emphasized contemplation or rational inquiry as the means to the truth. The Buddha acknowledged that both are useful but limited because, as here, they can sometimes lead to mistaken conclusions. ↩

I have my doubts about this phrase. Everywhere else, ito bahiddhā means “outside of the Buddhist community”, not “outside of the cases just considered”. Still, the commentary and the Chinese parallel at T 21 agree on this sense. ↩

A “view” (diṭṭhi) is a relatively fixed framework for understanding the world; a “theory”. The “grounds for views” (diṭṭhiṭṭhānāni) are the bases from which the views are derived. In this case these are the meditative experiences or the logical reasoning. ↩

The word parāmasati means “to take hold” and is often used in the sense “to misapprehend”. ↩

Yathābhūtaṁ is often translated as “as it really is”, while I usually render it simply as “truly”. It often has a technical sense of seeing “how things came to be (bhuta)” as a process of conditionality (SN 12.31:7.1). Such direct vision of the truth is an attribute of the stream-enterer, who has realized the first of the four stages of awakening, in contrast with those on the path who still rely on faith or inference (SN 25.1). Here it refers to the understanding of feelings from a fivefold perspective. Feelings underlie intellectual theories and arguments, which serve to sate cravings and fears. ↩

Long texts are sometimes marked by their “recitation sections” (bhāṇavāra), which was the length that would be recited in one session. ↩

Despite being views of the “self and the cosmos”, the main focus in the next four views is the self. ↩

This is the end of an eon. It might be compared with what the physicists call the “big crunch”. ↩

The human and similar realms are destroyed in the conflagration at the end of the universe, but sentient beings are sustained by the power of their past kamma. | The “realm of sublime radiance” is a Brahmā heaven corresponding to the second jhāna. The Sanskrit spelling ₋ābhāsvara suggests the derivation ābhā + vara, “sublime radiance”. The commentary derives this (and related forms bhassara and pabhassara) from sara (“stream”), but this is ruled out by the Sanskrit, which has vara in all cases, whereas “stream” is sara_. ↩

“Mind-made” (manomaya) beings are spontaneously born due to past kamma, not by sex. | “Rapture” (pīti) is a joyous emotional response to pleasure, usually a spiritual sense of elevation or uplift in meditation. | “Self-lumious” (sayaṁpabhā) as an external representation of the light of absorption through which they attained their exalted status. In the Rig Veda it is used of the divine light of the sun (1.52.9 svaścandram; 6.64.4 svabhāna) or the lightning (5.87.5 svarociṣa; 1.82.2 svabhāna). ↩

This might be compared with the “big bang” of a cyclic universe. ↩

The realms into which beings are reborn exist interdependently with the beings themselves. The different dimensions correspond with different kinds of kamma. ↩

That is, they pass from a world corresponding to the second jhāna to one corresponding to the first jhāna. ↩

This passage echoes the creation myth in Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.4. At 1.4.2, the self-created Divinity feels fearful and alone, and at 1.4.3 and 1.4.17 wishes for a partner. From a Buddhist point of view, this simply shows how even God is trapped by emotional attachments in the cycle of transmigration. ↩

These beings are reborn according to their own kamma, and it is just a coincidence that they appear after the first being made their wish. ↩

His first words ahamasmi brahmā (“I am Brahmā”) are equivalent to aham brahmāsmīti at Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.4.10. ↩

At Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.4.5 the Divinity thinks, “I created all this”. ↩

The other creatures appeared after his wish, not because of it. God confuses correlation with causation, a mistake perpetuated by no small number of his followers. ↩

At Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.4.9–10 the created humans also think first about the Divinity who preceded them, from whose knowledge of self all was created. ↩

Again, their meditation experience is genuine, but what they infer from it goes beyond the facts. ↩

The surviving forms of Indic religion (Buddhism, Hinduism, Jainism) typically hold that all creatures ultimately share the same nature and hence can find liberation. Here we see this was not always the case, for these theorists believed that there are inherently different orders of beings in the cosmos. This is not due to their conduct but to the circumstances of their creation. ↩

Delightful as the life of the gods is, even they are supposed to retain a sense of moderation (MN 37:11.2), a lesson forgotten by those “depraved by play” (khiḍḍāpadosikā). | Note that mindfulness (sati) is not held to be a specifically Buddhist virtue. Here it refers to a sense of moral compass and self-awareness, rather than a meditation practice. ↩

Here the difference in beings is attributed not to the circumstances of their creation but to their behavior. ↩

The parallel between manopadosika (“malevolent”) and khiddapadosika (“depraved by play”) suggests a rendering “depraved in mind” for manopadosika. However, elsewhere in the suttas manopadosa consistently means “malicious intent” (MN 56:13.15, MN 93:18.30, DN 26:20.3. Also see mano padūseyya at MN 21:20.1 and MN 28:9.6. Thus the contrast is between greed and hate. | Here, as usual, mano and citta are synonyms for “mind”. ↩

The Buddha critiqued this view at SN 12.61, arguing that the body is, in fact, longer lasting than the mind. ↩

The terms “mind” (citta), “sentience” (mano), and “consciousness” (viññāṇa) are broadly synonymous and in many cases may be substituted for one another. Nonetheless, they each have a particular context in which they predominate. Citta is to be developed, in which respect it pertains to the fourth noble truth, the path. Mano, which I translate here as “sentience” for the sake of disambiguation, is often used in the active sense of the deeds done by the mind, pertaining to the second noble truth, the origin of suffering. Viññāṇa is the key factor in the experince of suffering, pertaining to the first noble truth. ↩

Here we move from views that conceive of both the self and the cosmos together to those that focus only on the physical extent of the cosmos. It is not clear why these are classified as “views of the past”. ↩

Once again the view is inferred from meditation, showing that meditative experience was regarded by some as revealing genuine truths about the physical realm. ↩

The nature of their meditation is assumed to be the nature of the world itself. ↩

In each of the two previous sets of four views, the views themselves were the same, only the means of knowing them differed. Here the views themselves differ. The differences take the form of a tetralemma: A, not-A, both A and not-A, neither A nor not-A. This pattern is commonly found in early Buddhism, as well as Indian thought more generally. The final two items are not meant to be obscure or mysterious, but to express genuine possibilities that cannot be captured by a simple duality. ↩

It is common today to say that one’s own experience is valid for oneself. Clearly that is not how these philosophers thought. ↩

They perceive the universe as spread out like a disc. One might call it a “discworld”. ↩

The text doesn’t specify what this is, but it might include the view that the ideas “finite” and “infinite” are inadequate to describe the universe. Consider a universe expanding at the speed of light. At any point in time it is not infinite, but as it is impossible to reach its end it is not finite either. ↩

Vikkhepa is “ﬂip-flopping”. | Amarā is explained in the commentary as either “undying” or “eel-like”. However, amarā in the sense of “eel” is found only in the commentary to this term so is probably spurious. The feminine form amarā is attested in Sanskrit (eg. Manu 2.148). See also note to SN 4.1:5.2. ↩

This is a basic requirement for any spiritual teacher. ↩

Despite their dullness, they have a genuine sense of conscience and wish to avoid breaking precepts. ↩

A wise teacher avoids making pronouncements about what they do not understand, but these teachers use this as a cover to hide the fact that they do not understand anything. ↩

Here too they show a certain sincerity to avoid giving rise to unwholesome qualities. ↩

They avoid making statements, not from a sense of conscience, but for fear of public shaming. ↩

Also at MN 76:30.2. ↩

Here begins a series of four tetrads that are commonly encountered in the suttas. The first is the belief in an afterlife. ↩

The denial of an afterlife. ↩

This could include a belief that eternal life is offered only to adherents of a certain religion. ↩

This could include the idea that our intrinsic nature is one with the cosmos, and our separation from that infinitude in this life is only a veil of delusion. Thus there is no other world, because all worlds are this world, but it is also not the case that there is nothing after death. ↩

This is beings such as the gods or various ghosts and spirits, which are not born organically. ↩

This denies the existence of such beings. Not everyone in ancient India believed in the various orders of beings. ↩

The belief that beings are both spontaneously born and organically born. Perhaps this denies that such a distinction can be made clearly, because both kinds of birth take place within the same order of beings. ↩

Beings are reborn in other ways. ↩

This is the standard Buddhist view of kamma, shared with some, but not all, of the other Indian religions of the time. ↩

Doing good or bad has no result; moral nihilism. ↩

Sometimes good and bad deeds have results, other times not. ↩

The results of actions are too subtle to be described as good or bad. ↩

An awakened one, whether the Buddha or anyone else, exists after death, for example in an eternal state of Nirvana. ↩

A sage ceases to exist at the time of death. This assumes there is an enduring “self” that is done away with. ↩

For example, their body does not exist but their mind does. ↩

A sage persists in a subtle state that cannot be characterized in terms of existence or non-existence. ↩

Adhicca is usually translated in this context as “chance”. The root meaning refers to something that has been “lifted out”, making it a “special exception” or “anomaly”. It isn’t used in Sanskrit for a philosophical theory of chance, for which we find instead yadṛcchā (“arbitrariness”, Śvetāśvatara Upaniṣad 1.2). The theory proposed here is not that the universe in general operates by chance, but that the happenstance of creation is an “anomaly” in the general scheme of things. At SN 12.24:3.4 and SN 12.25:2.4 we learn that some philosophers who believed in the doctrine of kamma nonetheless argued that suffering arose anomalously. ↩

This is an obscure realm of existence where the operations of consciousness are suspended. ↩

The idea of creation from nothingness is discussed at Rig Veda 10.129, Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.2. ↩

First each section is concluded, then the whole first part is concluded. This formalism is a characteristic of oral tradition. It creates a nested hierarchy of content, clarifying the structure and helping to preserve the text in memory. ↩

This section introduces more tetralemmas. Many of the views describe the self in terms of the five aggregates—form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness. ↩

“Percipient beings” are mentioned in the Jain Tattvārthasūtra 2.24. ↩

Usually a self is conceived of as percipient, so that the subject experiences a continuity. | The term aroga (“healthy”) is explained by the commentary as “permanent” (nicca), drawing on the root sense of the word, “unbroken”. However, aroga is always used in the sense “free of disease, well, healthy” (eg. MN 97:2.4), and this applies to the Brahmanical tradition as well as the Buddhist. Chandogya Upaniṣad 7.26.2 says that one who sees (the self) does not see death, they have no disease or pain. Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.4.12 similarly says that one who sees the self will not suffer in the wake of the body, which Śaṅkāra explains, “Struggling with desires for himself, for his son, for his wife, and so on, he is born and dies again and again, and is diseased when his body is diseased.” ↩

Here the self has a physical dimension but no perception. This might include rebirth as a plant or inanimate object. ↩

Buddhism acknowledges a formless realm of neither perception nor non-perception, which is attained through advanced meditation. ↩

These theorists assert the true existence of a being, thus falling into the fallacy of identity view. For the Buddha, the words “being” or a “self” describe an ongoing process that is conditioned and impermanent, and do not correspond to a genuine metaphysical reality. The distinction between contingent, empirical reality and metaphysical, absolute existence is essential to understanding early Buddhism. ↩

This is the materialist view, which accepts only the coarse physical realm. This view is common today, but was also well known in the Buddha’s time. | The “four principal states” are earth, water, fire, and air, i.e. the states of matter: solid, liquid, plasma, and gas. ↩

The theorist accepts multiple selves. As self theories evolve, they typically move from more coarse materialist theories toward more subtle conceptions. Sometimes the former view is rejected as being false. Sometimes, as here, the former view is seen not as false, but as incomplete and shallow. ↩

“Form” (rūpa) includes not just the physical realm of the elements, but various kinds of subtle form (sukhumarūpa). These include the energetic or mind-made bodies of beings in various dimensions. Rūpa ultimately refers to the appearance or manifestation of physical properties, and can even include the perception of colors, lights, and shapes in the mind. Here the bodies of the divine beings are not very distant from our own, as they still consume solid food. This probably refers to various nature deities or entities that were believed to consume the food offered to them by humans. ↩

Whereas the eternalists believe that their heavenly rebirth will last forever, annihilationists believe that even heaven is limited, and it ends in final annihilation. ↩

This is a more subtle kind of divine rebirth, no longer dependent on physical food. The subtle body still takes on a humanoid form, however, appearing complete in all its limbs. It includes realms produced through the practice of the four jhānas. | Sabbaṅga has the sense “whole and healthy of limb” (Rig Veda 10.161.5c, Atharva Veda 8.2.8c, 11.3.32 ff.). One is reborn with “whole body” (sarvatanu, Atharva Veda 5.6.11c, Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 11.1.8.60, 12.8.3.31). | Paccaṅga means “minor limb”, for example the fingers or internal organs. ↩

Such a rebirth has left even the subtle body behind, becoming sheer consciousness. | The word āyatana is from a root meaning “expanse”. It is prominently used in this context, where it refers to a realm or “dimension” of rebirth, and in the analysis of sense experience, where it refers to a “field” of sense experience. ↩

This phrase appears incongruous as formless beings do not have a body. However the Chinese parallel at DA 21 does not mention kāya here, so it is likely to have arisen as an error in transmission where an earlier phrase was mistakenly copied. ↩

The extension of the normal description of this state with the phrase “this is peaceful, this is sublime” is found only here and at AN 10.99:35.1. ↩

These five theories argue for the extinguishment of suffering through the experience of pleasure in the present life. The Buddha taught extinguishment (nibbāna) in this very life, but not “of an existing being” (sato sattassa) or “self” (attā). The Buddha denied that there is such a thing, pointing out that we are a stream of ever-changing conditions, fueled by desire and attachment, and liable to suffering. With the end of craving there is no fuel to sustain the stream, so suffering comes to an end. | It is unclear why these views of the “present life” (diṭṭhadhamma) are classified under views of the future; see MN 102:2.8. ↩

The hedonist. ↩

Here we see the philosophical reasoning that prompts the evolution of more refined conceptions of self. ↩

The “absorptions” (jhāna) are central to Buddhist meditation. The Buddha did say that they can be considered “extinguishment in the present life” in a qualified sense (AN 9.51). As we have seen above, however, if they are undertaken with wrong view, the experience itself will tend to reinforce the attachment to a self. ↩

The theorist has an experience of a deeper state of meditation, so they know that the first jhāna cannot be the ultimate. ↩

Jhānas are subtle states of refined consciousness in which nothing is coarse when compared to ordinary consciousness. Within each state, however, certain mental factors are coarse relative to others. A meditator proceeds through the jhānas with the successive stilling of the relatively coarser factors in each state. ↩

Ābhoga (“partaking”) is unique in the early texts in this sense. The commentary says that after emerging from jhāna, one repeatedly partakes and attends to that bliss. Compare Patañjalī’s commentary on Yogasūtra 1.17: “vitarka is the gross partaking in the mental object, vicāra is subtle” (vitarkaś cittasyālambane sthūla ābhogaḥ, sūkṣmo vicāraḥ). For ābhoga with manasikāra, see vātassa ābhogo vā manasikāro vā at Mil 5.1.1:8.3; manaskāraścetasa ābhogaḥ at Vasubandhu’s Abhidharmakośabhāṣya 054|23), and cittābhogo manaskāraścarcā saṁkhyā vicāraṇā at Amarasiṁha’s Amarakośa 1.5.321. ↩

It is not clear why the still more subtle states of the formless attainments are not included here. ↩

Even the views of annihilation or extinguishment lead to rebirth, contrary to the beliefs of those who hold them. ↩

Here the Buddha brings to the fore the notion of feelings which has been briefly mentioned throughout the text. Views are not objective descriptions of the world, but responses to our innermost needs. The word paritassita (“anxiety”) conveys both fear and desire, while vipphandita (“evasiveness”) captures how attachment to theorizing serves as an avoidance strategy. ↩

The analysis is introducing more elements of dependent origination. The famous twelve links say that contact is the condition for feeling, which in turn causes craving. ↩

The text repeats all, but I abbreviate for legibility. In the oral tradition, extensive repetitions serve to reinforce the learning and ensure reliability of transmission. More subtly, they also help deepen understanding and contemplation. After reciting the extensive and complex treatment of the sixty-two views, the reciter takes the time to go over them again and again, letting them settle and consolidate. True learning takes time, but the repetitions that are reflective and reassuring in recitation become irksome and ponderous in reading. ↩

Finally the process of dependent origination, which has been foreshadowed little by little, is brought to its ultimate conclusion. The full twelve factors of dependent origination are not mentioned, but the process beginning with ignorance is implied throughout. Wrong view is a form of ignorance, and we have seen several examples of how such wrong views prompt intentional choices that generate consciousness in a new life. ↩

“Contact” (phassa) is the conjunction of the sense stimulus, the sense organ, and the associated consciousness. ↩

They cannot see a way past attachment so long as they theorize in terms of an existing self. ↩

The title is explained with a vivid simile. The Buddha was a master of observation, and constantly drew from everyday experience to illustrate his teachings. The metaphor works on a surface level to illustrate how theorists are trapped. But it also conveys something deeper, a sense of pathos and empathy with the helpless creatures who have no idea why they suffer. ↩

The Buddha is not his body, which is merely the remnant of past kamma. | The bhavanetti is “that which leads to continued existence”. Early Sanskrit netrī always retains the expected grammatical sense, a noun from the root “to lead”, i.e. a “leader” (Rig Veda 1.113.4, 4.56.2, 5.50.2, 7.76.6, 7.77.2). Compare the English concept of the psychopomp or ferryman who leads you to the afterlife. Here, the commentary explains, “It is a name for craving. For by it beings are bound in their heart and lead on to life after life, like an ox tethered by the throat.” This suggests the sense of “lead” as in “leash”, which fits the metaphor of “cutting off”. ↩

This metaphor is found at Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.3.36, where it refers to the separation of the self from the body at death. ↩

It is not uncommon to find multiple names for the same sutta, and here we see this practice originated with the Buddha himself. When is referred to by name, however, it is always called the Brahmajāla (SN 41.3:2.4, Kd 21:1.8.8, Vb 17:21.3). It is also referred to by the list of views, numbered sixty-three at Snp 3.6:42.1 and sixty at SN 8.2:5.1 = Thag 21.1:9.1. ↩

This sutta with its commentary was translated by Bhikkhu Bodhi in his The Fruits of Recluseship. ↩

This monastery belonged to the Buddha’s doctor, Jīvaka, who appears later in the sutta. His story is told in Kd 8, where we learn that he was raised by Prince Abhaya of Magadha, a Jain (MN 58) who was also interested in the teachings of Pūraṇa Kassapa (SN 46.56). MN 55 on eating meat is addressed to him. ↩

The Komudī was an especially celebrated full moon on the last month of the rainy season (kattikā, October/November), when the skies were clear, the lotuses (kumudā) were in bloom, and the moon was in conjunction with the Pleiades, which gave the month its name. ↩

Ajātasattu (“one against whom no foe is born”) was the son of Bimbisāra and heir to the Haryaṅka dynasty of Magadha. In inscription and Jain tradition he is also called Kūṇika. Jain tradition holds that his mother was Cellaṇā daughter of Ceṭaka, a Licchavī ruler from Vesālī. This begs the question as to why Cellaṇā was said to be “of Videha”; perhaps he married a Videhan princess to forge an alliance with the Licchavī’s northern neighbors. In any case, this is more plausible than the Buddhist tradition that his mother was Kosalan. ↩

Pāsādikā here does not mean “tranquil”; it is part of a stock list of terms meaning “beautiful, attractive” (eg. DN 4:13.7). | Lakkhaññā is unique in early Pali. It is probably a synonym in the sense of “possessing remarkable features, striking”, rather than “auspicious”. ↩

The king seeks redemption through his own actions; it is not that the ascetic has any special power to bring peace to his mind. | The sutta is deliberately holding back the reason for the king’s distress. Compare AN 5.50, where the reason for King Muṇḍa seeking solace is stated up front. ↩

Though the king mentioned “ascetics and brahmins”, his advisers only recommend famous teachers of the ascetics (samaṇa). For a shorter survey of their doctrines, see SN 2.30. ↩

A little-known teacher of the inefficacy of action and consequence, Pūraṇa was poorly regarded even by his own students (MN 77:6.19). He is said to have advocated a doctrine of six classes of rebirth (AN 6.57. The same text reverentially mentions Makkhali Gosāla, and it seems Pūraṇa, like Gosāla and Pakudha, was a defining teacher of the Ājīvakas. | Pūraṇa means “filling” (not purāṇa, “ancient”). ↩

The reason for the king’s silence is revealed later. The narrative is full of foreshadowing. ↩

Founder of the Ājīvakas, who became the third largest ascetic movement after Buddhism and Jainism. None of their texts survive, but their teachings can be partially reconstructed from Buddhist and Jain sources. He practiced with Mahāvīra for six years before an acrimonious split, following which he developed his doctrine of hard determinism. Makkhali denotes a kind of ascetic bearing a bamboo staff, so (like the similar appellations nigaṇṭha and samaṇa) it indicates his affiliation. This being so, and noting that Buddhist Sanskrit texts spell his name as gośālīputra etc., the second name (like nātaputta and gotama) might indicate his clan. However, I can find no trace of such a clan, and both Jain and Buddhist tradition, albeit unreliably, say the name arose because he was born in a cowshed. ↩

A materialist, he was an early proponent of the ideas later known as Cārvāka. Kesakambala means “hair-blanket”, which was worn as an ascetic practice (AN 3.137). ↩

Another obscure teacher, he taught a reductive atomism which negated the possibility of action with consequences. His first name is sometimes spelled Kakudha; both words signify a hump or crest. He was likely one of the early teachers of the Ājīvakas. ↩

An agnostic, he is evidently the “wanderer Sañjaya” who was the first teacher of Sāriputta and Moggallāna before they left him to follow the Buddha (Kd 1:23.1.1). His name is obscure. Sanskrit spells it vairaṭṭīputra, with several variations, but always with ṭi. The commentary says he was the “son of Belaṭṭha”; a Belaṭṭha Kaccāna is found selling sugar at Kd 1:26.1.2, supporting the idea that Belaṭṭha was a personal rather than clan name. ↩

The Jain leader Mahāvīra Vardhamāna is known as Nigaṇṭha Nātaputta in Pali texts. He is regarded as the 24th supreme leader of the Jains, although only he and his predecessor Pārśvanātha (not mentioned in the Pali) are historical. Nigaṇṭha means “knotless” (i.e. without attachments). As a term for Jain ascetics it is also found in Jain literature. Nātaputta indicates his clan the Ñātikas (Sanskrit jñātiputra; Prākrit nāyaputta). The Pali tradition has confused ñāti (“family”) with nāṭa (“dancer”). Thus Nigaṇṭha Nātaputta means “the Jain monk of the Ñātika clan”. | Jainism and Buddhism are the only ancient samaṇa movements to survive to the present day. The primary Jain teaching is the practice of non-violence while burning off past kamma by fervent austerities in order to reach omniscient liberation. ↩

His absence of speech signifies his wisdom. The narrative creates a dramatic expectation through his stillness, an exquisitely Buddhist aesthetic choice. ↩

According to the Vinaya, a monastery is normally offered to the “Saṅgha of the four quarters” and becomes their inalienable property. In the suttas this is not so clear, and it seems that Jīvaka still regarded the property as his. In practice there would have been a variety of arrangements, as there are today. ↩

The first appearance of the famous iti pi so formula. It is still recited in praise of the Buddha in Theravada communities. ↩

Indian kings were guarded by armed women inside the harem (Kauṭilya’s Arthaśāstra 1.21.1) and also while on hunt (Megasthenes’s Indica, via Strabo XV. i. 53–56). This passage may be the earliest evidence for this long-lasting practice. See also DN 23:15.4. ↩

The silence of the Buddha’s assembly is often contrasted with the rowdy gatherings of other ascetics, for example that of Poṭṭhapāda at DN 9:3.1. ↩

This is a double pun. Dīpa means “lamp” or “island, refuge”, while jhāyati means “burning” or “meditating”. So it could be rendered, “those are saviors meditating in the pavilion”. Jhāyati is the verb form of jhāna (“absorption”), which is the central practice of meditation described below. ↩

The Buddha looked like any other monk. But this also reveals Ajātasattu’s spiritual blindness. ↩

He has not yet gained faith, so does not bow. ↩

The Buddha, though fully aware of Ajātasattu’s crimes, responds to him with compassion. ↩

Most translators render sippa as “craft”. However, the basic meaning of “craft” is skill in doing or making things. What is meant here is a paid occupation regardless of whether it involves making things, i.e. “profession”. ↩

These are the professions on Ajātasattu’s mind. The first set of these is defined as branches of the military at AN 7.67. ↩

The question pertains to right livelihood, the fifth factor of the noble eightfold path. ↩

The purpose of right livelihood is to bring happiness in this life and the next. ↩

Ajātasattu’s question only pertains to happiness in this life. He would have seen ascetics living hard and austere lives for the sake of future happiness. ↩

The term “Great King” (mahārāja) identifies Ajātasattu as the hereditary monarch of a large realm, in contrast with the multiple elected “rulers” of the aristocratic republics such as Vajji and Sakya. ↩

As in DN 1:1.4.2, the Buddha begins by asking to hear what others have said. ↩

As with his meeting with the Buddha, Ajātasattu is respectful but not reverential. ↩

This is a denial of the doctrine of kamma. While his doctrine appears to be morally nihilistic, it seems unlikely this was Pūraṇa Kassapa’s full teaching. He may have subscribed to hard determinism, so that we have no choice in what we do. He may also have believed that we should keep moral rules as a social contract, but that this had no effect on the afterlife. | In such contexts, kar- means “punish, inflict” (MN 129:29.2). ↩

The unsatisfying nature of the answers given by these teachers is also emphasized at MN 36:48.4. ↩

Breadfruit is a starchy, fibrous fruit that is, needless to say, very different from a mango. ↩

Kings had a duty to protect all religions in their realm, even those with such extreme views. ↩

The commentary takes uggahita and nikkujjita as synonyms. Elsewhere, however, nikkujjati always means “overturns”. ↩

This denies the principle of causality and the efficacy of action. The vastness and inexplicably of the course of transmigration instils resignation. The fatalistic teachings of the Ājīvikas led to them becoming popular as prognosticators. | This view is attributed to Pūraṇa Kassapa at SN 22.60:2.2. ↩

The first three phrases, with the Magadhan nominative singular in -e, are unique to this passage. In AN 6.38:1.4 we find the regular nominative form in -o. They are omitted in the otherwise parallel passage at MN 76:13.6. ↩

For the “six classes of rebirth” see AN 6.57, where they are attributed to Pūraṇa Kassapa. | The next passage lays out the labyrinthine course through which souls must proceed before their final liberation. Many terms are unclear. The commentary is scathing of this text, seeing it as ignorant and plainly wrong. It is likely, however, that the Pali text misconstrues some of the technical terms. Basham has attempted to reconstruct their meaning, relying heavily on the Jain account in the Bhagavatī Sūtra (History and Doctrines of the Ājīvakas, p. 240ff.). My translation, drawing from Basham, assumes that the underlying scheme was coherent. For the commentarial account, see Bodhi. ↩

The “wombs” are probably species through which one transmigrates. | The many kinds of deeds classified by Ājīvakas have only contingent effect, as the ultimate course of transmigration is fixed. It seems the “half deeds” are performed by mind alone. | The 62 “paths of practice” perhaps echo the 62 wrong views of DN 1, indicating the kammic destinies of such practices. | The set of “4,900” (i.e. 7 × 700) refers to the number of times one will be reborn in each of these states. | Indriya perhaps means “lordship”, i.e. rulership in heaven or earth. | Rajodhātu perhaps relates to the Vedic sense of rajo as “dusky skies”, the cloudy regions of the lower atmosphere through which gods travel on their way from heaven. These are counted as three, six, or many. | The next set of sevens partially overlaps with a list in the Bhagavatī Sūtra, and appears to list kinds of rebirth experienced near the end of transmigration. | The Pali commentary says “non-percipient embryos” are plants, but it could be the “non-percipient beings”. | “Knotless embryos” (nigaṇṭhigabbha) perhaps refers to those born free of attachments in certain high heavens. | Pali mānusa (“human”) should probably be mānasa (“mental”), a name for an Ājīvaka heaven. But māṇasa and sara (“streams”) are also Ājīvaka terms for inconceivably long stretches of time in saṁsara. | Pavuṭā probably refers to the “castoff incarnations” (paüṭṭaparihāra), seven sages as whom, according to the Bhagavatī Sūtra, Gosāla had been born before his last life. | Papāta is “cliff”, here probably meaning “downfall” into a lower realm. | The significance of “dreams” here is unclear; perhaps they are portents. ↩

To “force unripened deeds to bear their fruit” by means of “fervent austerity” (tapas) is a Jain practice, whereas to “eliminate old deeds by experiencing their results little by little” is distinguished from the Jain view at AN 3.74. | For the stock phrase sīlena vā vatena vā tapena vā brahmacariyena vā (“by precept or observance or fervent austerity or spiritual practice”) compare the Vedic brahmacaryeṇa tapasā (“by divine studentship, by fervent austerity”, Atharva Veda 11.5.17–19). ↩

“Purification through transmigration” is saṁsārasuddhi. ↩

The denial of “mother and father” is usually interpreted as the denial of moral duty toward one’s parents. However, I think it is a doctrine of conception which denies that a child is created by the mother and father. Rather, the child is produced by the four elements, with parents as mere instigators and incubators. ↩

This is a materialist analysis of the person. | The word kāya (“substance”) is central to Jainism. Ācārāṅgasūtra 8.1.11 speaks of the “substances” of earth, water, fire, and air as being imbued with life so one should avoid damaging them. | The Buddha’s use of mahābhūtā (“principal states”) responds to Yājñavalkya’s core teaching at Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 2.4.12, where the several “states” or “real entities” (bhūtā)—namely the diverse manifestations of creation—arise from and dissolve into the “principal state” (mahābhūta) of the Self, singular and infinite. For the Buddha, the “principal states” are themselves plural, as there is no underlying singular reality. Later Sanskrit literature lists the “five states” (pañcabhūta) as earth, water, fire, air, and space. ↩

This is a reductive atomism. It argues that since all things are made of the seven fundamental substances (kāya), higher-order entities have no significance. ↩

Unlike the materialism of Ajita Kesakambala, one of the basic substances is the soul. He uses jīva, the same term used by the Jains, rather than attā as preferred by the brahmins. Likewise, the Jains held a similar doctrine of six uncreated and eternal “substances” (kāya or dravya): soul, the media for motion and rest, matter, space, and time. ↩

Compare AN 8.16:1.3. ↩

While this is a genuine Jain teaching, it has not been identified as a “fourfold restraint”. DN 25:16.3 preserves another “fourfold restraint” that is closer to that found in Jainism. At MN 12:44.1 the Buddha says he once practiced a “four-factored spiritual path” that consisted of Jain-like austerities. ↩

At Isibhāsiyāiṁ 29.19, Vardhamāna (Mahāvīra) teaches that a sage is savva-vārīhiṁ vārie, “restrained in all restraints”, which clearly parallels our current passage. In that passage, “restraint” refers to stopping the influx of defilements through the five senses, neither delighting in the pleasant nor loathing the unpleasant. Similarly we find vāriya-savva-vāri in the commentary to Sūyagaḍa 1.6.28. | Read vāri as future passive participle (cf. Sanskrit vārya). | Dhuta in the sense “shaken off (evil by means of ascetic practices)” is a characteristic Jain term. | For sabbavāriphuṭo compare ophuṭo at MN 99:15.5. In both cases phuṭ appears in a string of terms from the root var, and is possibly a corrupted form, or at least has the same meaning. ↩

This places him among the “endless flip-floppers” of DN 1:2.23.1. However, we do not know on which of the four grounds he justified his evasiveness. ↩

The Buddha answers directly, with confidence. This whole passage is a masterclass in effective dialogue. ↩

He engages Ajātasattu rather than lecturing him. ↩

See mukhaṁ ullokentī at MN 79 and SN 56.39. ↩

Even a servant believed in the doctrine of kamma. ↩

There is no question of the divinity of kings. ↩

The doctrine of kamma leads to living a better life, not stewing in resentment. ↩

Kd 1:47.1.1 penalizes the ordination of bondservants or slaves, despite the fact that Ajātasattu’s father, Bimbisāra, had ordered that no action was to be taken against any bondservant who ordained under the Buddha. ↩

Here the Buddha foreshadows the larger themes detailed later. ↩

Even under a king so compromised as Ajātasattu, a runaway slave who has ordained is rewarded not punished. ↩

In contrast with the former teachers, the Buddha gives a clear answer in terms that Ajātasattu would understand. ↩

The Buddha establishes common ground with the king before venturing into deeper waters. ↩

By starting with a very basic and obvious fruit, the Buddha stimulates Ajātasattu to seek a deeper answer. ↩

Karakārako rāsivaḍḍhako is a unique phrase. For karakāraka, compare MN 57:2.3, where a naked ascetic “does a hard thing”. Rāsi means “heap” (of grain or wealth according to the commentary). ↩

The bonded servant had no wealth or family to renounce, but the worker does. ↩

Having established the king’s genuine interest and understanding, the Buddha prepares him for the long discourse to follow. ↩

This is the start of the teaching on the Gradual Training, encompassing ethics (sīla), meditation (samādhi), and wisdom (paññā). Only the ethics portion appeared in the Brahmajālasutta, while all three are restated in all the remaining suttas of this chapter, although in truncated form. | It is exceedingly rare for a Buddha to appear. ↩

The Buddha realizes the truth by his own understanding, not through divine intervention or other metaphysical means. ↩

It is good when first heard, when practicing, and when one has realized the fruits. ↩

The word “householder” (gahapati) informally refers to any lay person, but more specifically indicates someone who owns a house, i.e. a person of standing. The renunciate life is not just for slaves or workers wishing to escape their station. ↩

This serves as a table of contents for the teachings to come. | Nowadays, the “monastic code” (pātimokkha) means the list of rules for monks and nuns found in the Vinayapiṭaka. In the early texts, however, it has three main meanings. Sometimes it does refer to the list of rules, as at AN 10.36:1.6. Here it refers to the code of conduct that follows, which is a non-legalistic set of guidelines that preceded the Vinayapiṭaka. At DN 14:3.28.1 it refers to the verses summarizing monastic conduct known as the “Ovāda Pātimokkha”. ↩

While the precept includes any living creature, if a monastic murders a human being they are immediately and permanently expelled. ↩

To steal anything of substantial value is an expulsion offense. ↩

Buddhist monastics are forbidden from any form of sexual activity. To engage in penetrative intercourse is an expulsion offense. ↩

While any form of lying is forbidden, if a monastic falsely claims states of enlightenment or deep meditation they are expelled. ↩

To avoid sleeping too much. ↩

This is the first step in the Buddha’s answer to Ajātasattu. This is the sense of happiness and well-being that you have when you know you have done nothing wrong for which anyone might blame you. It is the psychological foundation for meditation. ↩

Here begins the series of practices that build on moral fundamentals to lay the groundwork for meditation. ↩

It is not that one cannot see things, but that, mindful of its effect, one avoids unnecessary stimulation. | “Covetousness and bitterness” (abhijjhā domanassā) are the strong forms of desire and aversion caused by lack of restraint. ↩

Their happiness deepens, as they see that not only their actions but also their mind is becoming free of anything unwholesome. ↩

Situational awareness is a psychological term popularized in the 1990s. It has to do with the perception of environmental phenomena and the comprehension of their meaning, which is very close to the sense of the Pali term sampajañña. ↩

These acts describe the daily life of a mendicant: going into the village for alms, at which time there are many distracting sights. Then they return, eat their meal, and spend their day in meditation. ↩

A Buddhist monk has three robes: a lower robe (sabong or sarong), an upper robe, and an outer cloak. ↩

These are the prerequisite conditions for embarking on deep meditation. ↩

For parimukhaṁ (“present”) we find pratimukha in Sanskrit, which can mean “presence” or the reflection of the face. Late canonical Pali explains parimukhaṁ as “the tip of the nose or the reflection of the face (mukhanimitta)”. Parimukha in Sanskrit is rare, but it appears in Pāṇini 4.4.29, which the commentary illustrates with the example of a servant “in the presence” of their master (cp. SN 47.8). So it seems the sense is “before the face” or more generally “in the presence”. | To “bring mindfulness” (satiṁ upaṭṭhapetvā) is to “do satipaṭṭhāna”. The root sense of upaṭṭhāna is to “stand near” or “attend” (like a nurse on a patient, SN 47.13:1.3), and the Sanskrit upasthāna is commonly used in the sense “homage” of the gods, based on the idea of “attending” the sacred flame. A literal translation of the phrase might be, “having made memory attend to what is present”. ↩

Covetousness (abhijjha) has been curbed by sense restraint, and now is fully abandoned. ↩

Likewise ill will (byāpādapadosa), which was called domanassa in the formula for sense restraint. ↩

“Mindfulness and situational awareness” has a prominent role in abandoning dullness. ↩

Restlessness hankers for the future and is countered by contentment. Remorse digs up the past and is countered by ethical purity. ↩

The meditator set out on their path after gaining faith in the Buddha. ↩

The happiness of meditation is hard to understand without practicing, so the Buddha gives a series of five similes to illustrate in terms Ajātasattu would understand. ↩

The five hindrances remain a pillar of meditation teaching. The root sense means to “obstruct” but also to “obscure, darken, veil”. ↩

Each simile illustrates not the happiness of acquisition, but of letting go. ↩

The Buddha did not emphasize technical details of technique, but the emotional wholeness and joy that leads to deep meditation. ↩

Jhāna is a state of “elevated consciousness” (adhicitta), so all the terms have an elevated sense. | The plural form indicates that “sensual pleasures” includes sense experience, which the meditator can turn away from since they no longer have any desire for it. | The “unskillful qualities” are the five hindrances. | The “rapture and bliss born of seclusion” is the happiness of abandoning the hindrances and freedom from sense impingement. | “Placing the mind and keeping it connected” (vitakka, vicāra) uses terms that mean “thought” in coarse consciousness, but which in “elevated consciousness” refer to the subtle function of applying the mind to the meditation. ↩

As a meditator proceeds, their subjective experience of the “body” (kāya) evolves from tactile sense impressions in the “coarse body” of matter (olarikakāya), to the settling of the breath and physical energies in the body and mind (kāyapassaddhi), to the interior mental experience of bliss and light of the “subtle body” (sukhumakāya) or “mind-made body” (manomayakāya), to being a “body witness” (kāyasakkhī) of the formless attainments (MN 70:17.1), to the direct realization of the highest truth of Nibbana “with the body” (MN 70:23.2: kāyena ceva paramasaccaṁ sacchikaroti). Along the way, the sense of “physical body” recedes and kāya refers to direct personal experience. ↩

The kneading is the “placing the mind and keeping it connected”, the water is bliss, while the lack of leaking speaks to the contained interiority of the experience. | Here as elsewhere, water is used as a metaphor for the mind in absorption. Compare Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.3.32: “He becomes like water, one, the seer without duality; this is the world of Brahmā.” ↩

The Buddha has answered Ajātasattu’s question. But he is far from finished. ↩

Each jhāna begins as the least refined aspect of the previous jhāna ends. This is not consciously directed, but describes the natural process of settling. The meditator is now fully confident and no longer needs to apply their mind: it is simply still and fully unified. ↩

The simile emphasizes the water as bliss, while the lack of inflow expresses containment and unification. ↩

The water welling up is the rapture, which is the uplifting emotional response to the experience of bliss. ↩

The emotional response to bliss matures from the subtle thrill of rapture to the poise of equanimity. Mindfulness is present in all states of deep meditation, but with equanimity it becomes prominent. ↩

The meditator is utterly immersed in stillness and bliss. ↩

The emotional poise of equanimity leads to the feeling of pleasure settling into the more subtle neutral feeling. Pain and sadness have been abandoned long before, but are emphasized here as they are subtle counterpart of pleasure. ↩

The equanimity of the fourth jhāna is not dullness and indifference, but a brilliant and radiant awareness. ↩

The white cloth is the purity and brightness of equanimity. The commentary explains this as a person who has just got out of a bath and sits perfectly dry and content. ↩

Of the eight kinds of knowledge and vision, only the last is considered indispensable. The fourth jhāna is the ideal basis for developing higher knowledges, although elsewhere the canon shows that even the first jhāna can be a basis for liberating insight. Without jhāna, however, the eightfold path is incomplete and liberating insight is impossible. | The verb abhininnāmeti (“extend”) indicates that the meditator comes out of full immersion like a tortoise sticking out its limbs (SN 35.240:1.7). ↩

This is the “coarse” (olārika) body. Note that its generation by mother and father contradicts the doctrine of Ajita Kesakambala. The obvious impermanence of the body invites the tempting but fallacious notion that the mind or soul is permanent, which is dispelled by deeper insight. ↩

This distinction should not be mistaken for mind-body dualism. These are not fundamental substances but experiences of a meditator. ↩

Strung gems were loved in India from the time in the Harappan civilization, millennia before the Buddha. ↩

This form of “knowledge and vision” is rarely mentioned, being found only here, at DN 10:2.21.3, and at MN 77:29.2. The next realization, the “mind-made body” is also only found in these three suttas. | The Mahāsaṅgīti edition adds the spurious title vipassanāñāṇa (“insight knowledge”) to this section. This term does not appear anywhere in the Pali canon. ↩

The “mind-made body” is the interior mental representation of the physical body. In ordinary consciousness it is proprioception, which here is enhanced by the power of meditation. The higher powers in Buddhism are regarded as extensions and evolutions of aspects of ordinary experience, not as metaphysical realities separate from the world of mundane experience. ↩

This is similar to the experience of the “astral body” described by modern spiritualists. Note that it is still “physical” (rūpī) even though it is mind-made. This is the subtle (sukhuma) body, which is an energetic experience of physical properties by the mind. ↩

Here begin the “six direct knowledges” (chaḷabhiññā), which are found commonly throughout the early texts. | “Psychic powers” (iddhi) were much cultivated in the Buddha’s day, but the means to acquire them varied: devotion to a god, brutal penances, or magic rituals. The Buddha taught that the mind developed in samādhi was capable of things that are normally incomprehensible. ↩

Only a few of these are attested as events in the early texts. The most common is the ability to “materialize and dematerialize”, exhibited by the Buddha (AN 8.30:2.1), some disciples (MN 37:6.1), and deities (MN 67:8.1). The Pali is āvibhāvaṁ tirobhāvaṁ, literally “manifest state, hidden state”. Also found in Chāndogya Upaniṣad 7.26.1. ↩

These similes hark back to the descriptions of the purified mind as pliable and workable. ↩

This simile is extended in detail at AN 3.101. ↩

“Clairaudience” is a literal rendition of dibbasota. The root sense of dibba is to “shine” like the bright sky or a divine being. The senses of clarity and divinity are both present. ↩

The Buddha occasionally used this ability for teaching, as at MN 75:6.1. ↩

The simile emphasizes the clarity and distinctness of the sounds. Compare AN 4.114: bheripaṇavasaṅkhatiṇavaninnādasaddānaṁ. ↩

Note that the Indic idiom is not the “reading” of minds, which suggests hearing the words spoken in inner dialogue. While this is exhibited by the Buddha (eg. AN 8.30:2.1), the main emphasis is on the comprehension of the overall state of mind. ↩

Again the simile emphasizes how clear and direct the experience is. Without deep meditation, we have some intuitive sense for the minds of others, but it is far from clear. ↩

Here begins the “three knowledges” (tevijjā), a subset of the six direct knowledges. The first two of these play an important role in deepening understanding of the nature of suffering in saṁsāra. While they are not necessary for those whose wisdom is keen, they are helpful. ↩

Empowered by the fourth jhāna, memory breaks through the veil of birth and death, revealing the vast expanse of time and dispelling the illusion that there is any place of eternal rest or sanctuary in the cycle of transmigration. The knowledge of these events is not hazy or murky, but clear and precise, illuminated by the brilliance of purified consciousness. ↩

The word for “past life” is pubbenivāsa, literally “former home”, and the imagery of houses is found in the second of the three knowledges as well. Recollection of past lives is as fresh and clear as the memory of a recent journey. ↩

Here knowledge extends to the rebirths of others as well as oneself. Even more significant, it brings in the understanding of cause and effect; why rebirth happens the way it does. Such knowledge, however, is not infallible, as the Buddha warns in DN 1:2.5.3 and MN 136. The experience is one thing; the inferences drawn from it are another. One should draw conclusions only tentatively, after long experience. | “Clairvoyance” renders dibbacakkhu (“celestial eye”), for which see Chāndogya Upaniṣad 8.12.5, “the mind is (the self’s) celestial eye” (mano’sya daivaṁ cakṣuḥ). ↩

This simile is also found at DN 10:2.33.1. The Majjhima employs a slightly different simile (MN 39:20.3, MN 77:35.2, MN 130:2.1). | Pāsāda is often translated as “palace” or “mansion”, but in early Pali it meant a “stilt longhouse”. As here, it is an elevated place from which one can observe the street below. ↩

This is the experience of awakening that is the true goal of the Buddhist path. The defilements—properties of the mind that create suffering—have been curbed by the practice of ethics and suppressed by the power of jhāna. Here they are eliminated forever. ↩

These are the four noble truths, which form the main content of the Buddha’s first sermon. They are the overarching principle into which all other teachings fall. The initial realization of the four noble truths indicates the first stage of awakening, stream-entry. ↩

The application of the four noble truths to defilements indicates that this is the final stage of awakening, perfection (or “arahantship”, arahatta). | Many translators use “defilement” to render kilesa, but since kilesa appears only rarely in the early texts, I use “defilement” for āsava. Both terms refer to a stain, corruption, or pollution in the mind. ↩

Bhavāsava is the defilement that craves to continue life in a new birth. ↩

This is a reflective awareness of the fact of awakening. The meditator reviews their mind and sees that it is free from all forces that lead to suffering. ↩

This is a standard declaration of full awakening in the suttas, said both of the Buddha and of any arahant (“perfected one”). Each of the four phrases illustrates a cardinal principle of awakening. (1) Further transmigration through rebirths has come to an end due to the exhaustion (khīṇa) of that which propels rebirth, namely deeds motivated by craving. (2) The eightfold path has been developed fully in all respects. (3) All functions relating to the four noble truths have been completed, namely: understanding suffering, letting go craving, witnessing extinguishment, and developing the path. (4) Extinguishment is final, with no falling back to this or any other state of existence. | For “state of existence” (literally “thusness”, itthatta), see DN 15:21.4. ↩

Once again the pool of water represents the mind, but now the meditator is not immersed in the experience, but looks back and reviews it objectively. ↩

The Buddha roars his lion’s roar. His teaching leads not just to some benefits, but to the highest benefits that are possible. ↩

The king’s distress has been alleviated by the Buddha’s uplifting words. ↩

This is the standard form in which lay people went for refuge. It is not something that the Buddha required, but a spontaneous act of inspiration. Conventionally, it indicates that someone is a “Buddhist”. Today Theravadins recite the going for refuge thrice, but in the early texts this is found only as the ordination for novices (Kd 1:12.4.1). ↩

The king, unprompted, makes an astonishing confession. To say it in such a public forum, before a spiritual community and his own retinue, displays courage and integrity. ↩

The Buddha hears his confession, but it is Ajātasattu’s responsibility to do better. ↩

Even before such a dangerous and emotionally volatile king, the Buddha does not mince words. The Buddha makes a point to acknowledge what the king had done, without dismissing it and thereby discounting the inner work he had achieved to get to this point. ↩

Confession does not erase the past, but it does set a better course for the future. This confession is similar to that done by monastics when they have broken Vinaya rules. ↩

These terms are commonly used in the context of keeping precepts (eg. AN 3.50:4.1). The Buddha is supportive when he speaks with Ajātasattu, but does not hide the severity of his crime. ↩

The killing of one’s father is one of five “incurable” acts that doom a person to hell in the next life (AN 5.129:1.3). If he had not done so, he would have become a stream-enterer. ↩

This sutta marks a turning point where the Buddha’s teachings were embraced by the leading brahmin Pokkharasāti. The suttas that follow reverberate with the consequences of this encounter. He was one of the most influential brahmins of his time, although the Buddha elsewhere denied that he had any special knowledge (MN 99:15.5). Brahmanical texts confirm that he was a real person, an influential teacher around the time of the Buddha known as Pauṣkarasādi in Sanskrit. He is cited on grammar by Kātyāyana and Patañjali, and in the Taittirīya-prātiśākhya; on allowable food and theft in the Āpastamba Dharmasūtra; and on Vedic ritual in the Śāṅkhāyana-Āraṇyaka. His name identifies him as descended from a man of Puṣkarāvati, capital of Gandhāra. MN 99:10.3 clarifies that he is of the Upamañña lineage. ↩

Icchānaṅgala was a center east of Sāvatthī for the innovative brahmins of the Kosala region. ↩

Ukkaṭṭhā is mentioned only rarely, and always in the context of extraordinary teachings and events that emphasize the cosmic grandeur of the Buddha against the brahmins (DN 14:3.29.1, MN 1:1.2, MN 49:2.1). Sanskrit sources call it a droṇamukha, a leading market town accessible by land and water (Divyāvadāna 319.010). At MN 99:10.3 Pokkharasāti is said to be “of the Subhaga Forest”. | “Royal park” is rājadāya (cp. migadāya, “deer park”). | A brahmadeyya is a gift of land by a king to a brahmin, which was an outstanding feature of Indian feudalism. ↩

Contrast with his rejection of this possibility at MN 99:10.7. ↩

Pokkharasāti does not care whether the Buddha identified as a follower of the Vedas. The wise do not concern themselves with religious identity. ↩

“Vocabularies” is nighaṇḍu (Sanskrit nighaṇṭu), known from the Nirukta of Yāska. | Keṭubha lacks an obvious Sanskrit form. The commentary explains, “The study of proper and improper actions for the assistance of poets.” This suggests a connection with ritual performance, which is the special area of the Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa. There we often find phrases such as kṛtam bhavati, “it is performed”, of which keṭubha is perhaps a contraction. | Akkhara (literally “syllable”) is explained by the commentary as sikkhā (Sanskrit śikṣā), which is the study of pronunciation. This can be traced back to Pāṇinī, and is sometimes referred to as akṣara-samāmnāya, “collation of syllables”. | Pabheda is found in Buddhist Sanskrit texts as padaprabheda, “classification of words”, such as into the different parts of speech. The commentary identifies it with nirutti. | Padaka is one skilled in the padapāṭha recitation of Vedas, which separates the individual words. | For “testaments” (itihāsa) see itihāsa-purāṇa in Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 11.5.6.8, explained by the commentator there as legends of creation and olden times (see also Chāndogya Upaniṣad 7.1.4). | For “cosmology” (lokāyata), see note on DN 1:1.25.2. | For “authorized as a master” (anuññātapaṭiññāta) see MN 98:7.1 and Snp 3.9:6.1. | For “scriptural heritage of the three Vedas” (tevijjake pāvacane) see MN 95:12.2. ↩

Almost the same words are spoken to the bodhisatta by his first teachers, Āḷāra Kālāma and Uddaka Rāmaputta (MN 36:14.9). This connects Pokkharasāti with Āḷāra Kālāma and Uddaka Rāmaputta, and suggests that the anointing of a talented student in this way was a regular practice of wise brahmins. ↩

Following PTS and BJT editions of the parallel phrase at MN 91:4.9, which read tayā for tathā. ↩

The thirty-two marks are detailed in DN 14:1.32.7, DN 30:1.2.4, and MN 91:9.1. In Buddhist texts they are presented as the fulfillment of Brahmanical prophecy, but they are not found in any Brahmanical texts of the Buddha’s time. However, later astrological texts such as the Gārgīyajyotiṣa (1st century BCE?) and Bṛhatsaṁhitā (6th century CE?) contain references to many of these marks, albeit in a different context, so it seems likely the Buddhist texts are drawing on now-lost Brahmanical scriptures. | The notion of a two-fold course for a great hero—worldly success or spiritual—can be traced back as far as the epic of Gilgamesh. ↩

The idea of the wheel-turning monarch draws from the Vedic horse sacrifice, which establishes the authority of a king from sea to sea. The Buddhist telling is divested of all coarse and violent elements. The wheeled chariot gave military supremacy to the ancient Indo-Europeans, allowing them to spread from their ancient homeland north of the Black Sea. In Buddhism, the wheel, which also has solar connotations, symbolizes unstoppable power. For a legendary account of such a king, see the Mahāsudassanasutta (DN 17). Rig Veda 8.63.8 speaks of Indra as the “wheel turner”. ↩

The sacrificial horse on its journey across the land is protected by a hundred sons. ↩

The relation between Pokkharasāti and Ambaṭṭha is similar to that between the Buddha and his followers. They share the same understanding, but the Buddha is distinguished as the teacher. ↩

In this sutta, māṇava is always applied to Ambaṭṭha and māṇavaka to the rest. It seems that the diminutive māṇavaka means “young student”. | There are said to be sambahula students, a word that is often translated as “many”. But later we see that they all fit inside the Buddha’s hut, so the sense must be “several”. ↩

This is the practice of walking meditation. Meditators pace mindfully up and down a smooth path, keeping attention on their body. ↩

Bho is a respectful term of address used by brahmins. The forms of address used in Pali are complex, and it is rarely possible to map them to modern English with any precision. ↩

The parallel passage at MN 35:7.4 has a different phrase here. ↩

The term kulaputta (literally, “son of a family”) typically refers to someone from a well-to-do or respected family, a “gentleman”. It is a gendered term which assumes the social status of men. ↩

The introduction has told us that the Buddha was staying in a forest at this time. Nonetheless, this was not a wilderness, but was developed enough to have huts with latched doors. ↩

The Buddha draws attention to Ambaṭṭha’s rude behavior. Throughout the suttas, the manner in which people greet the Buddha gives us a hint as to their attitudes and qualities. ↩

Note the racial connotations of using kaṇha (“black”) as a slur. The brahmin caste hailed from the (relatively) fair-skinned Indo-Europeans who entered India from the north. Vedic texts indicate that there was Brahmanical prejudice against dark-skinned natives, but also that they were assimilated and raised to positions of honor. ↩

Ambaṭṭha is “qualified” (vusita) in scripture, but far from “qualified” in spiritual development. Vusita is normally an expression of arahantship: vusitaṁ brahmacariyaṁ (“the spiritual journey has been completed”). ↩

The PTS reading rabhasa means “violent, aggressive”. But the commentary reads bhassa, explained as “speaking much”. Moreover, the story below does not demonstrate violence. ↩

Ambaṭṭha despises the Sakyans as “primitives” (ibbha) who do not respect Vedic culture. The word ibbha (“primitive”) stems from a non-Aryan word for “elephant” (ibha); the sub-commentary glosses it with hatthigopakā (“elephant-keepers”). It originally referred to the native inhabitants who tamed elephants; see eg. Chāndogya Upaniṣad 1.10. At Snp 3.1:18.4 the Buddha describes his own people as “natives” (niketino), those who have a long connection with the land. ↩

The Buddha’s use of āyasmā is noteworthy here: he is taking a conciliatory tone. ↩

The Ambaṭṭhas were a people in the north-west of greater India (eg. Mahābhārata 7.4.5c, 7.132.23a). They were evidently the Abastanians whose rout at the hands of Alexander is recorded by Arrian (The Anabasis of Alexander, chapter 15). They were probably located near what is today the northern Sindh province in Pakistan. Later texts such as Manusmṛti 1.8 say that an ambaṣṭha is born of a brahmin father and vaiśya mother. ↩

Kaṇhāyana means “descendant of the dark one (kaṇha)”. Since no clan of that name is attested it is perhaps a confusion with the Kāṇvāyanas of Rig Veda 8.55.4. But the confusion, if it is such, has an old history, for Rig Veda 1.117.8 refers to “Dark Kaṇva” (Śyāva Kaṇva). ↩

Normally I take ayyaputta as a simple honorific, but here the sense is not that the Sakyans were the masters, but were descended from them. ↩

Okkāka (Sanskrit Ikṣvāku) was the legendary son of the first man, Manu, and the founder of the solar dynasty of Kosala. It is a Munda name, which may be associated with the introduction of cane sugar (ikṣuḥ) from eastern Asia, a theory endorsed by the 9th century Jain scholar Jinasena (Natubhai Shah, Jainism, the World of Conquerors, 2004, vol. 1, pg. 15). ↩

The words for “teak” (sāka) and “sal” (sāla) have evidently been confused from the Munda root sarja (both appear at MN 93:11.6). But teak does not grow so far north, so the sal must be meant here. To maintain the pun I use sakhua, which is an alternate Hindi name for the sal tree. This story suggests that when they settled in their northern home in the shadow of the Himalayas, harvesting sal was a primary source of wealth. Compare Gilgamesh, for whom Lebanese cedar was the foundation of his royal capital. ↩

“Own” is saka, the second pun on the Sakyan name. Incest is, of course, common among royal families for exactly the reason stated here. Marriage between cousins persisted even in the Buddha’s day. | For sambheda in the sense of “dissolving, leaking”, see AN 2.9:1.5 = DN 26:20.2, AN 5.103:6.4, AN 10.45:4.1. ↩

For this sense of sammati, see SN 11.9, SN 11.10. ↩

This draws on both the puns above. But the commentary also explains sakya here as “capable” (samatthā, paṭibalā) in reference to their survival against all odds, thus connecting Sakya with sakka (“able”). ↩

Vedic dāsa (“slave, bondservant”) refers to the “dark-wombed” (kṛṣṇayoni, Rig Veda 2.20.7) foes of the Aryan peoples (Rig Veda 10.22.8) who upon defeat were enslaved (Rig Veda 10.62.10). The name disā therefore probably means “foe” (Sanskrit dviṣa). ↩

The passage wavers between treating kaṇha (Sanskrit kṛṣṇa, i.e. Krishna) as a personal name, a description, and a word for a goblin. I try to capture this ambiguity by using variations of “black boy”. | The passage does not say who the father was. According to Arthaśāstra 3.13, a female slave is protected against sexual harassment by the master, but should she have a child by him, both mother and child are to be set free, and if the sex was not consensual, he must pay her a fine. ↩

Like Siddhattha, he spoke as soon as he was born. The boy was no common child, but had a larger destiny. His words are a dramatic contrast with Siddhattha’s words of confident proclamation, and his birth which was devoid of filth or impurity. ↩

Lineage was important to brahmins, but the Brāhmaṇa and Upaniṣad literature shows that, as here, many were more concerned with conduct and wisdom than with birth. ↩

The threat of losing one’s head is found at eg. Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.3.24, or at 3.9.26 when it actually did fall off. I cannot trace the detail of heads being split in seven to any early Sanskrit texts, but it is found in later texts such as Rāmāyaṇa 7.26.44c and Mahābhārata 14.7.2c. ↩

Vajirapāṇī (“lightning-bolt in hand”) appears here and in the parallel passage at MN 35:14.1. The synonymous Vajrahasta (Pali vajirahattha, DN 20:12.1) is a frequent epithet of Indra in the Vedas (eg. Rig Veda 1.173.10a: indro vajrahastaḥ), confirming the commentary’s identification with Sakka. Much later, Mahayana texts adopted the name for a fierce Bodhisattva who was protector of the Dhamma. ↩

The contemptuous senses of “black boy” represent the conservative brahmanical view, presented not as endorsement, but as a rhetorical means to undermine Ambaṭṭha’s pride. The Buddha now shows how a man of a supposedly low birth rose to great spiritual eminence. ↩

“Divine Spell” is brahmamanta, a term also found in the commentary to the Morajātaka (Ja 159), where it refers to a verse which, in Vedic style, worships the sun as the “one king”. In modern Hinduism it is used for a verse of praise for Brahmā. | Kaṇha is one of several “dark hermits” who accrued mighty and lineage-busting powers in the south. ↩

The Hindu deity Krishna won the hand of his seventh wife Lakṣmaṇā, also known as Madrī, at an archery contest. This detail is too precise to be a coincidence, and proves there must be some shared basis between the two figures. ↩

This draws on the ancient belief that the king’s acts affect the natural order of things. ↩

This sequence seems to be an etiological myth explaining certain rites of kingship and succession, providing an origin story for this prayer. ↩

National prosperity is ensured through symbolic regicide. This example was omitted from Frazer’s accounts of such substitute sacrifices in the Golden Bough. Here there is a double substitution: the prince substitutes for the king, then a threat substitutes for the act of killing. This suggests that, even from the legendary perspective of this story within a story, the rite was an ancient one that had evolved through multiple stages. ↩

The use of the bare personal name for the king is unusual. ↩

“Divine punishment” is brahmadaṇḍa, harking back to the Divine Spell (brahmamantra). The Buddha had his own version of the brahmadaṇḍa, which was to give the silent treatment (DN 16:6.4.1). ↩

In MN 56:19.2 āvaṭa/anāvaṭa is used in reference to Upāli “shutting his gate” against the Jains and opening it for the Buddhists. In DN 17:1.23.2 anāvaṭa means “open to the public”. ↩

Sanaṅkumāra (“Everyoung”) became a Hindu deity closely associated with the worship of Krishna. He first appears in the seventh chapter of the Chāndogya Upaniṣad. There he teaches the learned Nārada what lies beyond the mere surface of words (nāma) by giving a progressive meditation that ultimately reveals the highest Self. Thus he is a perfect foil for Ambaṭṭha. The occasion he spoke this verse is recorded at SN 6.11, and it is repeated several times in the suttas. ↩

To his credit, after that thorough humiliation, Ambaṭṭha is ready to learn. ↩

Reading anuttarāya vijjācaraṇasampadāya as locative, in agreement with yattha below. ↩

The Buddha emphasizes that his “knowledge and conduct” rejects the notion of birth that is so essential to Brahmanism. ↩

The Pali text abbreviates the gradual training in this sutta and those that follow. The reader is expected to understand it as in DN 2. Note, however, that the suttas sometimes have small differences in their perspective that make reconstruction tricky. ↩

In later Theravada, apāyamukha refers to deeds that cause rebirth in lower realms. However this does not apply in the early texts; the acts described here are not evil. Rather, it means an “opening” (mukha) for “departure” (apāya). ↩

A common practice of pre-Buddhist hermits, who avoided the slightest harm to plants. Buddhist mendicants may also not harm plants, but they rely on alms and only eat fallen fruit in case of famine. ↩

The Buddha inverts Ambaṭṭha’s earlier claim that the other three castes only succeed in serving brahmins (DN 3:1.14.7). ↩

They are less strict than the previous ascetics, for they dig the soil and harm the plants. ↩

The “fire chamber” was a building set up for performing the fire ritual. The Buddha stayed in them from time to time (MN 75:1.2, Kd 1:15.2.2). Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 13.4.1.8 describes how a king enters the fire chamber to spend the night with his wives, the king entering by the east door, the wives by the south. Kauṭilya says that a king should try religious cases there (Arthaśāstra 1.19.31). ↩

“Denomination” renders sācariyaka, literally “that which stems from one’s own tutor”. It is a term for one’s own particular religious or philosophical denomination. ↩

This practice is not elsewhere attested in early Pali. ↩

Ugga is a rare word whose root sense is “mighty”, but here it must be a noun. Given that it is a military man who consults with the king, I translate as “warrior-chief”. | Rājañña is used occasionally in the suttas; it is an archaic synonym for khattiya. ↩

Taking this and the next as one sentence, despite the punctuation of the Mahāsaṅgīti text. ↩

The “hymns” (mantā) are the verses of the Rig Veda. The ten names here all correspond with Vedic authors according to the Brahmanical tradition (for details, see note on DN 13:13.1). Note that in Sanskrit the names of the rishis are distinguished from the lineage holders, which take the patronymic. For example, Bharadvāja is the rishi, the Bhāradvājas are his descendants; Vasiṣṭha is the rishi, the Vāsiṣṭhas are his descendants. Pali texts do not make this distinction, but use the patronymic, although the two forms are not always readily distinguishable. | “Seer” is isi (Sanskrit ṛṣi), for which the Proto-Dravidian root icai (“sing”) has been proposed. It was taken to mean that they had “seen” the Vedas (mantradraṣṭa) or directly “heard” them from Brahmā through divine inspiration, rather than “composing” them like ordinary authors. Here, however, the Buddha says they were “authors” (kattāro). The Buddha adopted isi in the sense “enlightened sage”. ↩

Veṭhakanatapassāhi is otherwise unattested. At MN 55:12.4 veṭhaka evidently means “collar”. In the Lokuttaravāda Bhikṣuṇī Vinaya, the brazen nun Thullānandā gets out of the water and wraps herself in a veṭhaka, which here seems synonymous with paṭṭaka, a strip of cloth. It is allowable if used to tie a basket (Lo Bi Pn 3). Nata is “curve”, passa is “side, flank”. Walshe has “flounces and furbelows”, Rhys Davids has “fringes and furbelows round their loins”. These are prissy descriptions of what is evidently stripper gear. ↩

The Buddha calls back to earlier in the sutta, where Ambaṭṭha drove a mare-drawn chariot (DN 3:1.6.1). | The verbs here (vitudenti vitacchenti) are elsewhere applied to the pecking and slashing of vultures, crows, or hawks (SN 19.1:3.2, MN 54:16.2, etc.). The Buddha was disgusted with this maltreatment of the mares. ↩

Remembering that Pokkharasāti lived in a wealthy property that was a royal endowment. Just as today, excessive wealth breeds insecurity. ↩

The Buddha has been hard on Ambaṭṭha, but he is not unfair. He invites the same level of scrutiny for himself. ↩

This transition occurs nowhere else. ↩

Finally he remembers what his teacher Pokkharasāti told him in DN 3:1.5.2: he will know the Buddha by his marks. ↩

This exceedingly strange “miracle” is also found at MN 91:7.1, MN 92:14.1, and Snp 3.7:11.5. ↩

The diminutive ending for paṇḍitaka is the same as in samaṇaka, which Ambaṭṭha used of the Buddha. | For re (“bloody”), compare cara pi re at Bu Pc 70:1.35 and he je kāḷī at MN 21:9.13. Hard as the Buddha was on Ambaṭṭha, his own teacher was harder. ↩

Pokkharasāti shows his astuteness, for in many other dialogues the Buddha engaged with brahmins perfectly politely, as he does in the next sutta (DN 4). ↩

Illustrating the lack of restraint of even a senior brahmin teacher. ↩

Given Pokkharasāti’s mood, this was probably a diplomatic move. ↩

Khādanīya and bhojanīya are food categories commonly mentioned in Pali. Etymologically they stem from “hard and soft”. Bhojanīya is defined in Bu Pc 37:2.1.10 as grain, porridge, flour products, fish, and meat, thus being foods that are typically eaten cooked and “mooshed up” in with the fingers in the bowl. Khādanīya is not so readily defined, being essentially everything not included in other categories. But it would have included such “crunchy” things as fruit and vegetables, which may be eaten uncooked. ↩

Pokkharasāti makes sure he hears both sides of the story. ↩

So far has Ambaṭṭha fallen from the learned sage we were introduced to at the start of the sutta. ↩

The Buddha bears no ill will. Sukhī hotu is one of the most recognizable Pali phrases, but in early texts it is spoken only a few times: by the Buddha at DN 21:1.8.8 and Snp 5.1:54.1; by Punabbasu’s Mother at SN 10.7:10.1; and by various women at Bu Ss 5:1.4.8. ↩

“Robed up” because inside the monastery, monks would normally wear just a lower robe, and would don the upper and (sometimes) outer robes when visiting a layperson’s home. ↩

While all these teachings feature commonly in the suttas, there is no text that depicts this framework in detail. ↩

This is the briefest expression of the four noble truths. ↩

This indicates that he became a stream-enterer (sotāpanna), the first of four stages of Awakening. Such details of personal attainment are typically found in the narrative rather than the teaching attributed to the Buddha, and hence were added by redactors at some point. They vary considerably in different versions. In this case, the parallel at DA 20 says that he became a stream-enterer and later a non-returner. T 20 said that he understood the teaching and went for refuge, and agrees that he became a non-returner before his death. ↩

This is the insight into universal impermanence and dependent origination. ↩

When wandering for alms, mendicants would often roam randomly through the village (sapadānacārī). However if an invitation such as this were issued, the mendicant may visit that place for a meal. It was considered a special ascetic practice to refuse such invitations. The same invitation was issued by Lohicca to Mahākaccāna at SN 35.132:14.7. ↩

Māṇavikā is also mentioned at MN 56:27.1 and Ud 2.6:1.3 of a young married woman; and at AN 5.192:8.5 of a baby being born. Thus it does not seem that it meant “female student of the Vedas”. ↩

Kalyāṇaṁ vuccati is a politely ambiguous phrase. It is spoken twice elsewhere in the Pali, and both times the mendicant who said it immediately departed and never returned (SN 41.3:7.13, SN 41.4:6.7). ↩

This sutta shows how the conversion of Pokkharasāti in DN 3 affected the brahmins as far away as Campā. ↩

Campā is modern Champapuri near Bhagalpur in Bihar state, not far from West Bengal. It is near the eastern-most reach of the Buddha’s journeys. Campā was the capital of Aṅga, one of the sixteen “great nations” (mahājanapadā). It was a flourishing trade center at which Northern Black Polished Ware has been found, and became a sacred city for the Jains. ↩

Gaggarā, an onomatopoeic reduplication (“gargle”), is the name of a number of rivers and whirlpools in Sanskrit (cp. the modern Ghaggar River in north-west India). ↩

Here we see how the endowment of brahmadeyya helped the king of Magadha establish his influence over the Aṅgas. ↩

“Householders” (gahapati) is literal; it means land owners. Thus the “brahmins and householders” (not “brahmin householders”) were the wealthy class. ↩

Both the repetition below and the parallel at MN 95:8.3 include the phrase “it’s appropriate that he comes to see you”. It may have been omitted here by mistake. ↩

Jātivāda is sometimes translated as “doctrine of birth”, but the context here shows this cannot be the case. It refers to the genealogical records of the family lineage. ↩

Brahmavarcasa (“divine lustre”) commonly describes a spiritual or ethereal beauty due to ritual (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 13.1.9, 2.3.1, 4.1.1), or simply the healthy glow from time in the sun, which if overdone leads to sunburn (eg. Taittirīya Saṁhita 2.10.2). Brahmavarṇa (“divine looks”), on the other hand, seems unknown in the Vedic tradition. | For Mahāsaṅgīti vacchasī read vaccasī (Sanskrit varcasin), “possessing lustre”. ↩

Notice that the royal endowment was not just for a luxury residence, it was the site of a major international college. Kings invested in education. ↩

Later tradition says that the young Siddhattha sneaked out of his home to avoid creating such a scene, but the early texts say he left despite his parents’ weeping. ↩

In contrast with some of the other ascetics in DN 2. ↩

This description is applied to the Buddha at DN 5:7.24, and to the corrupt but superficially charming monks Assaji and Punabbasuka at Bu Ss 13:1.3.4. ↩

This would be the assemblies of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, and ascetics (AN 5.213:3.1), rather than the Buddha’s four assemblies of monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen (DN 16:5.16.3, AN 4.129). ↩

Titthakara, literally “ford-maker”, is a term restricted to those such as the Buddha who founded a religion, or Mahāvīra who was a major reformer on the same level as a founder. ↩

Bimbisāra’s refuge is at Kd 1:22.11.4. ↩

Pasenadi’s refuge is at SN 3.1:14.5. ↩

This sutta must have been before the events of DN 2, but after those of DN 3. ↩

“Knapsack” is puṭosa, where puṭa is “bag” and osa is “food” (Sanskrit avasa). The compound is a dative-dependent tappurisa with reversal of the usual order, yielding the sense “bag for food”. ↩

Even before he meets him, Soṇadaṇḍa has extensive knowledge of the Buddha and faith in him. It’s also notable how Soṇadaṇḍa gives Pokkharasāti a special status. Perhaps Pokkharasāti told Soṇadaṇḍa of the encounter with Ambaṭṭha in DN 3, which would explain his hesitation. | Note the use of the term yoniso here, which I render “rational”. The basic meaning of the term is “womb, source”, and it is used to mean “with reason”, which here has the sense “pertinent, relevant”. ↩

For all his previous avowal of faith, Soṇadaṇḍa is merely polite, not reverential. This foreshadows the ending. ↩

This stock passage indicates different attitudes toward the Buddha, and perhaps also different social status. Examples of such behaviors are given in Dharmaśāstras. While they might not exactly apply to this situation, they do indicate that these behaviors were nuanced and deliberate. Here is an example: “One should rise to greet a sacrificial priest, father-in-law, paternal uncle, or maternal uncle who is younger than oneself, but not verbally salute him. Likewise, one should rise to greet, but not verbally salute a different fellow-citizen who is older than oneself—even a Śūdra provided he is at least eighty—if one is equal in age to his son. And a Śūdra should rise to greet, but not verbally salute an Ārya, even if he is younger than himself.” (Gautama 6.9–11, translation David Brick). ↩

The Buddha goes out of his way to make him comfortable. Soṇadaṇḍa is nervous and overly eager to please, but he is not contemptuous and grinding a personal axe like Ambaṭṭha. ↩

Suja (Sanskrit sruc) was a large wooden ladle for pouring ghee on to the sacred flame. ↩

The Buddha uses “Socratic method”. He has the other person articulate a view, then leads them to refine their view, leading to a clearer vision of the truth. ↩

When the Buddha convinces Soṇadaṇḍa, he does not crow over it or take pleasure in his discomfort, but praises his wisdom and affirms his conclusions. ↩

The Buddha has taken pains to establish common ground, but Soṇadaṇḍa’s description of wisdom is lacking, so the Buddha prompts a deeper inquiry. ↩

Normally, the Buddha frames his teaching as ethics, meditation, and wisdom, but here he adapts to Soṇadaṇḍa’s framing and places meditation under wisdom. ↩

Soṇadaṇḍa’s attachment to his reputation betrays his lack of inner confidence and stands in contrast with Pokkharasāti. Perhaps it may also be read as a regional characteristic, since Buddhism was less well established in the Aṅga region than in central Magadha. ↩

When asked about sacrifice, the Buddha tells a story of how a king was persuaded to forgo cruelty and institute a constructive social policy of welfare instead. ↩

Khāṇumata is only mentioned here. It means “stumpy”, perhaps indicating that it was, or had recently been, a rough out-of-the-way place. ↩

The commentary says this was similar to the Ambalaṭṭhikā of DN 1:1.2.1. ↩

Like the town Khāṇumata, the brahmin Kūṭadanta appears only here. His name means “pointy teeth”, but there is no evidence that he was a vampire. ↩

At Snp 2.7:26.1, the sacrifice of cows in particular was said to be the nadir of decline for brahmins. When similar sacrifices are described elsewhere in the canon, the number is five hundred rather than seven hundred (SN 3.9:1.2, AN 7.47:1.2). ↩

News of the Buddha had spread in Brahmanical circles. In DN 3 we saw the Buddha use his rhetorical technique of adapting his teaching to reframe Brahmanical doctrines in order to establish a common ground. Here we see the downside to such techniques, as the details of the reframing have been lost. ↩

No such sacrifice has been identified in Brahmanical texts. ↩

Kūṭadanta’s proposal that the Buddha advise him on the sacrifice of 700 animals is outrageous. Nonetheless, the Buddha responds politely since Kūṭadanta is being polite. While it is tempting to see the sacrifice of animals by supposedly virtuous priests as sheer hypocrisy, the fact of sacrifice remains one of the most widespread and mysterious of human religious practices. In an empathetic work that addresses this squarely, Roberto Calasso’s Ardor sees the vast complex of Vedic ritual and theory as making plain the fact of killing so that the guilt may be contained, in contrast with our modern culture of killing on an industrial scale while hiding it out of sight. ↩

Mahāvijita means “Great Dominion”. He seems to be only known from this story. The idiom bhūtapubbaṁ (literally “so it was in the past”) introduces legendary narratives of usually dubious historicity, like the English idiom “once upon a time”. ↩

In the Pali, meaningful thoughts often occur to people when withdrawn in seclusion. This doesn’t necessary mean they were in formal meditation. ↩

The great sacrifices, especially the horse sacrifice, ensured royal authority. Their very scale and wastefulness showed off the wealth of the king. ↩

“High priest” is purohita. He was a family chaplain advising and consecrating the royal family. The closeness of the relationship is shown by the fact that the royal family would take the lineage name of the purohita. ↩

Then, as today, government policy was driven by the perception of rising crime rate. This whole passage is one of the Buddha’s most important statements on public policy. It is expressed through storytelling, giving a good example of how myths were invoked—and subverted—as rationales for current policy. ↩

“Taxes” is bali. He would have had to press his people for the extra funds to hold the sacrifice. ↩

“Plague of savages” (dassukhīla) is the only occurrence of Sanskrit dasyu in early Pali. The dasyu were inveterate foes of the Aryans in the Vedic period. Bereft of civilizing rites, scriptures, and observances, they were no children of Manu (Rig Veda 10.22.8). Their wiles (māyā) made them a potent threat (Rig Veda 4.16.9, 8.14.14, 10.73.5). Indra was invoked to ensure their destruction (Rig Veda passim; Atharva Veda 2.14.5, 4.32.3, 20.21.4, 20.37.5, 20.42.2). Legend has it that Agni and Soma first supported the dasyu before being won over by Indra (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 1.6.3.13; see also 6.4.2.4). By the time of the Buddha the dasyu have vanished except as a legendary foe of the past. Where the Brahmanical texts advocate the pitiless destruction of the dasyu, the brahmin high priest in the Buddhist text advocates an inclusive policy of social welfare. ↩

The priest knows that the king will respond better to a pragmatic argument than a moral one. ↩

Effective social policy requires a forward-thinking plan, not just reacting to grievances. ↩

The king should spend his own resources to support his citizens in the various occupations. ↩

Here the priest identifies a fundamental cause of social unrest and disorder. ↩

The king spends out of pocket, but the economy flourishes, so tax revenues increase even though he has not raised taxes. This is the essence of Keynesian economic theory. ↩

Khema means a place of safety and sanctuary, where both humans and animals have no fear. ↩

A good leader listens to advice. ↩

Here the phrase “of both town and country” qualifies each group. At AN 4.70:1.3, however, “brahmins and householders” and “people of town and country” are separate groups of people. Elsewhere the context does not always decide between these two possibilities. Generally the idiom aims at inclusivity, as opposed to here where the king is consulting the rich and powerful, so I treat them as two separate groups, thus including the common folk. ↩

“Consenting factions” is anumatipakkhā. The king governs with the consent of his people, although only the landowning classes are considered. ↩

Royal authority is not based just on birth, conquest, ritual, or power, but on quality of character. ↩

Read sahati (“prevails”) over the several variants. ↩

Showing the importance of comprehension over blind adherence to tradition. ↩

Meditators focus on the present, but that does not mean they cannot think about the past or future; it just means they are not trapped in useless thoughts. ↩

These are four of the five qualities that Soṇadaṇḍa identifies as the qualities of a brahmin at DN 4:13.2. Missing is appearance, which is the first factor that Soṇadaṇḍa admits is unnecessary. ↩

Compare the three factors of a donor’s mind-state at AN 6.37:2.4. ↩

What a recipient does with a gift is beyond the donor’s control. ↩

PTS edition acknowledges sajjata only as a variant reading, but it is in the commentary, so should be accepted in the text. It is from √sajj (relinquish). ↩

Another lesson in leadership: the importance of communication. ↩

Due to abbreviation, the text only mentions householders here, but clearly all are intended. ↩

A leader gets results through inspiration, not fear. ↩

These were regarded as valuable yet harmless products. ↩

The king’s generosity and sincerity brings out the best in the others. ↩

Here ends the Buddha’s legendary account of the past. ↩

The other brahmins are satisfied, but Kūṭadanta senses there is more to it. ↩

“So I have heard” (evaṁ me sutaṁ) is the standard opening for Buddhist suttas. This tag was used to indicate that the speaker was not present at the events, but “heard” about them. This is in contrast with the phrase “I heard and learned this in the presence” (sammukhā sutaṁ, sammukhā paṭiggahitaṁ), which is used when reporting a teaching heard directly from the Buddha (SN 55.52:5.1, SN 22.90:9.1, MN 47:10.7, etc.) ↩

This qualifies the story of Mahāvijita as an early canonical Jātaka. There are a small number of such stories in the early suttas, only some of which overlap with the later Jātaka collections, the story of Mahāvijita not being among them. ↩

Kūṭadanta is hoping for a better return on his investment. Throughout the suttas, we find a strain of what might be called “spiritual economics”. ↩

The anukula (“propitious”) sacrifice is mentioned several times (eg. DN 5:22.4, AN 4.40:2.2). The Pali commentaries interpret it as “in line with (anu-) family (kula)”. But nothing in the contexts connects it with family customs, nor is such a term known in Sanskrit. It seems rather to be a misunderstanding of Sanskrit anukūla, literally “along the riverbank”, and in applied use, “in conformity with”, “favorable to”, as in the favor of the gods. This is the standard reading in Buddhist Sanskrit. Such a sacrifice is characterized, not by family custom, but by harmlessness. Thus anukula means “propitious, favored (by the gods and the Dhamma)”. ↩

This contradicts the description given above. ↩

This means that the dwelling could be used by any Saṅgha member, as opposed to being given to a particular monastic or group. The gift of a dwelling is regarded as the best kind of offering to the Saṅgha. ↩

Thus far the Buddha has described the regular practice of a Buddhist lay person. ↩

The entire path may be described as a “sacrifice”. ↩

Releasing animals remains a Buddhist practice today. ↩

Lying some 60 kilometers north of Pāṭaliputra (Patna), Vesālī was the largest city in the Vajji Federation, a republican league in the region north of the Ganges. ↩

In the earlier suttas of this chapter, we have seen how news of the Buddha spread, evidently following Pokkharasāti’s conversion. Here we see an example of the kind of meeting at which such news would be discussed. | The phrase “brahmin emissaries” (brāhmaṇadūtā) does not seem to occur elsewhere and is not explained in the commentary. Perhaps they were emissaries of the kings, meeting in a neutral location. Or perhaps they were emissaries of their respective communities of brahmins. ↩

This monastery features prominently as the Buddha’s usual place of residence near Vesālī. ↩

At some times the Buddha would go on retreat and ask that no one visit him except to bring food; this sometimes happened at the Great Wood (SN 54.9:2.1). He also had the habit of withdrawing into the wood itself for meditation (AN 5.58:1.3). At this time, however, he was simply staying in a nearby hut, so it seems Nāgita is being over-zealous. ↩

Oṭṭhaddha mean “hare-lip” and is evidently a nickname or epithet. Throughout, the Buddha refers to him by his personal name, Mahāli. And it is under that name we meet him again in SN 11.13, SN 22.60, and AN 10.47. | The Licchavis, whose name is derived from “bear”, dominated the Vajji Federation. Note that the Mahāsaṅgīti edition here spells the masculine singular as licchavī, whereas normally it is licchavi. ↩

This Sīha is unknown elsewhere. ↩

Kassapa is Nāgita’s clan name; either he was a brahmin or a khattiya whose family chaplain (purohita) was a Kassapa. ↩

In trying to protect the Buddha, Nāgita was inflexible and lacking compassion. When given good advice by Sīha, he responded gracelessly, fobbing off responsibility to a junior. No wonder he was replaced by Ānanda. ↩

This is still a common place for forest monks to receive guests. ↩

This is the last we hear of these emissaries. ↩

Sunakkhatta features in several suttas, through which his journey may be traced. In MN 105 he meets the Buddha and gains faith; here in DN 6 he is becoming dissatisfied; in DN 24 he rejects the Buddha; and in MN 12 he attacks the Buddha after disrobing. ↩

This refers to “clairvoyance” and “clairaudience”, sometimes translated as the “divine eye” and “divine ear”. Despite being included in the Gradual Training, they are not a goal of Buddhist practice. Rather, they are unnecessary but potentially useful, as they reveal dimensions of being inaccessible to ordinary consciousness. Sunakkhatta, however, was evidently just interested in having pleasant supersensory experiences. ↩

This must have wounded his pride. ↩

This description of meditation is unique in the Pali canon. The Buddha answers Mahāli’s question directly, even though the premise betrays Sunakkhatta’s limited understanding. When a questioner is sincere, answering directly shows respect and builds trust. ↩

Having directly answered the original question, the Buddha reframed the issue on request. ↩

This is the first description of the four stages of awakening which are featured throughout the Pali canon. The three fetters are identity view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances (MN 2:11.3). ↩

The five lower fetters are the three mentioned above, plus sensual desire and ill will (AN 10.13:1.5). This is the non-returner, who spends their last life in an exalted Brahmā realm. Compare Chāndogya Upaniṣad 8.15.1: one who lives properly “attains the Brahmā realm and does not return again” (brahmalokam abhisaṁpadyate na ca punar āvartate) | A “spontaneous” rebirth is one that occurs without gestation in the womb, like most devas, or for that matter, Boltzmann brains (see note on MN 12:32.3). ↩

This is the arahant, the “worthy” or “perfected” one. Elsewhere it is said they abandon the five higher fetters: desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance (AN 10.13:2.2). ↩

This is the most fundamental of the Buddha’s teachings on the path, declared in his first sermon (SN 56.11). It reappears in DN 8:13.5, DN 19:61.7, and DN 22:21.2. ↩

The eight factors map roughly on to the Gradual Training thus: hearing the Dhamma gives rise to right view; the choice to renounce is right thought; ethics includes right speech, action, and livelihood; undertaking seclusion and sense restraint is right effort; developing meditation is right mindfulness; and gaining the four jhānas is right immersion. Realization of the Dhamma completes the circle by deepening conceptual right view to liberating insight. Sometimes this is expressed by adding two further factors, right knowledge and right liberation. ↩

The Buddha retells the events recorded in the next sutta, DN 7. ↩

Muṇḍiya means “bald one”; his name is spelled Mandissa in some manuscripts. He appears only in this passage. Jāliya returns in DN 24:2.4.1, which recounts the farcical events following Sunakkhatta’s disrobal. There he takes the Buddha’s part against the delusional Pāṭikaputta favored by Sunakkhatta. ↩

The term “soul” (jīva) was favored by the samaṇas, as opposed to the “self” (attā) of the brahmins. Both are rejected by the Buddha as forms of “metaphysical” self: they postulate the absolute, eternal existence of entities that cannot be established empirically. The repeated demonstrative pronouns (taṁ jīvaṁ taṁ sarīraṁ) assert an emphatic identity. ↩

They evidently believed that the experience of jhāna would grant insight into this dilemma. But it is a loaded question: it assumes that the soul is real and that what needs determining is its relation to the body. ↩

Until this point, none of the experiences described are fundamentally incompatible with the notion of an eternal metaphysical self. Buddhists believe that non-Buddhists, before and after the Buddha, are quite capable of realizing such states. However, they would tend to interpret them in line with their previous beliefs, thus reinforcing their theories of self. Faced with the end of all rebirth, however, no theory of eternal self can stand. ↩

This sutta depicts the events that were subsequently related by the Buddha in the previous sutta, DN 6. ↩

Ujuññā was a Kosalan town at which King Pasenadi visited the Buddha in MN 90. | “Deer parks” were nature reservations where the animals were safe from hunters. ↩

Naked ascetics are still found in India today. Some Jains went naked, but if he were a Jain he would have been introduced as such. Kassapa is an ancient clan name of the brahmins, and we meet four naked ascetics named Kassapa in the canon (here, SN 12.17, SN 41.9, and MN 124). They cannot be the same person, for at the end of each account it is said they went forth and attained arahantship. ↩

In his first sermon, the Buddha rejected extremes of self-mortification. There the term was attakilamatha (“self-mortification”), whereas here it is tapas (“heat, burning, fervor”). These refer to the same practices, but tapas points to the fervent ardor of the practitioner, generating an inner heat that “burns off” the corrupting traces of kamma and defilements. This topic is also discussed in AN 10.94. ↩

While the self-mortification itself may be useless, the person who practices it may have other good qualities. The Buddha is cautioning against rash judgment. ↩

Again we see the Buddha’s preferred method of establishing common ground first, then building an argument from there. ↩

Rather than logical hair-splitting, the Buddha recommends looking at a person’s conduct. ↩

Here -va has an exclusive sense (= eva). Compare Dhp 274: eseva maggo natthañño (“This is the path, there is no other”). ↩

Compare DN 16:5.27.1. ↩

What follows is a description of ascetic practices undertaken by the Jains and similar groups. | The phrase “course of fervent mortification” (tapopakkama) is unique to this sutta. Pakkama means “stepping out”. ↩

Buddhist mendicants may not receive food in their hands, nor lick them while eating. Followers of the practices listed here would have walked steadily and randomly for alms, accepting only what was given at the time. ↩

Keeping sheep (eḷaka, for slaughter) goes against the Jain principle of non-violence, as does keeping weapons (daṇḍa). | A musala often means “pestle”, but it can also be a “shovel”; at MN 81:18.12 it is regarded as a virtue to not use one to dig the soil (which is regarded as being alive in Jainism). | Thusodaka is an alcoholic porridge fermented from grain-husks, mentioned alongside sovīraka in the Pali commentaries and Carakasaṁhitā 27g.191. ↩

It is not easy to meaningfully distinguish the various kinds of grain. ↩

All are extremely uncomfortable. Christian ascetics wore a “hair shirt” in order to “mortify the flesh”. ↩

Jain ascetics tear out their hair at ordination, rather than shaving. ↩

Remaining in one posture for months or years at a time is one of the most difficult practices. ↩

Strict Jain ascetics did not bathe. ↩

At Kd 6:14.6.3 the four “great unnaturals” (or “filthy edibles”, mahāvikaṭa) are said to be feces, urine, ash, and clay. At MN 12:49.3 the Buddha said he ate the “unnatural things” of feces and urine when undertaking ascetic practices. ↩

This seems out of place here. It was a Brahmanical practice (SN 7.21), as the Jains refused to bathe at all. Indeed, bathing three times a day in the Indian climate would, for most of the year, be quite pleasant. ↩

The term “accomplishment in mind” (cittasampadā) is equivalent to “accomplishment in immersion” (samādhisampadā). More generally, when citta is used in the context of meditation, it is normally a synonym of samādhi. ↩

Mettā is universal love and good will free from attachment. As well as being a foundation for good character and healthy emotional development, it serves to lead the mind into deep meditation of jhāna. ↩

The Buddha was criticized for going soft after abandoning austere practices, but here he flips the script, arguing that it is inner transformation that is really hard, not outer shows of mortification. ↩

Note that the heading for this section in the Mahāsaṅgīti edition uses samādhi rather than citta. Headings were added by later editors, and are not part of the original text. ↩

This is the ethical practices as described in the Gradual Training. ↩

“Mortification in disgust of sin” renders tapojigucchā; tapo is “fervent mortification” and jigucchā is “loathing, disgust”. It captures the severity with which practitioners regarded the “evil” or “sin” with which they were infected, like a quasi-physical stain on the soul, and the burning flame of white-hot pain required to cauterize their spiritual wounds. ↩

The Buddha repurposes the concept of “disgust of sin”, which here stands in the place of meditation (samādhi). ↩

A “lion’s roar” is an unapologetic proclamation of spiritual supremacy. ↩

The Buddha is referring to the events of the Udumbarikasutta (DN 25). There Nigrodha is referred to as a “wanderer” (paribbājaka) who according to the commentary was clothed. The term tapabrahmacārī here is unique and is not explained in the commentary. I think it means he was a celibate student of a Brahmanical teacher. Tapas and brahmacariya are closely linked in Atharvaveda 11.5. ↩

In the early period, there was no distinction between “going forth” (pabbajjā) and “ordination” (upasampadā). They refer to two sides of the same coin: leaving the home life and entering the ascetic life. Ordination was originally granted by the Buddha with the simple call, “Come mendicant!” (Kd 1:6.32.1). As the community grew, the Buddha authorized the Saṅgha to perform the “going forth and ordination” (Kd 1:12.1.1). Later still, the novice (sāmaṇera) platform was introduced for teenagers and became known as “going forth” (Kd 1:54.3.2). Finally, the novice ordination was standardized for all ordinands, even if it was a mere preliminary for the “full ordination”. ↩

This probation is laid down in the Vinaya at Kd 1:38.1.5. The candidate shaves, dons the robes, takes refuge, and asks for probation. They must show good conduct and restraint, diligence in duties, and enthusiasm for the Buddha’s teachings and practice. ↩

In addition to individual exceptions, there are general exceptions for dreadlocked fire-worshipping ascetics, since they believe in kamma, and for the Buddha’s relatives (Kd 1:38.11.3). ↩

Poṭṭhapāda appears only here; he was named for a month of the lunar calendar (August/September). | Mallikā was the chief queen of Pasenadi, and her hall is mentioned in a similar context at MN 78:1.3. The commentary explains that the brahmins, Jains, and others would assemble there to “debate their beliefs” (samayaṁ pavadanti). Evidently the monastery grounds had accommodation for many ascetics of different beliefs, but only “one hall” where they would gather for debate. We hear many times of such debates, but here we catch a glimpse of a place that was set up to facilitate them. For -ācīra, read in the sense of “boundary, hedge” (commentary: timbarūrukkhapantiyā parikkhittattā; cf. Sanskrit prācīra, “enclosure, hedge, fence, wall”). ↩

According to the commentary, when he approached the vicinity of the city gate, he decided to check the position of the sun and noticed that it was too early to enter. The commentary and sub-commentary explain that it only sounds like the Buddha was in doubt, for Buddhas deliberate before deciding on a course of action. ↩

This can be understood as answering the criticism voiced in DN 8:22.2, that the Buddha was afraid to speak in an assembly. ↩

In contrast with the silence of the Buddha’s community at DN 2:10.7. ↩

The Buddha encourages quiet for the sake of mental development; Poṭṭhapāda does it for the sake of reputation. ↩

Poṭṭhapāda’s address is almost overly deferential. ↩

Always polite, the Buddha begins by showing an interest in them. ↩

Abhisaññā does not appear elsewhere. Here the prefix abhi- means not “higher”, but rather “about, concerning”. Compare abhidhamma at MN 32:8.6: dve bhikkhū abhidhammakathaṁ kathenti (“two mendicants engage in discussion about the teaching”); also abhivinaya at AN 3.140:4.4. The commentary here says abhi- is a mere particle, so it need not be translated. ↩

This discussion appears to have been directly sparked by the difficult passage in Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 2.4.12 and 4.5.13. The sage Yājñavalkya, teaching his wife Maitreyī, says that the true Self is a sheer mass of “consciousness” (vijñāna, Pali viññāṇa), which is “great, endless, infinite reality”. After realizing this, he says, there is no “perception” (saṁjñā, Pali saññā), a statement that bewilders even the wise Maitreyī. He explains that only in an apparent state of duality (dvaitamiva) do the separate functions of sense consciousness operate. When all is realized as the Self, how, he asks, can one know that owing to which all this is known? He is implicitly distinguishing between viññāna as “infinite” (= vi-) knowing and saññā as “constrained” (saṁ-) knowing. Yājñavalkya says the separate Self emerges with these elements and vanishes with them (etebhyo bhūtebhyaḥ samutthāya tānyevānu vinaśyati), but he does not explain how or why this happens, which is the question the theorists here attempt to address. ↩

Here perception is not identified with the “person” (purisa), but rather belongs to them (cf. etaṁ mama, “this is mine”). In the discussion to follow, the Buddha only directly addresses this theory, while the remainder are included by inference. ↩

This idiom is also at SN 47.19:1.10. ↩

The self is defined as perception (eso me attā), one of the five aggregates. Compare the various theories of the self and perception at DN 1:2.38.0. ↩

Implying that at such times a person lacks a “self”. This is perhaps related to Yājñavalkya’s: “That man, when born, acquiring a body, is connected with ills (the bodily organs); and when he dies, departing, he discards those ills” (Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.3.8). ↩

The commentary says these were devotees of āthabbaṇa, i.e the practices preserved in the Atharvaveda. This “fourth Veda” is mentioned only once by name in the early Pali (Snp 4.14:13.1), where, as here, it is associated with the performance of magic and the casting of spells. The commentary fairly drips with contempt: “Allegedly, the Āthabbaṇa practitioners cast a spell, showing a creature’s head as if cut off, or their hand as if cut off, or as if dead. Then they show them back to normal; imagining so, they say, ‘From cessation they have arisen.’” ↩

See DN 29:16.20 for upakaḍḍhati and apakaḍḍhati in this sense. ↩

Pakataññū is not elsewhere attested in the suttas, but it is found in the Vinaya, for example at Bu Pc 72:1.8. ↩

Here the Buddha argues that, since it is possible to change the nature of one’s own mind through practice, such changes cannot be random. ↩

It is unusual to add “said the Buddha” (bhagavā avoca) in such a context. Normally, once a speaker starts, the text does not insert extra tags identifying the speaker without a reason, such as an interruption for a question. ↩

Sinhalese manuscripts, followed by PTS, include the paragraphs on the metaphor of the king’s security (DN 2:63.1) and on guarding the sense doors here. ↩

Progress through the jhānas is explained in terms of the refining of perceptions. ↩

“Subtle and true” is sukhumasacca, a term that appears only here. ↩

We have encountered the “formless attainments” (arūpasamāpatti) before, where they formed a refined basis for attachment to self (DN 1:3.13.4). Here they appear as part of the gradual refinement of consciousness through the cessation of increasingly subtle perceptions. ↩

This is the vision of light that later came to be called a “sign” (nimitta). In the first four jhānas this persists as a “subtle” (sukhuma) reflection or echo of the “substantial” (olārika) material basis of meditation, such as the breath or the parts of the body. Even though it is a purely mental phenomenon, it is still “form” (rūpa) since it has physical properties like light or extension. ↩

The “light” (obhāsa) of jhāna grows from “limited” (paritta) to “limitless” (appamāṇa, MN 128:29.1). Then the perception of even this limitless light vanishes, leaving only infinite space. ↩

Perception of infinite space fades away leaving only the infinite consciousness that is aware. ↩

The meditator is no longer even aware of infinite consciousness, but of the even vaster nothingness. ↩

The last of the four formless attainments is the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. Since this, by definition, lies beyond the scope of perception, it is not included here. ↩

For sakasaññī (“takes charge of their own perception”), see Bu Pj 2:6.2.2. One relevant factor in determining whether an object has been stolen is if the accused “perceives it as their own”. Here it means that the meditator understands that they can evolve their own perceptions through meditation. ↩

“Intend and choose” is ceteyyaṁ abhisaṅkhareyyaṁ (1st singular optative). These synonyms are used in the sense of a subtle sense of will or intentionality that underlies such attainments (MN 52:14.3) and which must be let go lest they generate rebirth (MN 140:22.10). ↩

Compare with “progressive cessation” (AN 9.31), “progressive tranquilizing of conditions” (SN 36.15), “progressive meditations” (AN 9.32), etc. | “Awareness” is sampajāna, which we have encountered previously as “situational awareness” in daily activities, or as the “awareness” in the third jhāna. Here it refers to a reflective capacity to understand the nature of deep meditation in terms of causality. The term was adopted by Patañjalī, who defined saṁprajñātasamādhi in a way that is clearly drawn from the Buddhist definition of jhāna. It is attained with vitakka, vicāra, ānanda (“bliss”), and āsmitā. According to the commentary, this last term is “experience of the one self” (ekātmikā saṁvid) and so is probably adapted from the Buddhist factor of ekaggatā. (Yogasūtra 1.17). ↩

Taking the kernel of Yājñavalkya’s theory of the cessation of limited perception, the Buddha has expanded it in psychological and practical detail, while leaving out the metaphysical assumption of the Self. ↩

Poṭṭhapāda shows the Buddha that he has been paying attention. Notice how it is culturally assumed that it is possible to retain and repeat the exact content of the teaching. ↩

The meaning of this is not clear to me. It might mean that insight can be developed based on any of the stages of meditation, so for that person their peak of perception is different to another’s. The commentary says that it refers to different meditation subjects, or simply to different occasions of meditation. ↩

Poṭṭhapāda’s distinction between “perception” (saññā) and “knowledge” (ñāṇa) echoes Yājñavalkya’s distinction between “perception” (saṁjā) and “consciousness” (vijñāna, or in the repeated passage at 4.5.13, prajñāna). ↩

Perception has been described in terms of the progress through more refined meditations (samādhi). Only then does the “knowledge” (ñāṇa) of insight arise. ↩

The term “specific condition” (idappaccayā) is well known from dependent origination (eg. SN 12.20:2.3), where it applies to the general situation of ongoing existence in transmigration. When developing insight, a meditator takes their own meditation experience as their primary locus. This is then generalized to an understanding of the nature of conscious existence. ↩

This draws from the initial presentation of different theories of the person and perception (DN 9:6.4). ↩

“Believe” is paccesi, literally “fall back on”. It implies that an idea is something one relies on or takes as fundamental. The Buddha wants to know where Poṭṭhapāda stands before exploring this topic. ↩

Despite his previous questions about perception and the self, Poṭṭhapāda takes his stand on a purely materialist view, identifying the “self” with the organic “substantial” body. ↩

Again, the Buddha does not rush to tell Poṭṭhapāda he is right or wrong, but rather draws out the implications of his statement. ↩

Here tiṭṭhateva is not “leaving aside”, but “remains”. Compare the similar construction at MN 107:13.1. ↩

This is the “subtle” (sukhuma) body, corresponding with the form experienced in the four jhānas. All manuscripts appear to be missing the expected rūpī in this passage, but it occurs in the corresponding passage on “reincarnation” below. ↩

This identifies the self as that which is experienced in the formless attainments. Poṭṭhapāda is simply cycling through possible self theories without really thinking through the implications. ↩

Poṭṭhapāda can only attest a belief in various theories and still does not know how to assess them for himself. ↩

This is the famous list of ten “undeclared points”, which are found throughout the suttas (eg. MN 25:10.21, MN 63:2.3, MN 72:3.1, and the whole of SN 44). They seem to have functioned as a kind of checklist by which philosophers could be evaluated and classified. | The word loka occurs in a number of senses, but here it refers to the entire “cosmos” of countless worlds. ↩

This phrase recurs at SN 21.9:1.4 and AN 3.64:11.1, with some variant readings. ↩

The commentary says Citta was the son of an elephant trainer. Here he shows greater respect to the Buddha than does Poṭṭhapāda. ↩

This point seems to be lost on a number of modern commentators, who infer from passages such as the ten undeclared points that the Buddha refused to make any definitive declarations at all. The Buddha, rather, was a vibhajjavādin (MN 99:4.4, AN 10.94:4.7), “one who speaks after analysis”. ↩

See DN 1:2.38.2. ↩

The Buddha does not rely on rumor; he begins by checking his facts with those concerned. Not only does this affirm his commitment to truth, it shows respect and establishes a common ground from which the argument proceeds. ↩

The verb viharati means “dwell”, and functions as an auxiliary verb implying duration. In spiritual contexts it often means “a period or state of meditation”. This first question is asking whether they see such a state in a regular meditation practice. ↩

Perhaps they might not be able to develop a meditation for seeing that self, but at some point they may have had some sort of perception or vision or insight. ↩

Since they have no experience, they might at least have an idea how to reach that experience. ↩

They haven’t even heard a report about it. ↩

“No demonstrable basis” renders appāṭihīrakataṁ. The Vedic pratiharate means “to yearn for, to welcome, to delight in”, from which pāṭihāriya means “that which should be delighted in, an amusement, an entertainment, an attraction”. In early Pali, the primary sense is something demonstrated or displayed that is convincing or inspiring. In later Pali this narrows to “miracle”. ↩

Janapadakalyāṇī is typically rendered as “the most beautiful lady in the land”. At SN 47.20:2.2 we learn that she is a dazzling singer and dancer. And while she was famed for her beauty (Ud 3.2:9.1), the word kalyāṇa normally means “(morally) good, fine, lovely” and does not refer solely to her appearance. ↩

The same color “dingy”—mud-green—is used of Gotama when his skin was ruined by austerities. It might seem an odd color for a beautiful woman, but then “men’s tastes vary” (SN 4.25:5.2). ↩

Nisseni only occurs elsewhere in Bu Ss 6:2.3.6 and Bu Ss 7:2.67, where it is something carried, i.e. a ladder rather than a flight of stairs. ↩

Attapaṭilābha is literally “re-acquisition of self”, where attā is explained by the commentary as attabhāva, the “state of the self” or “life-form” that is acquired or “incarnated” at rebirth, i.e. the body (sarīra), whether material or immaterial. Here we see an echo of the old use of ātman as “body”, although it is applied even to the formless realms. ↩

These recap the three theses of perception and the self posted by Poṭṭhapāda from DN 9:22.1. ↩

Compare with the similar sentiment at SN 22.2:10.1. ↩

The Buddha points to the experience to demonstrate what he is talking about, rather than offering a long theoretical explanation. Ayaṁ is a pronoun of presence, used to indicate what is apparent before the subject. ↩

Citta is asking an ontological question, assuming that these three states are existent realities of the self. ↩

The Buddha reframes the question as one of conventional description. He is describing states in which one might be reborn, not underlying ontologies. ↩

This anticipates one of the great philosophical debates of sectarian Buddhists which gave rise to the Sarvāstivāda, the school whose core doctrine was that “all exists (in the past, future, and present)”. The Buddha describes past, future, and present with the three grammatical tenses. ↩

Compare Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 3.3.3.2. ↩

Words such as “self” have a conventional usage and in that context are perfectly fine. But what that “self” refers to is constantly changing, as it is reincarnated in different states. It is like a river which keeps the same name even though the water is always changing. If, driven by attachment, we assume there is a metaphysical reality underlying the conventional “self”, we step beyond what can be empirically verified. Note, however, that the Buddha is not asserting that there are two levels of truth, conventional and ultimate, a distinction not found in early Buddhism. | Compare MN 139:3.9, MN 74:13.1, SN 1.25. ↩

In AN 6.60 we find Citta Hatthisāriputta, still a somewhat junior monk, rudely interrupting his seniors. After admonition he disrobed, but he ordained again and later achieved arahantship. We can reconcile these two accounts by recognizing that the phrase acira “not long after” is a conventional term, which might be several years. Thus the events of AN 6.60 occurred some time between his ordination and awakening. ↩

Ānanda’s role became more prominent as a leader of the Saṅgha in the years after the Buddha’s passing. This sutta shows the continued propagation of the Buddha’s teachings after his death. ↩

The same Subha earlier met the Buddha in MN 99 and again in MN 135, where he asked about kamma. His father Todeyya was a prominent brahmin, often mentioned alongside Pokkharasāti. The two apparently lived not far from each other, as, according to the commentary, Todeyya was named for his village of Tudi outside of Sāvatthī (see Pāṇini’s Aṣṭādhyāyī 4.3.94). | These events suggest a certain, albeit tenuous, timeframe for the significant conversion of influential brahmins initiated by Pokkharasāti in DN 3. Here, Subha is active after the Buddha’s death, suggesting his age is aligned with that of Ānanda, a generation younger than the Buddha. If this is so, Subha’s first meeting with the Buddha would have taken place no earlier than the middle period of his teaching, perhaps twenty years before the Parinibbāna (MN 99). There he mentions Pokkharasāti’s hostility to the claims of ascetics, so this must precede Pokkharasāti’s conversion in DN 3 by a considerable period. If we are on the right track, the conversion of Pokkharasāti, and the events that flowed from that, must have happened late in the Buddha’s career, perhaps in the final decade of his life. ↩

Ānanda was getting old. ↩

Cetaka is mentioned only here. The commentary says he was named for his home country of Cetī, which is roughly the modern region of Bundelkhand, about 500 km south-west of Sāvatthī. ↩

What follows has much the same content as DN 2, but arranged under these three heads rather than as successively refined happiness. ↩

While samādhi proper is the deep immersion in meditation, here it is a category that pertains to developing such states. ↩

He had already gone to the Buddha for refuge in MN 99:28.4 and MN 135:21.4. ↩

This was the scene for some controversial discussions with Jains (MN 56, SN 42.8), and Sāriputta’s touching declaration of faith shortly before his passing (SN 47.12, DN 16:1.16.1, DN 28). It is probably the Pāvā (modern Pawapuri) at which Mahāvīra died according to the Jain tradition. ↩

Kevaḍḍha is mentioned only here. Manuscripts spell his name variously as Kevaddha or Kevaṭṭa (“fisherman”). The Chinese form 堅固 means “sturdy” (from dṛḍha) and thus supports Kevaḍḍha. ↩

I have been asked to do the same thing for the same reason. ↩

In fact it is forbidden in Kd 15:8.2.23. ↩

The reading dhaṁsemi is dubious. An old Burmese manuscript has the reading dhammaṁ desemi, which echoes the Buddha just above. Note too that Kevaḍḍha urges the Buddha to “direct” the monks (samādisatu, from the same root as desemi). I think the tension is deliberate: Kevaḍḍha says he isn’t telling the Buddha how to teach, but he absolutely is. Other readings convey the sense “attack, insult”, but this seems out of place. ↩

As noted previously, the basic sense of pāṭihāriya is “demonstration”, and as the context here shows, it may or may not involve a “demonstration of wonders” i.e. a “miracle”. ↩

These three are mentioned frequently in the suttas. Only the last is endorsed by the Buddha, as it leads to genuine growth. ↩

Their priors have been confirmed. ↩

Note how a skeptical mindset sticks closer to the truth. ↩

“Spell” is vijjā (Sanskrit vidyā, “(potent) knowledge”, cf. English “wicca”, “wizard”, “witch”). The commentary says it was practiced by the seers of Gandhāra (north-west Pakistan). Jain tradition also knows a Gandhārī mantra, but attribute it to certain vidyādhara deities. Sanskrit tradition similarly knows of a vidyādevī (“lore goddess”) named Gandhārī. Gandhāra was an ancient land of learning, and a convenient location for exotic magics. ↩

These feats that have nothing to do with spiritual growth, hence they may be produced or perhaps faked by a variety of means. ↩

“Revealing” is ādesana, from root dis “to indicate, show, or point”. ↩

The Pali terms here are citta, cetasika, vitakka, and vicāra. ↩

Here we have mano (twice) and citta. ↩

From maṇi, “gem”. Magical gems are a common feature of Indian storytelling. Buddhist stories often feature the “wish-granting gem” (cintāmaṇi), which according to the commentary is meant here. ↩

This story is presented as an actual event, but is phrased like a fable. ↩

The question is about meditation, not the annihilation of the material world. The first four jhānas are based on the “subtle form” (sukhumarūpa) that manifests as light in deep meditation. He is asking how to go beyond this to the formless attainments. ↩

The mendicant has already well developed the jhānas. | “Controlling the body as far as the Brahmā realm” is one of the “demonstrations of psychic power” listed above. ↩

The “gods of the Four Great Kings” are deities born in a realm subject to the overlords known as the Four Great Kings. These deities inhabit the lowest of the celestial realms. ↩

These are powerful spirits who guard the four quarters. In AN 8.36 it is explained that they, like the other leading gods mentioned below, achieved their station due to their greater generosity and morality. ↩

The “thirty-three” enjoy refined sensual delights. The number is a reduplication of the trinity. In Buddhist texts they are not enumerated, but Yājñavalkya reckons them as eight Vasus, eleven Rudras, twelve Ādityas, plus Indra and Prajāpati (Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 3.9.2). The final pair are elsewhere said to be Dyaus (“Heaven” = Zeus) and Pṛthivī (“Earth”), or the twin Aśvins. ↩

Conventionally known as “lord of gods”, but in fact the ruler only of the relatively lowly realm of the thirty-three. He is Vedic Indra, heroic slayer of the dragon Vṛtra, and is the most personally known god in the Pali Canon. ↩

Gods in this realm (spelled yāma, “of Yama”) are subjects of the god of the dead, Yama. ↩

The previous deities achieved their station by mere morality and generosity, not by jhāna. The gods of Brahmā’s Host practiced the first jhāna, but they do not know what lies beyond. ↩

The same passage appears in DN 1:2.5.2, where it also had a satirical tone, poking fun at the pomposity of religious titles. ↩

Even Brahmā’s community are not confident. ↩

This passage may be one of the sources for the later use of nimitta to mean the appearance of light that signifies the approach of jhāna. ↩

He puffs his own chest, but like the ascetic teachers of DN 2, he does not answer the question. ↩

He addresses Brahmā with āvuso. This is often translated as “friend”, but the root is āyu (“age”) and it is respectful not familiar. ↩

Rather than trying to engage with Brahmā’s agenda, he keeps restating his question. This is a skillful way of curbing narcissism. ↩

Brahmā is embarrassed to reveal his ignorance. Perhaps a satire of Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 3.2.13, where Yājñavalkya takes Jāratkārava Ārtabhāga by the hand and leads him aside for a secret discussion. ↩

At least he is honest about his lack of knowledge, even if not publicly. ↩

The first pair of couplets rephrase the question about where the (absorptions based on) material form cease. This couplet is also found at SN 1.27:2.1, Ud 1.10:14.1. | A gādha is a “ford” across a river (Rig Veda 7.60.7, 7.97.8, 10.106.9; Gopatha Brāhmaṇa 1.5.2a), a safe path on which one has a “footing” to cross the water. In this verse, the verb form gādhati means to be “established” (patiṭṭhita) like a seed in soil, or a beam of light on a floor, or consciousness in name and form. ↩

The verse is syntactically ambiguous, as there are three couplets, each with the question-word kattha, but only two verbs. I take the first pair of couplets as a distinct verse, with the verb gādhati acting as a “lamp” illuminating both the first and second couplets. These are also unified in that they deal only with material qualities. ↩

A similar list of descriptors elsewhere describes things that are not stolen (Snp 3.9:45.1) or the kinds of sentient beings (Snp 1.8:4.3). These are aspects of how “form” manifests in desirable or undesirable ways. ↩

Four terms in this verse are identical with the first four terms in Yājñavalkya’s description of the immutable Brahman as “neither coarse nor fine, neither short nor long” at Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 3.8.8. ↩

This final couplet is distinguished in having a different verb (“cease”) and in including mental qualities (nāma). It therefore appears there are two questions with two answers. ↩

This couplet is spoken by Baka the Divinity at MN 49:25.1, so it was probably a free-floating couplet illustrating the Upaniṣadic theory of the Self as infinite consciousness. I think the Buddha is quoting Brahmā here in order to contrast with his own teaching of the cessation of consciousness, to emphasize that even this most sublime form of consciousness will cease. | “Where no form appears” (anidassanaṁ) here is a synonym for “formless” (see eg. MN 21:14.8, “space is formless and invisible”, ākāso arūpī anidassano). Normally the colors and images seen in the “form” absorptions are described as “appearing” (eg. DN 16:3.29.1), so this indicates a formless attainment. ↩

“Infinite” (ananta) is the direct qualifier of “consciousness”, but in the Pali it is shifted to the next line to fit the meter. It indicates the second of the formless attainments. Yājñavalkya describes consciousness as infinite in the famous passage at Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 2.4.12. | Pabhaṁ means “radiant”, as with the deities that are “self-radiant” (sayaṁpabhā, DN 27:10.3). This echoes descriptions of the Divinity of consciousness as “radiant” (Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 5.6.1, Chāndogya Upaniṣad 3.14.2). See too Thag 20.1:59.6, AN 1.51:1.1, and AN 3.101:1.11, and notes there. | Sabbato pabhaṁ (“radiant all-round”) is synonymous with pariyodāta (“bright”, literally “white all over”), a stock descriptor of the mind of fourth jhāna, on which the formless states are based. ↩

The division of these ten lines is not obvious. Since the previous couplet appears to be an independent saying, I take the remaining eight lines as two four-line verses. This couplet, too, appears as the first two lines of a six-line verse, with the initial yattha rather than ettha (SN 1.27:2.1). ↩

The verb “has no footing” applies to both the former and subsequent couplet. ↩

These lines also at Snp 5.2:6.6, with initial yattha instead of ettha. ↩

According to dependent origination, when consciousness ceases, name and form cease, and with it the manifestation of all things desirable and undesirable in the world. ↩

Throughout, take the locative ettha (“here”) as locative of reference (“in reference to this”), as in similar constructions (eg. SN 1.30). When the Buddha is speaking of the cessation of consciousness, he is speaking specifically of the “infinite consciousness” of the Upaniṣads: that is what ceases. ↩

This is the only appearance of a place called Sālavatikā (“Abounding in Sal Trees”). A courtesan of Rājagaha named Sālavatī appears in Kd 8:1.3.1; she might perhaps have come from there. ↩

A certain brahmin Lohicca also appears in SN 35.132. But since that is set far away in Avantī after the Buddha’s passing, and since in both cases he is said to have taken refuge, it seems likely these are different people. ↩

A similar view is sometimes unjustly imputed to the Theravādins, that they are only interested in their own liberation. ↩

While nhāpita would seem to be identical with nhāpaka (“bathroom attendant”), it is usually translated per Ja 395 where it means “barber”. ↩

Note the unusual use of kira in this idiom, found in SN 35.133:2.3, MN 85:3.5, MN 127:2.5, and Ud 2.8:6.8. I think this expresses polite deference, and render with “might” rather than “would”. ↩

It seems the barber was not only a trusted confidant, but an intelligent man with sincere concern for Lohicca’s well being. ↩

The Buddha is modest as to his chances. ↩

Here the Buddha takes the initiative. “Harmful misconception” is pāpakaṁ diṭṭhigataṁ. ↩

Kosala is the native realm of Pasenadi. Kāsi had formerly been an independent kingdom, but was taken over by Pasenadi’s father Mahākosala. Towards the end of the Buddha’s life it was contested between Kosala and Magadha (SN 3.14, SN 3.15). Ultimately it became part of the greater Magadhan empire. ↩

It is only through sharing what good things we know that we can support each other. ↩

Even though he has characterized Lohicca’s view as harmful, the Buddha goes out of his way to show that it is not entirely wrong. There are cases where it is best to avoid teaching. ↩

The genders of this passage are made clear through the use of feminine nouns. Making unwelcome advances was seen as an obvious example of something wrong. ↩

At DN 29:5.2 the opposite sense is expressed as samādāya taṁ dhammaṁ vattati. ↩

The Buddha adopts Lohicca’s formulation, but applies it in a specific sense, not as a generalization. ↩

Now that the Buddha has established a degree of overlap between their views, Lohicca wants to hear more. ↩

Again, the Buddha answers directly and simply. ↩

Naraka means “cliff” or “abyss” in early Pali (MN 49:5.9, MN 86:6.15, Snp 3.11:28.4, Thag 16.8:4.2). It does not have the sense “hell” until the late canonical period; the early Pali term for hell is niraya. Notably, naraka is not strongly attested in the sense of “hell” for pre-Buddhist Sanskrit either, although we do find nāraka, apparently in the sense of “hell being”, at Atharva Veda 12.4.36c and Śukla Yajur Veda 30.5. ↩

Manasākaṭa is mentioned only here. ↩

Aciravatī is called Rapti today. It was one of the great rivers that flowed from the Himalayas through Kosala into the Ganges. ↩

Similar discussions are found in MN 98 = Snp 3.9 and DN 27. | The compound maggāmagga can be read either as “what is the path and what is not the path” (per commentary, magge ca amagge ca), or as “the variety of paths” (compare phalāphala, “all sorts of fruit”). Here, however, they are concerned to distinguish one path as correct. ↩

This must have been earlier than Pokkharasāti’s conversion at DN 3:2.22.1. Pokkharasāti was a family man who denied the reality of superhuman meditative attainments (MN 99:10.4) and emphasized ethics and duties over lineage (MN 98:3.7), which agrees with him being cited on ethical matters at Āpastamba Dharmasūtra 1.6.19.7 and 1.10.28. | Brahmasahabyatā does not mean “union with Brahmā” but rather “rebirth as one of the members of Brahma’s retinue” (see eg. AN 5.34:9.4). The non-dualist concept that the limited personal self merges with the cosmic divinity is expressed in Pali, rather, with such phrases as so attā so loko (“the self is identical with the cosmos”). | For añjasa (“direct route”) see SN 12.65:7.1 and note. ↩

In Pali we never meet Tārukkha and he is only mentioned in his absence. He evidently advocated that lineage rather than conduct made one a brahmin (MN 98:3.4). There is a Tārukṣya whose view was that union (with Brahmā) arose with the conjunction of speech and breath; this was discussed alongside the views of many other brahmins (Aitareya Āraṇyaka 3.1.6.1; Śāṅkhāyana Āraṇyaka 7.19). In Rig Veda 8.46.32 a certain Balbūtha Tarukṣa the Dāsa makes an offering to a sage. Sāyaṇa, the Vedic commentator, says that Balbūtha Tarukṣa was a guardian of cows, evidently alluding to the Aitareya Āraṇyaka, which describes Tārukṣya as a guardian of his teacher’s cows, thus locating Tārukṣya in the lineage of Tarukṣa. Hiraṇyakeśīgṛhyasūtra 2.8.19 also mentions him as a teacher, there spelled Tarukṣa. ↩

Identified by Wijesekera (A Pali Reference to Brāhmaṇa-Caraṇas, Adyar Library Bulletin, vol 20, 1956; reprinted in Buddhist and Vedic Studies) and Jayatilleke (Early Buddhist Theory of Knowledge, p. 480). I use the familiar Sanskrit forms, as the Pali has several dubious spellings and variants. Their texts and corresponding Vedas are respectively: Adhvaryu = Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa (incl. Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad; White Yajur Veda); Taittirīya = Taittirīya Brāhmaṇa (Black Yajur Veda); Chāndogya = Chāndogya Brāhmaṇa (Sāman Veda); Cāndrāyaṇa (omitted from MS edition) = Kauṣītaki Brāhmaṇa (Rig Veda; spelling established by Wijesekera; see below at DN 13:16.2); Bahvṛca = Bahvṛca Brāhmaṇa (Rig Veda; incorporated in Aitareya and Kauśītaki.) This is the only time the Pali canon mentions these schools, but in some cases we can identify them with brahmins in the canon. Examples include the murmuring Chāndogya brahmin (Ud 1.4); or the Buddha’s former teachers, who evidently hailed from the Addhariya tradition of the Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa (MN 26:15.1ff.). | Jayatilleke notes that the Śatapatha describes its own adherents as Adhvaryu (addhariyā), those priests of the Yajur Veda responsible for the physical acts at the ritual. Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 10.5.2.20 and Kauṣītaki Brāhmaṇa 6.5.6–10 list the Adhvaryu, Chandoga, and Bahvṛca, thus including the same schools in the same order, except the Pali has split the Yajur and Rig followers into two. ↩

Earlier they were arguing over which one of the paths was correct, whereas now they have shifted to a more universalist “many roads up the same mountain” position. When speaking with each other they saw each other’s views as contradictory, but when speaking with an outsider they adopted a more conciliatory position. ↩

The ten names in Pali include the seven authors of the so-called “family books” of the Rig Veda (Maṇḍalas 2–8). As founders of poetic lineages, we often find works by their descendants, which are not always confined to their dedicated family book. Poems by the other three authors are mostly outside the family books. Thus the sages listed here cover most of the Rig Veda, although the Vedic tradition records many other authors as well. | Aṭṭhaka = Atri Bhauma (Maṇḍala 5, rather than Aṣṭaka Vaiśvāmitra of 10.104); Vāmaka = Vamra(ka) Vaikhānasa (10.99; see 9.66); Vāmadeva = Vāmadeva Gautama (Maṇḍala 4); Vessāmitta = Viśvāmitra Gāthina (Maṇḍala 3); Yamadaggi = Jamadagni Bhārgava, a descendant of Bhṛgu (several hymns mostly in Maṇḍalas 9 and 10); Aṅgīrasa = Aṅgirasa, identified with Agni as the founder of a lineage of poet-singers (Maṇḍala 8); Bhāradvāja = Bharadvāja Bārhaspatya (Maṇḍala 6); Vāseṭṭha = Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi (Maṇḍala 7); Kassapa = Kaśyapa Mārīca (several hymns mostly in Maṇḍalas 9 and 10); Bhagu = Bhṛgu, the bringer of fire from heaven whose adoptive descendant was Gṛtsamada Bhārgava Śaunaka (Maṇḍala 2). ↩

Unlike the Buddhist monk at DN 11:80.1. ↩

“No demonstrable basis” is appāṭihīrakataṁ. ↩

The “blind following the blind” is also at MN 95:13.24 and MN 99:9.25. Maitrī Upaniṣad 7.8–9 turns it around, saying that the blind teach false doctrines aimed at destroying the Vedas, “the doctrine of not-self” (nairātmyavāda), an obvious reference to Buddhists. We also find it at Kaṭha Upaniṣad 1.2.5, Muṇḍaka Upaniṣad 1.2.8, Mahābhārata 2.38.3, and the Jain Sūyagaḍa 1.1.2.19. ↩

Sarvajit Kauṣītaki worshiped the rising and setting sun and moon, turning himself to follow their course (Kauṣītaki Upaniṣad 2.7–9). He founded the Kauṣītaki lineage, referred to above as “those who follow the course of the moon” (cāndrāyaṇa). ↩

Indra taught Bhāradvāja a new threefold knowledge by which he might become immortal and realize companionship (sāyujya) with the sun (Taittirīya Brāhmaṇa 3.10.11.15). ↩

For the following list, compare the nine gods listed at Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.4.11 with the eight here. Six are shared with the Pali: Brahma is first, from whom derive Indra, Varuṇa, Soma, Yama, and Īsāna. Even the names that are not in common might arise from flawed transmission: Parjanya there is perhaps Pajāpati here; Rudra (or Shiva) would be well-described by Mahiddhi (“he of great power”); Mṛtyu (death) may have merged with Yama. If this connection is admitted, it would seem the Buddha is making a sly dig. Those who proclaim themselves to be true brahmins are prostrating themselves to those powers among the gods who, with the exception of Brahma himself, are in fact aristocrats (khattiya), not brahmins at all. The Upaniṣad draws attention to the rājasūya coronation, at which the brahmin sits beneath the aristocrat. Further, Indra, Pajāpati, Varuṇa, and Īsāna are also invoked in the martial exhortation at SN 11.3, cementing their status as aristocrat warriors. ↩

Soma is the ritual drug of exhilaration, identified with the moon. | Vedic Varuṇa was the god of command, the king of tough rule. | Īsāna (Sanskrit Īśāna) was created by Pajāpati as “president”, said to be the sun (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 6.1.3). He was also identified with Rudra and Śiva. | Pajāpati (“progenitor”) was the lonely god of creation (“Let Prajāpati generate progeny for us”, Rig Veda 10.85.3). The heat of his fervent exertions (tapas) created the world and all things in it (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 6). | Brahmā, like Pajāpati, is also a creator god, but is the divine power immanent within creation, rather than the forgotten instigator of the past. | The Mahāsaṅgīti reading Mahiddhi (“he of great power”) is not a regular name for a deity, but as noted above, he may be Rudra/Shiva, regarded as the chief deity of psychic powers. The BJT reads Mahinda (Sanskrit Mahendra), the “Great Indra”, said to be a title of Indra bestowed after slaying the dragon Vṛtra (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 2.5.4.9). | Yama (“twin”, with his incestuous sister Yamī) was born immortal but chose mortality, becoming the god of the dead. ↩

Drawing from imagery already established in this text, the passage relies on the metaphor of crossing a river, but the river is not mentioned. Read visādaṁ after the common expression saṁsīdati visīdati (AN 5.75:1.3). The three verbal phrases express increasing intensification of “go under water”: “dive in” (āsīditvā), “sink down” (saṁsīdanti), “undergo drowning” (visādaṁ pāpuṇanti). ↩

The close -ti has apparently confused some editors; Vāseṭṭha is quoting what he has heard. ↩

Here the four brahmavihāras (“meditations of Brahmā”) stand in place of the four jhānas. Brahmavihāras are simply one of the means by which jhānas may be attained, chosen here to fit the stated goal of teaching the path to Brahmā. The suttas treat them as pre-Buddhist, but they have not been traced as a group in pre-Buddhist texts. However, they are shared with later non-Buddhist texts such as Yogasūtra 1.33 and the Jain Tattvārthasūtra 7.11. | “Love” (mettā) is a universal positive regard and well-wishing free of personal desires or attachments. It ultimately derives from the Vedic in the sense of “union”; Mitra was the god of alliances (Rig Veda 3.59). ↩

The mind in jhāna is so powerful that it effectively overrides any limited kamma, including ordinary good or bad deeds. Unless they have committed serious crimes with a fixed kammic result such as matricide, etc., the meditator will be reborn in a Brahmā realm. ↩

“Compassion” (karuṇā) is the quality of empathy with the suffering of another or oneself and the wish to remove it. ↩

“Rejoicing” (muditā) is joyful celebration in the success of others or oneself, free of jealousy or cynicism. ↩

Equanimity (upekkhā) is literally “close watching”, not interfering but standing ready when needed. It is not indifference, which is why it emerges only at the end, after the positive emotions are developed. ↩

A brahmin student who for their whole life practices harmlessness for all beings—except at holy places—attains the world of Brahmā (Chāndogya Upaniṣad 8.15.1). The exception for holy places is, of course, to allow for the sacrifice. ↩

Here the entire concluding section of the Gradual Training dealing with wisdom is omitted, as the aim is limited to teaching rebirth with Brahmā to Brahmanical laypeople, rather than teaching liberation. Vāseṭṭha and Bhāradvāja later applied to ordain, in which time the Buddha taught the full path to Nibbāna (DN 27:7.8). ↩

They also went for refuge in similar circumstances at MN 98:14.4 = Snp 3.9:69.3. According to the commentary, that was the first time they went for refuge, while this was the second time. This makes sense in terms of the progress of the teachings, for there they discuss what makes a brahmin, whereas here they ask the more subtle question how to achieve rebirth with Brahmā. The discussion, too, is on a more detailed level, with a more explicit criticism of the brahmins. Nonetheless, it is difficult to square the details of the narratives, for the opening of this sutta depicts Vāseṭṭha and Bhāradvāja speaking about the Buddha by reputation rather than as devotees who have previously met him and gone for refuge. ↩

In the suttas, apadāna means “evidence”, “traces left behind” (DN 27:16.4, DN 24:2.7.3, MN 15:3.32, AN 3.2:1.1). The sense here seems to have been “(story about) the traces that deeds leave behind”. The sense “legend of past lives” probably grew out of this sutta, and later became the title of the collections of legends of past lives of the monks (Thera-apadāna) and nuns (Therī-apadāna). ↩

Kareri is evidently Miliusa tomentosa, known as hoom or kari in Hindi. It is related to the custard apple, not the curry tree (Murraya koenigii). ↩

“Past life” is pubbenivāsa, literally “former abode”. ↩

At MN 71:14.2 and SN 42.9:4.5 the Buddha says he recollects ninety-one eons, which must refer back to the life of Vipassī. We shall see the origin of his name below. ↩

Sikhī means “crested one” and refers to a halo or crown. A story of him and his disciples is told at SN 6.14; cf. AN 3.80. ↩

Vessabhū is Sanskrit Viśvabhṛt. It means “all-bearing”, probably originating as a word for the earth. A legendary king of the same name once ruled over the city of Avantī (DN 19:36.14). ↩

Due to the appearance of four Buddhas in this cycle it is known as “fortunate” (bhadda). | Stories from Kakusandha’s day appear at MN 50 and SN 15.20:2.8. There is no obvious etymology for his name, but perhaps it stems from kaku (“peak”) and thus “the union of the peaks”, a valley at the junction of mountains. ↩

The meaning of Koṇāgamana is unclear. In Sanskrit it is often spelled Kanakamuni, “the golden sage”, while in the (dubious) Nigali Sagar Edict of Ashoka it is Konākamana. At Thig 16.1:71.1 we hear the past life of three nuns in the time of Koṇāgamana. ↩

Kassapa (Sanskrit Kaśyapa) means “tortoise”. It is a common Brahmanical clan name, stemming from an ancient figure reckoned as the eldest of the “seven sages”, to whom some Vedic verses are attributed. Details of the Buddha Kassapa’s time are found at MN 81, SN 15.20:4.1, and SN 48.57:3.1. ↩

These numbers make up a quasi-logarithmic scale: the time gaps multiply by three, while the number of Buddhas divides by two. In eon one there are four Buddhas. Thirty eons ago the number is halved, so they had two Buddhas. Twice-thirty eons before that, the number is halved again, to one Buddha, thus ending the scale. ↩

In ancient India, the “aristocrats” (khattiya) and the brahmins vied for the prestige of being the highest class. The traditional business of the aristocrats was land, politics, agriculture, and war, while the brahmins were a hereditary priestly caste who served as advisers and ritualists. It is said that the Buddha-to-be was born in whatever caste was most prestigious at the time so that his word would have the most impact. | In this sutta, the Buddha simply refers to himself as “I” with no personal name. When the seven Buddhas are listed at DN 32:3.14, however, he is called Aṅgīrasa. ↩

The Koṇḍaññas (Sanskrit Kauṇḍinya) originated as the leading clan of the city of Kuṇḍina the capital of Vidarbha, which is probably modern Kaundinyapura on the Wardha River. ↩

Gotama is an ancient Brahmanical clan name, which like Kassapa stems from the Vedas and the seven sages. Why does the Buddha, an aristocrat, have a Brahmanical clan? During initiation by a Brahmanical family priest (purohita), an aristocrat was ritually determined to be a brahmin for a short time, during which he would assume the lineage name of the priest. After being restored as an aristocrat, he and his family would still be referred to by that name. Thus the Sakyans’ purohita must have been of the Gotama lineage. Other examples of this practice include the Mallas who are called Vāseṭṭha (DN 16:5.19.2) and Saccaka who is called Aggivessana (MN 35:4.2). The Jain Ācārāṅgasūtra 2.15.15 records a similar situation, for while Mahāvīra was, like the Buddha, a khattiya, he was of the Kāśyapa gotta, and various relatives were assigned to Vāsiṣṭha, Kauṇḍinya, and Kauśika. ↩

Stereospermum chelonoides. Dictionaries of Pali and Sanskrit call this the “trumpet-flower tree”, but that is more commonly used for Oroxylum indicum. ↩

Puṇḍarīka is the white lotus, but here it is the name of a tree. The commentary says this is setamba (“white-mango”). It is not, however, the mango variety known by that name today (Mangifera caesia), which is not found in India. ↩

Shorea robusta. ↩

Albizia lebbeck, sometimes still known by the old name of sirisa. Older sources sometimes call it an acacia. ↩

Ficus racemosa. ↩

Ficus benghalensis. ↩

Ficus religiosa, sacred to Buddhists, Jains, and Hindus alike. Ancient sources referred to it both as assattha (Sanskrit aśvattha) and pippala. Buddhists today simply call it the Bodhi (or Bo) tree. ↩

Abhibhū means “Victor”, while Sambhava means “son of Śambhu the blessed”. Śambhu is commonly found in the Rig Veda in the sense, “blessing, benefit”, and became a common name or epithet of gods, etc. ↩

The number of disciples diminishes as we approach historical time. ↩

An extensive journey of the Buddha with 1,250 mendicants is documented in Kd 6, at one point of which occurs the events of the Selasutta (Snp 3.7 and MN 91). The Buddha is also accompanied by 1,250 mendicants in the Sāmaññaphalasutta (DN 2) and the Parosahassasutta (SN 8.8). ↩

Bandhumā literally means “one who has kin”. A King Bandhumant is recorded as a descendant of Ikṣvāku, son of Manu, son of the Sun (Viṣṇu Purāṇa 4.1). Gotama, likewise, was a “kinsman of the sun” (ādiccabandhu). ↩

The son of King Dawn and Queen Radiant in the City of the Dawn, Sikhī is the streaming rays of sunrise. These names recall a solar myth. ↩

In Mārkaṇḍeya Purāṇa ch. 131, a Pabhāvatī, daughter of the king of Vidarbha, is said to have married Marutta, king of Vajjī. ↩

There is an Arunawati River in Maharashtra, not far from the ancient homeland of the Koṇḍaññas in Kuṇḍina. ↩

The names King Goodfall (suppatita) and Queen Rainy (vassavatī) evoke a seasonal fertility myth, where they gave life to their son Vessabhū, the earth, “the nourisher and bearer of all”. Note, however, the variants suppatīta (“well pleased”) and yasavatī (“celebrated”). ↩

The names of the brahmin fathers all refer to ritual offerings. Aggidatta means “offered to the fire”. ↩

The names of the brahmin mothers all recall Indian nakkhatta. These are “constellations” or more properly “lunar mansions”; segments of the sky through which the Moon passes and which are associated with certain stars or clusters. In the Atharvaveda system, Visākhā is the 16th lunar asterism (Libra). ↩

Based on the Ashoka pillar there, this is identified with modern Gotihawa, southeast of Kapilavastu in Nepal. ↩

“Offered in sacrifice”. ↩

Several constellations are distinguished as “former” (pubba) and “later” (uttara). Since it lies between Visākhā and Dhanavatī, this may be the 21st constellation, Uttara Āṣāḍhā (Sagittarius/Capricorn). ↩

If the dubious Ashokan edict there is to be believed, this was traditionally identified with the town known today as Nigali Sagar near Kapilavastu in Nepal. ↩

“Offered to Brahmā”. Many of the Jātakas feature a king of this name, usually said to reside in Benares. ↩

Dhanavatī means “wealthy”, but it is also an alternate name for the 23rd constellation, dhaniṣṭhā (or śraviṣṭā, Delphinus). ↩

Kikī (“blue jay”) appears in the story of the past Buddha Kassapa at MN 81. ↩

Suddhodana means “white rice”. He is mentioned by name at Thag 10.1:8.1, Snp 3.11:7.2, and Kd 1:54.1.4. ↩

Māyā means “illusion”. She is mentioned by name at Thag 10.1:8.2 and Thig 6.6:6.2. ↩

This is the only doctrinal context where we find vaṭuma (“course”). The commentary explains it as the “course of craving”. However, in Buddhist Sanskrit we find the phrases chinnaṁ vartmaṁ na vartati (Mahāvastu 2.416) and chinnaṁ vartma na pravartate (Nidāna Saṁyukta 11.6), which recall the Pali phrase vaṭṭaṁ vattati (DN 15:22.6), where vaṭṭa occurs in the next word of the current passage. This suggests that the sense is, rather, the “course of transmigration”, as in the later Sanskrit phrase saṁsāravartmani. ↩

“Principle of the teachings” is dhammadhātu. At SN 12.32:18.1, Sāriputta’s mastery of the dhammadhātu gives him the ability to answer any questions on the Dhamma. ↩

These characteristics of the birth of the Buddha-to-be are also found in MN 123, where Ānanda quotes the Buddha, although the wording is a little different and three extra details are added at the start. In addition, this detail and that about emerging mindfully from the womb are found at AN 4.127. | Normally in early Pali, the word bodhisatta is reserved for the Buddha-to-be once he has left home and is practicing “intent on awakening” (eg. MN 26:13.1). This passage extends the usage back as far as the end of the immediate past life. ↩

“Normal” is dhammatā, a natural principle. This entire passage differs from the earliest concept of the bodhisatta (“one intent on awakening”), which in early texts is typically applied to Siddhattha after he left the home. ↩

The commentary identifies this realm of “utter darkness” (andhakāratimisā) with a cold hell realm. There is a corresponding Purāṇic hell called andhatāmisra. | Asaṁvutā was translated by Ñāṇamoḷī as “abysmal”, but this relies on a commentarial cosmology that is not found in the suttas. The sense, rather, is “boundless”. The root harks back to the Vedic serpent Vṛtra who wraps the world in darkness. | Nānubhonti (“makes no impression”) is glossed in the commentary to AN 4.127 as nappahonti (“ineffective”). ↩

The light is a physical one, not just a metaphor. From this, it appears that sentient beings may be spontaneously reborn in interstellar space. Compare the problem of the “Boltzmann brain” in physics. ↩

These are the Four Great Kings, regarded as protector deities. | The term okkanti (“conception”) is a synonym of “rebirth” (DN 15.4.3). It literally means “descent”. Its usage in this context is anticipated by Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.4.1, which describes how, as a man is dying, his self “descends” into the heart. He loses sense awareness, the tip of his heart lights up and he departs, “rising” (utkrāmanta) with his life-breath, and “descending” with consciousness into a new life, taking his knowledge, deeds, and past experiences. ↩

The five precepts. ↩

While sensual pleasures provoke attachment, they are nonetheless a kind of pleasure and therefore a sign of virtue and good past kamma. ↩

This tragic detail is also mentioned in Ud 5.2. The Buddha is raised by a step-mother, which in our Buddha’s case was Māyā’s sister Mahāpajāpatī (AN 8.51:9.8, MN 142:3.3). ↩

Ten signifies fullness and completion, as for example the “ten directions”. | The notion that the term of pregnancy was “nine or ten months” is also found at Chāndogya Upaniṣad 5.9.1. In the Rig Veda it is typically “in the tenth month” (5.78.7, 10.84.3), as also at Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 6.4.22. ↩

In illustrations she is depicted standing while holding a tree in the pose known as sālabhañjikā, a common motif in Indian art representing the abundance of springtime. ↩

Kāsi is the nation of which Varanasi is the capital. Their cloth was of exceptional quality. ↩

This passage implies that Buddhahood was destined from the time of birth, which stands in contrast to the rest of the suttas, where Buddhahood was hard-won by the Bodhisatta’s efforts while striving for awakening. | “Stands firm on his own feet” signifies that he will be awakened by his own efforts. | “North” is uttara, which is also “the beyond”; this predicts his attaining Nibbāna. | “Seven strides” signifies crossing over the vast cycles of birth and death, especially by developing the seven awakening factors. | The “white parasol” signifies purity and royalty (DN 14:1.34.3, Snp 3.11:11.3, Cp 26:3.3; Viṣṇu Purāṇa 5.35.14), and a white canopy at SN 41.5:5.2 is said to symbolize freedom. | “Surveying all quarters” signifies his universal knowledge. | The “dramatic proclamation” is āsabhiṁ vācaṁ, literally the “voice of a bull”. Other contexts show that this is is an expression emphasizing speech that is dramatic and imposing (SN 52.9:3.2, DN 28:1.5 = SN 47.12:5.2). | At Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 6.1.1 and Chāndogya Upaniṣad 5.1.1 the “vital breath” (prāṇa) is said to be “eldest and first” (jyeṣṭhaśca śreṣṭhaśca). ↩

Many of the details of the following account were later incorporated into the life of Gotama, under the principle that the major events of the lives of Buddhas follow a natural order. Nonetheless, they are not always consistent with other accounts in early texts. For example, in the Attadaṇḍasutta the Buddha says his going forth was prompted by disillusionment and fear due to chronic conflict and warfare (Snp 4.15). ↩

In Snp 3.11, the newborn Siddhattha is examined by the dark hermit Asita. These two versions are combined in later accounts. ↩

Asita did not look at the 32 marks, and he predicted only one destiny: that he would become a Buddha. ↩

Various “treasures” (ratana) or “gems” of a king are discussed in such texts as Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 5.3.1. ↩

The marks are elsewhere listed in DN 30:1.2.1 and MN 91:9.1. Here I list the related marks in the Bṛhatsaṁhitā as identified by Nathan McGovern (On the Origins of the 32 Marks of a Great Man, Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies, 2016, vol. 39, pp. 207–247). ↩

This echoes the posture of the newborn bodhisatta, and has the same meaning: that he will become awakened by “standing on his own two feet”. ↩

These are solar symbols, evoking the sun as the “twelve-spoked wheel of truth” (Rig Veda 1.164.11). They leave marks that were seen by Doṇa (AN 4.36:1.3). They are often depicted in Buddhist art, signifying the perfection and completeness of the traces that the Buddha leaves behind in his teachings and practice. Bṛhatsaṁhitā 69.17 lists several auspicious marks, including the wheel. ↩

Described as “abundantly long” at DN 30:1.12.8. ↩

Same at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.36. ↩

Tender feet at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.2. ↩

Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.2 has śliṣtāṅgulī (“compact or sticky fingers”). The commentary denies that the Pali jāla means a physical web. I think it means that the fingers and toes were usually held together rather than splayed, hence not letting things slip through the fingers. ↩

Ussaṅkha means “(curved) up like a shell”, while Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.2 says “curved up like a tortoise”. The descriptive verse at DN 30:1.21.12 shows that it refers to the tops of the feet. ↩

These are presumably the long, elegant rear calves of the Indian Blackbuck. ↩

This agrees with Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.35. ↩

Same at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.8. ↩

Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.102 says kings have a shining complexion. ↩

Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.102 mentions a “clean complexion” (śuddha). ↩

Same at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.5. ↩

Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.26 says those with hairs turning right become kings. ↩

Here brahm- is an adjective from √brah + ma, equivalent to the Sanskrit bṛṁh, having the sense “grown, extended”. The Sanskrit form here is bṛhadṛjugātra. ↩

Hands, feet, shoulders, and chest (DN 30:1.13.5). ↩

Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.18 compares not the chest but the hips with a lion. ↩

Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.27 says the heart is raised and muscular. ↩

Bṛhatsaṁhitā 69.13 has the same proportions without the simile. These are the normal human proportions, yet we cannot touch our knees without bending. The only way these marks could be reconciled is if the arms were extra long and the length of the legs below the knees was extra long as well. And this is exactly what we are told: the ankles are stretched and long, and the calves are like those of an antelope, whose rear calves are long proportionate to the thigh. Thus in this regard the marks appear to be internally consistent, though not describing normal human anatomy. ↩

“Ridged taste buds” is rasaggasaggī. Rasa can mean either “taste” or “nutrition”, but the use of ojā in DN 30:2.9.8 confirms the latter. Gasa is “swallow” and per DN 30:2.7.4 it is the “conveyance of savor” (rasaharaṇīyo). Agga often means “best”, but this is derived from the primary sense of “peak”. The descriptors uddhagga (“raised”) at DN 30:2.7.4 and susaṇṭhitā (“prominent”) at DN 30:2.9.8 confirm that the latter is meant. The mark refers to taste buds raised in noticeable ridges on the tongue that absorb nutrition and aid digestion. It has often been interpreted as “excellent (aggī) sense (gasa) of taste (rasa)”, but this, being imperceptible to others, is rather a secondary consequence of the mark. ↩

Even, gapless, and white teeth are at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.52. ↩

Same at Bṛhatsaṁhitā 68.53. ↩

At Thig 13.1:6.2 Ambapālī describes her eyes as abhinīla. While some Indians do indeed have blue eyes, this probably describes a black so deep it appears blue. ↩

Cows have long and elegant eyelashes. ↩

The uṇhīsa is depicted as a bulge on the Buddha’s crown. ↩

This is the dakkhiṇā, the religious offering given in gratitude and respect for the services. ↩

His birth mother has passed away and there is no mention of a step-mother. ↩

Normally clairvoyance and related abilities are said to arise due to the power of the fourth jhāna, whereas here it comes naturally due to past kamma. After jhāna this ability is empowered by the radiant mind clear of hindrances, whereas here it seems to be a more limited ability to see clearly and in the dark. ↩

Vipassī’s name is simply the personal form of the word made famous in Buddhist meditation, vipassanā. This is usually rendered as “insight”, but the sense here is more like “clear seeing”. | Pali frequently blurs the line between names and epithets. Here we see how a name is given, not at birth, but as a descriptive nickname that caught on. ↩

Indian epistemology acknowledges two fundamental sources of knowledge: direct perception (paccakkha) and inference (anumāna). This passage shows that vipassanā includes both. I render vipassanā with “discernment” in an attempt to capture both nuances, rather than the standard “insight”. ↩

Here begins the story of the four signs that led to Vipassī’s going forth—an old man, a sick man, a dead man, and a renunciate. Later texts apply the same story to Siddhattha, indeed to all bodhisattvas. | These four “signs” (nimitta) are also called “messengers of the gods”, reckoned as five (MN 130) or three (AN 3.36). ↩

Antepuraṁ (“royal compound”) was the inner sanctum of the royal residence. Maximally it referred to the area enclosed by walls within which the ruling families and staff lived. It later became used in the more restricted sense of “harem”. ↩

“Brood” is pajjhāyati. He is having an existential crisis. ↩

In any story of prophecy, efforts are made to avert it and they invariably fail. This is a recursive property of prophetic myth. If the prophecy were averted, the myth would not exist and we would not know of it; but because the myth does exist, we know how it ends and the prophecy must come true. ↩

An existential crisis takes its own time; it cannot be rushed. ↩

Neither reading vilāta or milāta appears to occur elsewhere in this sense. The commentary says it is a bier (sivika). ↩

“Renunciate” is pabbajita (“one who has gone forth”), one of the many words for religious ascetics. It is a general term and does not specify his affiliation. ↩

“Celebrate” is sādhu, the famous Buddhist words of approval and rejoicing still heard every day in Theravāda Buddhist cultures. It later acquired the meaning “renunciate” but does not have that sense in early Pali. The virtues that he celebrates are common values of Indian religions. ↩

His apparently sudden decision to go forth arises only after an extensive period of crisis and contemplation. ↩

The idea that a whole populace would follow the bodhisatta on his renunciate path occurs several times in the Jātakas. ↩

Following the PTS edition in omitting janapada, which is absent from the commentary and the parallel passage at DN 19:58.3. ↩

This is the only place vāsūpagata (“entered his dwelling”) is added to this stock phrase. ↩

At SN 12.4–10 this same reflection is attributed to each of the seven past Buddhas, kicking off an investigation into dependent origination in reverse order, starting with the outcome: suffering. Here this is treated as a meditative contemplation, whereas the next sutta, DN 15 Mahānidānasutta, delves into the philosophical implications. ↩

The reflection shows how the bodhisatta is still digging into the trauma of discovering the reality of old age and death. ↩

Yoniso maniskāra (“rational application of mind”) is a distinctively Buddhist term that literally means “applying the mind by way of source”. It is mostly used in investigating causality, although over time it came to have a more general sense of “reflection, inquiry, attention”. ↩

Here begins the sequence of dependent origination. I give basic definitions of terms here, and more details in DN 15. See also my notes in the Nidānasaṁyutta, especially SN 12.1 and SN 12.2. | Rebirth is a necessary antecedent condition for old age and death. Note that it is not a sufficient condition for old age, for many die when young. ↩

Since there cannot be an end to the “birth” that starts this life, jāti means “rebirth”, the next stage in the ongoing cycle. ↩

Bhava means “being, existence, life” in the sense of “past and future lives”. It refers to the ongoing process of continued existence, transmigrating through life after life. By itself, bhava has a positive connotation, and represents the longing that many people have to continue to exist after death in a permanent and happy state. The Buddha, however, situates it as just one more dimension of the flow of conditions. ↩

“Grasping” (upādāna) at sensual pleasures, views, precepts and observances, and theories of a self (DN 15:6.3). Grasping has the active sense of “taking up” a new life, not just “clinging” to what one has. It has a dual sense, because it also means the “fuel” that sustains the fire of existence. ↩

Craving (taṇhā, literally “thirst”) and grasping have a similar meaning, but craving is primal desire while grasping is more complex, involving doctrines and behaviors. ↩

“Feeling” (vedanā) is more fundamental than the complex concept of “emotion”. It refers to the hedonic tone of experience as pleasant, painful, or neutral. ↩

“Contact” is literally “touch” (phassa), and refers to the stimulation that occurs when sense object meets sense organ in experience. ↩

The five senses with the mind as sixth. This topic is treated extensively throughout early Buddhism, with a special focus on understanding and restraining the pull of sense stimulation. Āyatana has a root sense “stretch”, from which derived senses include “dimension”, “field”, etc. ↩

“Name and form” (nāmarūpa) is a Vedic concept referring to the multiplicity of material forms (rūpa) and associated names (nāma), especially the individual “sentient organisms” such as gods and humans (Rig Veda 5.43.10, Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.6.1, Chāndogya Upaniṣad 6.3.2), which are ultimately absorbed into the divine, like rivers in the ocean (Muṇḍaka Upaniṣad 3.2.8, Praśna Upaniṣad 6.5). The Buddha treated “name” analytically as feeling, perception, intention, contact, and application of mind, and “form” as the four elements and derived matter (DN 15:20.8, MN 9:52.1–54.7, and SN 12.2:11.1). ↩

“Consciousness” (viññāṇa) is simple subjective awareness, the sense of knowing. It arises stimulated by either an external sense impression or a mental phenomena such as thought, memory, etc. It is the subjective awareness that makes the entire multiform world of concepts and appearances possible. Thus far the analysis agrees with Yājñavalkya, who says that the manifold appearances in the world arise from consciousness (etebhyo bhūtebhyaḥ samutthāya, Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 2.4.12). ↩

Here the Buddha decisively departs from Yājñavalkya’s view that individuated awareness (saññā) returns into “this great reality, infinite, unbounded, a sheer mass of consciousness” (idaṁ mahadbhūtam anantam apāraṁ vijñānaghana eva, Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 2.4.12). Consciousness (viññāṇa) is not a fundamental reality (mahadbhūta) underlying multiplicity, but rather a conditioned process that exists only together with name and form. ↩

Dependent origination normally continues with two further factors: choices and ignorance. The full series does not appear in the Dīghanikāya. This truncated series emphasizes the mutuality of name and form with consciousness, but does not preclude the normal linear series. Each presentation of dependent origination reveals a different aspect of a complex, ramified process. ↩

Note the use of repetition to sum up the main doctrinal teachings. This serves to lock the sequence in memory and ensure no items are missing or displaced, while for one who is reciting the text from memory it provides an opportunity to reflect and apply the meaning in their own experience. ↩

This phrasing recalls the Buddha’s first sermon (SN 56.11:5.1), an insight that is said to be common to all Buddhas (SN 56.12:1.1). Pubbe ananussutesu (“not learned before from another”) means that this is a fresh insight not passed down in an oral tradition. ↩

The PTS edition has vipassanā-maggo here, despite admitting the term is found in no manuscripts and is taken from the commentary, where it is clearly an explanation not a reading (maggoti vipassanāmaggo). This error is followed by Rhys Davids and Walshe in their translations. ↩

Insight into dependent origination here indicates the attaining of stream entry. ↩

The five grasping aggregates (pañcūpādānakkhandhā) are mentioned as a summary of suffering in the Buddha’s first sermon (SN 56.11:4.2). Most of the teachings on this topic are collected in the Khandhasaṁyutta at SN 22, but they are also found in the Dīghanikāya at DN 22:14.1, DN 33:1.11.45, DN 33:2.1.4, and DN 34:1.6.16. The contemplation on the aggregates dispels the mistaken assumption of a self. Many of the theorists in DN 1 identify the self with one or other of the aggregates. ↩

Saṅkhāra in early Buddhism has three main doctrinal senses. (1) The broadest sense is “conditioned phenomena”, which we find in the Dīghanikāya at DN 16:6.10.10, DN 17:2.16.1, and DN 34:1.8.59. This essentially means “everything except Nibbāna”. (2) Sometimes it is a physical or mental “process” or “activity” as at DN 18:24.1, where it refers to the gradual stilling of energies in the development of meditation. (3) In the five aggregates and dependent origination it has the sense of “morally potent volitions or choices” and is a synonym for cetanā (“intention”). It is defined as good, bad, and imperturbable choices (DN 33:1.10.77), the latter of which refers to the kamma of the fourth jhāna and above. In this sense it is the moral “choices” for good or ill that propel consciousness into a new rebirth. ↩

The radical thesis of the Buddha’s teaching is the idea that consciousness is merely another empirical phenomena that comes to an end, as is also emphasized in the concluding verses of DN 11. ↩

This indicates the attainment of arahantship, the complete release from all attachments leading to rebirth. ↩

No longer a bodhisatta, he is now called a Buddha for the first time. ↩

In early Buddhism, the idea of teaching the Dhamma only arose after awakening. ↩

A similar account is told of Gotama Buddha at SN 6.1:1.4, MN 26:19.2, MN 85:43.2, and Kd 1:5.2.2. ↩

Here “clinging” is ālaya, from a root meaning “to stick”. ↩

“Specific conditionality” (idappaccayatā) refers to the fact that dependent origination traces the specific conditions for other specific things: this conditions that. It is not a general principle of universal conditionality (“everything is interconnected”). ↩

“Stilling of all activities” (sabbasaṅkhārasamatho) is the cessation of all conditioned energies or phenomena. | “Attachment” here is upadhi, which is both the things of the world to which we cling, and the inner clinging. The Jains defined upadhi similarly (Tattvārthasūtra 9.26). The dominant meaning in Sanskrit is “fraud”, which perhaps informs the Buddhist sense. ↩

The commentary is careful to specify that the Buddha means physical exhaustion only. ↩

“Not supernaturally inspired” (anacchariyā) rejects the Vedic “channeling” of scripture from the Divinity, while “not learned before in the past” (pubbe assutapubbā), echoing the Dhammacakkappavattanasutta (SN 56.11:5.1), rejects the oral tradition. ↩

“Cloaked” is āvuṭā, which is from the same root as asaṁvutā in DN 14:1.17.5 above, as well as nīvaraṇa (“hindrance”). All these terms ultimately stem from the Vedic serpent Vṛtra (“the constrictor”) who wraps the world in darkness. ↩

Had he followed this inclination he would have been a paccekabuddha, a Buddha “awakened for himself”. ↩

In the accounts of Gotama’s life this is specified as Brahmā Sahampati (see MN 26:20.1 and note). This whole passage is a moment of high cosmic solemnity and drama. ↩

The Buddha teaches on the invitation of the highest divinity. This sets a precedent for Buddhists to refrain from proselytizing, but rather teach by invitation. These passages are still recited in some places to invite a teaching. ↩

Aññātāro is an agent noun in plural, literally “understanders”. ↩

Previously he simply reflected to himself, now he uses his psychic abilities to ascertain people’s spiritual potential. ↩

Indriya (“faculty”) is an abstract noun from indra, the name of the potent Vedic god of war. In the Vedas, Indra manifests his indriya by drinking soma. The drug enables him to release his full potential and power; originally this probably referred to drinking an amphetamine-like substance before battle. Here we see that it means something like “spiritual potential” which is unleashed by the practice of the eightfold path. ↩

Here we see a verbal echo of Sahampati’s martial origins. ↩

A “caravan leader” (satthavāha) guides their flock through treacherous deserts and wastelands, as illustrated at DN 23:23.3. | Anaṇa (“debtless”) is a technical term in the Vedic system. According to Manu 6.35–7, a renunciate must first pay off three debts: study of Vedas, begetting a son, and offering of sacrifices. One who goes forth with these debts unpaid is headed for a downfall. The Buddha has indeed paid off all these debts: he studied the Vedas under his former teachers (MN 26:15.6); he has a son Rāhula; and his path is regarded as the highest form of sacrifice (DN 5:24.1). But in Buddhism the concept is reinterpreted as meaning one has let go of all defilements, becoming a “perfected”, literally “worthy” one, after which one can eat almsfood free of debt (MN 124:38.1, SN 16.11:13.2). ↩

Pamuñcantu saddhaṁ has long troubled translators, as the basic sense of pamuñcantu is “release”. The problem is a long-standing one, for Sanskrit variants include pramodantu (“celebrate”) or praṇudantu kāṅkṣāḥ (“dispel doubts”). I think it is a poetic variant of adhimuñcantu, to “decide” or “commit” to faith. Pali commonly uses a synonymous verb to reinforce the sense of the noun. In Snp 5.19, muttasaddho, pamuñcassu saddhaṁ, and adhimuttacittaṁ are all used in this sense. ↩

In the account of Gotama, he first thinks to teach his former colleagues under whom he practiced the formless attainments. Here we see the start of a tendency in the legends of past Buddhas to erase the education among other spiritual teachers before awakening. Note that these two, who will become Vipassī’s chief disciples, are leading khattiya and brahmin sons of the royal household. Khaṇḍa was Vipassī’s brother, and the priest’s son was virtually family. ↩

Khema (“sanctuary”) originally meant “oasis”. It is common name for lakes and nature parks in the Jātakas. ↩

There is a clear distinction between such managed “parks” and wilderness regions (arañña). ↩

In the early period, there was no distinction between “going forth” (pabbajjā) and “ordination” (upasampadā). They refer to two sides of the same coin: leaving the home life and entering the ascetic life. Ordination was originally granted with the simple call, “Come mendicant!” (ehi bhikkhu). ↩

Thus they became arahants, realizing the same truth that Vipassī had. ↩

As at Kd 1:11.1.4 and SN 4.5:2.3. One of the Buddha’s first acts is to empower his students. ↩

In the Vinaya of the current Buddha, the recitation occurs every fortnight on the uposatha (“sabbath”), and it includes only the mendicants resident in a specific monastery. Here they gathered from all over India. ↩

“Black Plum Tree Land” is jambudīpa, the South Asian subcontinent, including India, Pakistan, Nepal, Bangladesh, and Afghanistan. The number 84,000 does not seem excessive, as the Chinese pilgrims recorded many thousands of monasteries throughout India. In modern Thailand there are around 40,000 monasteries. ↩

The verses that follow form the climax of the whole discourse. They are known as the Ovāda Pātimokkha, the “monastic code for exhortation”. It seems that they were recited on the uposatha in the days before the establishment of the list of rules that is also called pātimokkha. Most of the extant Vinayas still include these verses in the pātimokkha texts, the Pali being a notable exception. ↩

The Buddha redefines tapas from painful mortification to gentle acceptance. | See the Jain Ācaraṅga 8.25, titikkhaṁ paramaṁ. ↩

These verses speak of “Buddhas” in plural. ↩

These famous lines serve as a succinct summary of the entire Buddhist path. ↩

“Embrace” is upasampadā, to “enter into”. It is the same word used for taking ordination as well as entering jhāna. ↩

Through meditation. ↩

The buddhasāsana (“instruction of the Buddha” or “dispensation of the Buddha”) is the normal word used by Buddhists to refer to their own religion. ↩

Here “monastic code” means the principles outlined in these verses. They are spelled out in more detail in the Gradual Training (DN 2, etc.), and ultimately in the detailed legal code of the Vinayapiṭaka. ↩

The “higher mind” is the four jhānas (AN 3.90:3.2). ↩

The Buddha now returns to the present life. Ukkaṭṭhā is the home of Pokkharasāti (DN 3:2.13.1) and the site of the astonishing and cosmically significant discourses MN 1 and MN 49. ↩

Only non-returners are born in the pure abodes (suddhāvāsā), from where they realize full awakening. ↩

“Order of gods” is devanikāya. I use “deity” to distinguish devatā from deva but there is no substantial difference. ↩

This is a list of the major events in any Buddha biography. ↩

The lifespan in such a realm can be many hundreds of eons. ↩

These are absent in the Pali text at this point, but they are mentioned below, and the commentary says they should be included here. ↩

This is the detailed answer to the question asked by the mendicants at DN 14:1.13.6. ↩

This sutta with its commentary was translated by Bhikkhu Bodhi in his The Great Discourse on Causation. It is the longest and most complex discourse on dependent origination in early Buddhism. ↩

The Kurukṣetra was an ancient Brahmanical kingdom situated in the region around modern Delhi, bordered by the Ganges in the east, the Sarasvatī in the west, the Himalayas in the north, and the hills of the Aravalli Range in the south. The Mahābharata climaxes with the battle fought there between the Kurus and the Pāṇḍavas. These events, to the extent that they can be established historically, took place several centuries before the Buddha. Kuru marks the north-western extent of the Buddha’s travels. Kammāsadamma is identified with modern Kumashpur in Haryana, about 40 km north of Delhi. ↩

While we cannot date this text, the fact that Ānanda has evidently been studying deep matters for a long time, that it takes place outside the Buddha’s accustomed locales, and that it builds on teachings found elsewhere, suggests that it happened rather late in the Buddha’s life. At SN 12.60 we find the same introduction to a much shorter discourse. ↩

At SN 6.1:1.6 (and DN 14:3.1.6 in the case of Vipassī), the Buddha hesitated to teach because dependent origination is so hard to see. Ānanda was not only learned and wise, he was a stream-enterer, and therefore must have directly experienced dependent origination (SN 12.27:5.1, SN 12.41:12.1), yet he still underestimates it. ↩

The sutta introduce subtle variations in the standard formula as a means to illuminate hidden implications and dimensions. ↩

The Buddha establishes the primary purpose of dependent origination: to understand transmigration so as to be free from it. ↩

Dependent origination is here taught in reverse order, starting with the existential problem: we are all going to die. This factor and the next are resultant, so we cannot solve them directly. ↩

With this the Buddha denies the promise of immortality in this or any other realm. ↩

“Continued existence” (or “life”) is an encompassing term, including both resultant and causal dimensions. ↩

“Grasping” and “craving” (together with “ignorance” in the full sequence) are the defilements that drive the process on. It is here that the practice of the path takes effect, uprooting them entirely. ↩

The next three factors spell out the process of sense experience that unfolds automatically. Meditation slows it down so it can be seen clearly, but the process remains even for the perfected ones. ↩

Here we encounter the first unique feature of this sequence, as normally the six sense fields appear as the condition for contact. The reason for this special presentation becomes clear later on. ↩

The mutual conditioning of consciousness with name and form is a further subtlety of this presentation. We have met this idea before in DN 14:2.18.43; it also occurs in SN 12.65 and SN 12.67. Again, implications of this are explored below. ↩

The sequence is recapped in forward order (anuloma, Ud 1.1:1.4). ↩

The Buddha now takes up each of the terms in more depth. ↩

This emphatic phrasing drives home that “cessation” (nirodha) is not simply temporary suppression or non-arising, but permanent and complete absence. ↩

“Rebirth” (jāti) is defined as the birth of a new life, not as simple arising. ↩

The various terms for “cause” are used as synonyms (hetu, nidāna, samudaya, paccaya). The purpose of using different terms is not to add nuances, but to reinforce the central meaning and guard against the corruption of meaning; if one word is lost or misunderstood, the meaning of the sentence as a whole is not changed. ↩

These realms relate to the kamma that projects consciousness into them. The realms of “luminous form” (rūpabhava) and the “formless” (arūpabhava) are generated by the form and formless attainments respectively. Any other kamma, good or bad, pertains to the sensual realm (kāmabhava). All rebirth takes place in one or other of these realms. ↩

“Grasping” (upādāna) begins with the primal desire of the senses, but the three other graspings are rather intellectual and sophisticated. Only a grown human being with a developed linguistic ability is able to formulate a view to become attached to, and likewise with attachment to religious observances and vows, and to theories of a self. This is why the bulk of kamma is produced by adult humans, rather than by, say, animals or children, for whom these dimensions of grasping are nascent. ↩

“Craving” (taṇhā) is a fundamental desire or urge. Unlike grasping, it is fully active in children and animals. Often it has a threefold definition, which we find below, but in dependent origination it is usually defined in terms of the six senses, which relates it to the items to come. ↩

The usual threefold definition of feeling (pleasant, painful, neutral) is reframed in terms of the six senses. ↩

Here the Buddha introduces another, even more radical, departure from the typical sequence. Rather than continue back to contact and name and form, he branches out in an entirely new direction. These “nine things rooted in craving” are found independently at AN 9.23:1.2 and DN 34:2.2.31, but only here are they integrated with the standard dependent origination. ↩

While the purpose of the main dependent origination is to disclose the web of conditions that generates the suffering of transmigration, here the Buddha looks at the arising of social conflict and disorder. ↩

In DN 27 Aggaññasutta the Buddha narrates a legend showing how these things arise. The point is not that we should not safeguard (ārakkha) our possessions. It is, rather, that so long as we live in a world where safeguarding possessions is necessary, there will be conflict and violence. ↩

“Stinginess” is macchariya. ↩

There are many words in Pali that approximate the English word “attachment”. Here it is ajjhosāna. ↩

“Evaluation” is vinicchaya. We like to weigh up and consider the pros and cons of different objects of desire. ↩

Those who have nothing are grateful for any small thing, and do not indulge in picking and choosing. ↩

Our senses are tuned to hunt out and acquire pleasure. ↩

This is the normal definition of craving in the four noble truths, supplementing the previous definition in terms of the six senses. Both are included in this sutta to show that they do not contradict, but rather reveal different aspects of the same thing. It is not just sensual desire that drives acquisition. For example, religious people fight over sacred ground or holy objects to gain a place in heaven; or else those driven by nihilism go to any lengths for alcohol or drugs to erase existence. ↩

The threefold analysis of feeling leads to the process of acquisition, while the sixfold analysis of feeling leads to dependent origination. ↩

And now we rejoin the main sequence. ↩

People mostly want to enjoy pleasant sensations, in this life and the next, but those sensations depend on a constant supply of the appropriate stimuli. ↩

Name and form are said to be conditions for contact also at Snp 4.11:11.1. ↩

The “set of mental phenomena known as name” is nāmakāya. Its function depends not on any underlying essence, but on the “features” by which it is “made known”; this is a phenomenological analysis. | “Labeling contact” is adhivacanasamphassa; it is the active process by which the mind makes sense of the world by attaching labels to experience. This passage reinforces the linguistic significance of nāma. ↩

The “set of physical phenomena known as form” is rūpakāya. | “Impingement contact” is paṭighasamphassa. Here paṭigha refers to the “striking” of physical phenomena against each other, such as light “hitting” the eye. It most commonly appears in this sense in the formula that begins the formless attainments. ↩

Labeling moves from the mind to the world; impingement moves from the world to the mind. Together they create a dynamic two-way process by which we learn about the world and how to make sense of it. ↩

Contact is fundamentally a meeting, normally expressed as the coming together of the sense stimulus (light), the sense organ (eye), and sense consciousness. By skipping the direct mention of the six senses, the Buddha opens another perspective on this process: mental labeling meets sense impingement, each essential to the other, and together making contact possible. The analysis itself exemplifies this process, as it starts by looking at the process from each side, and moves toward integration, seeing them both together. ↩

Consciousness in dependent origination is normally defined as the six kinds of sense consciousness (SN 12.2:12.3). The purpose of this is to emphasize that the process of rebirth and transmigration is an empirical process, which depends on the same ordinary consciousness we are experiencing now. Here, once again, by skipping the six senses, a new mode of analysis opens up, which emphasizes the organic growth of the individual. ↩

“Conceived” is okkamissatha, literally “descend” or “arrive”. | “Coagulate” assumes the PTS reading samucchissatha (Sanskrit sammurch). I believe this echoes the belief that the embryo is “coagulated” from the mix of blood and semen. Compare the Jain term sammūrcchana, “congealment”, which covers all kinds of birth not from a uterus or spontaneous (Tattvārtha Sūtra 2.35). | Linguistically, this passage through to DN 15:22.2 is marked with the extremely rare verbal ending -issatha, which is the middle form of the third person singular conditional. ↩

“Miscarried” is vokkamissatha. | “This place” is itthattā, which is most commonly found in the declaration of the arahant that they will no longer be reborn in “this place”, namely transmigration. | Here “born” is abhinibbatti, which is listed along with jāti, okkanti, and other terms as a synonym in the standard definition of rebirth (SN 12.2:4.2, MN 9:24–26.7, DN 22:18.4). ↩

The connection between dependent origination and childhood development is further explored in MN 38:28.1. ↩

Now we turn to the mirror side of the pair of conditions. ↩

Just as name and form—the organic, sensual, and sense-making body—cannot grow without consciousness, so too consciousness must acquire a landing or grounding place to be “planted” in name and form. | Dukkhasamudayasambhavo (“the coming to be of the origin of suffering”) might be rendered “the coming to be and origin of suffering”. However, dukkhasamudaya occurs some hundreds of times in the sense “origin of suffering” so I take it in the same way here. This is supported by the PTS variant reading dukkhasamudayo sambhavo. ↩

This passage continues to employ rare middle forms, this time -etha, the third person singular optative. ↩

This passage explains why the sequence ends here rather than proceeding in the usual way to choices and ignorance. Any state of being ultimately depends on the codependency of name and form with consciousness. Within this key relationship is the extent not only of language, but also of wisdom, and the secret to the undoing of transmigration itself. One of the many profound implications of this is that there is no such thing as a state of pure consciousness independent of concepts. | Ettāvatā vaṭṭaṁ vattati itthattaṁ paññāpanāya should be read with such passages as SN 22.56:5.3: ye kevalino vaṭṭaṁ tesaṁ natthi paññāpanāya (“For consummate ones, there is no cycle of rebirths to be found”). | In Chāndogya Upaniṣad 7.1.5, one who worships Divinity as name can do as they please “within the limits of name” (yāvannāmno gataṁ). | The Mahāsaṅgīti reading aññamaññapaccayatā pavattati is spurious, since it inserts an Abhidhamma concept from the commentary. ↩

The text now turns to an analysis of theories of “self” (attā), which is comparable to some of the passages of DN 1. The Buddha began his discourse by stating that it is the failure to understand dependent origination that keeps beings trapped in transmigration. Dependent origination explains transmigration in a purely empirical way by inferring from the mental and physical phenomena we experience here and now. Self theorists, on the other hand, explain transmigration by introducing a new metaphysical principle, the “self” or “soul”, by which they assume that the individual has an eternal underlying essence. ↩

“Formed” is rūpī (“possessing form”), identifying the self with the first of the five aggregates. If something were really the core essence of a person, you would think it is readily knowable. But the Buddha shows that theorists describe the self in multiple different and incompatible ways. Each of these draws on some more-or-less arbitrary aspect of empirical reality, such as “form”, to describe an unknowable metaphysical entity that is in fact just pure supposition. ↩

An example of a self that is “physical and limited” would be the body. ↩

Such as the cosmos. ↩

Perhaps this is the self of “limited perception” (DN 1:2.38.13). This would be where the mind is aware of something limited, and the self is identified with the mental dimension of that awareness. ↩

Such as the formless dimensions. ↩

The three options (“it is”, “it will be so”, and “I will make it be so”) illustrate how the theorist resorts to ever more convoluted means to justify the lack of empirical support for their pet theory. | Bhāviṁ (“sure to become”) is the root bhū with the primary affix -ī, which connotes an inevitable future state. | Tattha (“in some other place”, literally “there”) is explained by the commentary as paraloke (“in the next world”). ↩

Their surface differences rest on the same underlying assumption, so if the assumption is disproved there is no need to refute each individual theory. | Iccālaṁ resolves to iti alaṁ. ↩

This is the Buddha, who does not theorize a metaphysical self. Implicit in this argument is Occam’s razor, “entities must not be multiplied beyond necessity”. Since the self theorists want to prove the existence of the “self”, it is up to them to supply the grounds to support their suppositions. Since they fail to do so, the rational position is that there is no self. The Buddha is not under a similar obligation to prove the non-existence of the “self”, since it is reasonable to assume that things do not exist until the evidence says otherwise. ↩

Having asserted a metaphysical “self”, the theorists go on to make certain observations and interpretations regarding it. ↩

The Buddha moves from theories of the self as form to feeling, the second of the five aggregates. ↩

For example, identifying the self with the supposed eternal bliss of heaven. As with the description of self in physical terms, the theorist proceeds from a simple assertion of identity to more complicated hypotheses. ↩

This is the inverse of the previous. The self is still defined in relation to feeling, but it is a negative relation. Such theories are commonly found in the Upaniṣads, where a prominent thread of analysis systematically rejects all the things that are not the self (neti), before finally arriving at what is the self (eg. Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.5.15). ↩

Here the theorist describes feeling as a function of the self: it is not what the self is, but what the self does. At MN 38:5.11 (= MN 2:8.8), Sāti describes the self as consciousness, “the speaker and feeler who experiences the results of good and bad deeds in all the different realms”. ↩

The Buddha goes on to develop specific arguments addressing each position. ↩

The Buddha points out the universal experience of feeling, thus establishing his argument on common ground. This same argument is found at MN 74:10.1. ↩

The idea that only one kind of feeling can be experienced at a time became an adage of Buddhist psychology, but it is not obvious to me that it is the case. Here and at MN 74 it is assumed to be a shared belief with non-Buddhists. ↩

Feeling is part of the fundamental structure of consciousness. This argument comes through more clearly in Pali, for the word for “feeling” (vedanā) is derived from and still lies close to the sense of “knowing, experiencing”. Thus the question is, “If there was no mind, would there be the thought ‘I am this’?” The commentary explains that this refers to the bare material realm which is devoid of consciousness. The commentary appears to support the variant reading ahamasmī here. This makes sense in context, for “I am” is the first and most primordial assertion of a self, while “I am this” is a more sophisticated identification of the self in relation to the aggregates. ↩

The theorist avoids identifying feeling as the self, but they must identify something as the self (as for example, Sāti said the self was viññāṇa). Feeling, however, is deeply wound into the structure of consciousness, so if feeling were to be utterly absent, no other mental phenomena could continue, and there would therefore be no possibility of forming a theory of self. ↩

Letting go is not just a conceptual matter, it has immediate emotional consequences. Paritassati conveys the twin senses of desire and agitation, for which “anxiety” seems the best fit. ↩

This recalls the similar statement at DN 15:22.6. Whereas there it was a statement about name and form with consciousness, here it is a description of the arahant who has fully realized it. Unlike the theorists whose views do not withstand empirical scrutiny, the arahant’s liberation is based on a direct understanding of reality. | Nirutti means the “clear expression” or “definition” of a word. In the pre-Buddhist literature, that which is “undefined” is the mystical truth to be muttered under the breath, whereas that which is “defined” is clearly expressed in language. A list of such definitions is a nirukti, a glossary or dictionary. ↩

The Buddha returns once more to the question of rebirth, describing various states of rebirth in terms of consciousness. The seven planes are also mentioned at DN 33:2.3.28, DN 34:1.8.11, and AN 7.44:1.1. ↩

“Plane of consciousness” is viññāṇaṭṭhiti, which could also be rendered “station”. ↩

In the first of these dimensions there is no consciousness at all, and in the second there is no consciousness in the normal sense, which is why they cannot be called “planes of consciousness”. ↩

Abhinandituṁ, to “take pleasure in”, to “relish”, or to “delight in” appears in the standard formula for the second noble truth, where craving “takes pleasure in various realms” (tatratatrābhinandinī). ↩

One “freed by wisdom” has wisdom as the dominant faculty. ↩

The eight liberations (vimokkhā) are an alternative way of describing the meditative experiences of jhāna. Elsewhere they are listed at DN 16:3.33.1, DN 33:3.1.168, DN 34:2.1.191, AN 8.66, MN 77:22.1, and referred to at AN 4.189:1.8 and Thag 20.1:33.1. At AN 8.120 and MN 137:27.1 they are listed but not called the eight liberations. ↩

Someone sees a meditative vision based on the perception of their own body, such as through mindfulness of breathing or one’s own body parts. The first three liberations all cover the four jhānas. ↩

A meditator grounds their practice on some external focus, such as a light, the sight of a corpse, or an external element such as earth. ↩

This is a practice based on wholly pure and exalted meditation, such as the meditation on love, or the sight of a pure brilliant color like the sky. ↩

The “cessation of perception and feeling” (saññāvedayitanirodha) is a culminating meditation state of supreme subtlety that often leads directly to awakening (but see AN 5.166). The state itself, like all meditation states, is temporary, but afterwards the defilements can be eliminated forever. This liberating insight is the consequence of the balanced development of all eight factors of the path. ↩

This passage emphasizes that this person is fully adept and has mastered all the states of meditation. The Buddha claimed such mastery (AN 9.41:16.1), and retained the ability even on his deathbed (DN 16:6.8.1). ↩

Here we see the terms “one who is freed” used in two ways. All arahants have “freedom of heart” (by means of samādhi) and “freedom by wisdom” (the realization of the Dhamma). At the same time, one who emphasizes samādhi is said to have “freedom of heart” in contrast with one who emphasizes wisdom, who has “freedom by wisdom”. One who has consummate mastery of both samādhi and wisdom is said to be “freed both ways”. ↩

The longest of all early discourses, this dramatic and moving narrative tells the story of the Buddha’s slow journey toward his final passing. ↩

After the events of DN 2, Ajātasattu retained and consolidated his power. Magadha ultimately conquered the Vajji Federation and continued to expand until almost all of India was under its sway. ↩

According to the commentary, Ajātasattu’s anger was rooted in a dispute on trade routes. Control of shipping on the Ganges was essential for establishing international trade. There was a port on the Ganges extending over a league, split half and half between Magadha and Vajji. Valuable products were sourced from a mountain and brought down for trade, but the Vajjis kept absconding with the whole lot. The place is not identified, but Munger, a strategic port east of Patna, fits the description. The nearby hills have been mined since paleolithic times. It is also likely, as maintained in Jain tradition, that the Vajjis disputed Ajātasattu’s accession after committing regicide. His threatening posture toward the Vajjis is also mentioned in SN 20.8:2.2. ↩

Vassakāra appears in the suttas as a devoted follower of the Buddha. ↩

The Vajji Federation harks back to an early settlement founded by the legendary Nābhānediṣṭha in the Vedic period. It built its wealth on its extensive fertile plains and the trading possibilities opened up by the Gandak and Ganges rivers. ↩

While it may seem strange to consult the Buddha on such a violent plan, Ajātasattu knows from his experience in DN 2 that the Buddha will not hesitate to tell him the truth, even if it is bad news. It seems he is trying to avoid the downfall of tyrants who are surrounded only with yes men. ↩

Reading yojapetvā (“had them harnessed”), which is found in the Mahāsaṅgīti in similar passages, and in this passage in the PTS edition. ↩

Ānanda cares for the Buddha in his old age. Shortly after these events, Ānanda was entrusted with reciting the suttas at the First Council. This discourse would have been composed by him in the years following his Master’s death. More than a simple interlocutor, Ānanda shapes the story as its second lead, a relatable character with an empathetic point of view. He imbues the discourse with his emotional struggles as he deals with the Buddha’s passing and helps ensure the future survival of the Dhamma, while still developing his own meditation practice. ↩

As for example at AN 8.12:1.2. ↩

Harmony is especially important as the Vajji Federation was comprised of several different clans, among them the Licchavis of Vesālī, the Ñātikas just south of Vesālī, the Uggas of Hatthigāma (Elephant Village), and the Bhogas of Bhoganagara. Some sources say the Vajjis proper were another tribe within the alliance. The Videhans of Mithilā are also sometimes included, but several sources indicate that they remained an independent, if reduced, kingdom until they were conquered by Magadha some years later. The Mallas of Pāvā and Kusinārā formed a closely allied independent republic (MN 35:12.8). ↩

The “ancient Vajjian principles” (or “laws”, porāṇe vajjidhamme) would have been established with the founding of the Vajji Federation some centuries earlier, which ensured that the members of the federation would have a voice in the Licchavi-dominated union. Compare with the “ancient traditions of the brahmins” (porāṇā brāhmaṇadhammā at AN 5.191 and Snp 2.7), the falling away from which is said to be the cause of Brahmanical decline. Similarly, the Buddha elsewhere scolds the Vajjis for their indulgence (AN 5.143), suggesting that the decline may have already set in. ↩

This advocates for legal protection for women from sexual violence. | For various legal regulations regarding women and sex, see Kauṭilya’s Arthaśāstra 12. ↩

The Buddha will stay at several of these shrines later in this discourse. They were sacred groves, maintained by the people in reverence for the powerful spirits of nature. | “Spirit-offerings” is bali. | The commentary explains “inner or outer” as inside or outside the town. ↩

It is an old Indian belief that the presence of holy persons provides a kind of umbrella effect that protects the realm. ↩

This event is recorded at AN 7.21, where the Buddha addresses the Licchavis. That chapter of the Aṅguttara mostly consists of the teachings found here presented as separate suttas. | The Sārandada shrine was short walk from Vesālī (AN 5.143). ↩

There is a certain tension here: the Buddha taught these principles to the Vajjis, one of which is that the Vajjis should not adopt new decrees. It seems that a “decree” (paññatta) is more like constitutional law, whereas a “principle” (dhamma) is more like a behavioral guideline. ↩

Upalāpana is used a number of times in the Vinaya, where it always has the sense of giving someone something to get them to do what you want. It has the same sense at SN 3.25:4.13, where an enemy king may be bribed with gold from the royal treasury. | The commentary says that Vassakāra himself was assigned with the task of weakening the Vajjis in this way. ↩

There were several monasteries and hermitages around Rājagaha (Kd 2:11.1.1). ↩

Also at AN 7.23. ↩

This especially refers to the fortnightly uposatha. Despite the dangers faced in the rugged hills around Rājagaha (Kd 2:12.1.1), the Buddha insisted that all monks of the locality attended the uposatha (Kd 2:5.3.1). ↩

The Buddha encouraged the mendicants to recite the Dhamma in harmony (MN 103:3.2), to resolve issues in harmony (MN 104:14.3), and on the uposatha to recite and train in the pātimokkha in harmony (Bu As 7:4.11). ↩

Picking up from the similar injunction to the Vajjis, this kicks off a long narrative arc that binds together the Buddha’s invitation to abolish the minor rules (DN 16:6.3.1) with the bad monk Subhadda’s seizing on the Buddha’s death as an excuse to give up the rules, which was the direct motivation for the First Council (DN 16:6.20.3 = Kd 21:1.1.24), at the end of which the Saṅgha agreed not to abolish any rules (Kd 21:1.9.20), a decision that was affirmed a century later at the Second Council (Kd 22). ↩

The nature of seniority in the Saṅgha is often misunderstood. There is no “hierarchy” (literally “rule of priests”) in the sense of power-based relationships: no monastic has the authority to command another monk or nun. Seniority is owed respect, not obedience. ↩

This stands in place of the injunction against sexual violence, both principles being concerned with the harmful effects of desire. ↩

This stands in place of the injunction to maintain the shrines, where mendicants would frequently stay. ↩

This stands in place of the injunction to look after arahants. ↩

Also at AN 7.24. ↩

“Work” is kamma, which especially means “building work”. Of course it is essential to do work, but one should not get too caught up in it. The Buddha did not believe that working hard was ennobling in and of itself. ↩

“Corrupt wishes” (pāpicchā) is defined as when a faithless person wishes to be known as faithful, or person otherwise lacking good qualities wishes to be known as having them (AN 10.23:6.2). ↩

This item and the preceding two were the downfall of Devadatta (Iti 89). ↩

Also at AN 7.25. ↩

Also at SN 46.25 and AN 7.26. ↩

As at AN 7.27. These “perceptions” are all meditation practices which are described at AN 10.60. ↩

These six principles are found in several places, but they are not elsewhere called “principles that prevent decline”; for example at AN 6.11 they are called “warm-hearted qualities” (dhammā sāraṇīyā). At AN 6.22, however, a different six qualities are called “principles that prevent decline”: not relishing work, talk, sleep, and company, being easy to admonish, and having good friends. ↩

This is the right view of the noble eightfold path, in other words, the four noble truths. ↩

This epitome of the Dhamma is repeated eight times in this discourse, summarizing the teachings in the Gradual Training. It is not found in this exact form elsewhere. ↩

“Imbued” (paribhāvita) as a mother hen imbues her eggs with warmth by sitting on them (AN 7.71:2.2). See also SN 55.21:2.3. ↩

Some editions add diṭṭhāsava (“defilement of views”), but since that appears to be a late interpolation I follow the Mahāsaṅgīti in omitting it. ↩

This is the same rest-house at which the Buddha sojourned on his way from Rājagaha to Nāḷandā in the Brahmajālasutta (DN 1). ↩

This was apparently the last time that the Buddha met Sāriputta. This encounter is recorded in an independent sutta at SN 47.12 and expanded into a long discourse at DN 28. The Saṁyutta follows this meeting with the record of Sāriputta’s passing at SN 47.13, and then the lament for the absence of both Sāriputta and Moggallāna at SN 47.14. For some reason these events were omitted from the present discourse, even though they fit well thematically. ↩

As at DN 14:1.37.4, inference (anvaya) is regarded as a valid form of knowledge. The Buddha himself is said to rely on inference using the same simile at AN 10.95:10.4. See SN 12.33 and notes for discussion. ↩

This is modern Patna. In this account we see how it was developed from the simple riverside village of Pāṭaligāma to the citadel of Pāṭaliputta. Ajātasattu ultimately moved the capital of Magadha from the defensively-postured Rājagaha surrounded by hills to this trading center on open waters. Under Ashoka it became one of the greatest cities of the ancient world. It was named after the pāṭalī tree (Stereospermum chelonoides), known as patala in Hindi. ↩

Also at AN 5.213, Ud 8.6:4.1, DN 33:2.1.36, and Kd 1:28.4.1. ↩

The Buddha begins with the things most obvious and pertinent to the audience. ↩

Bewildered by fear and regret. ↩

Suññāgāra normally means an “empty dwelling”, but here the commentary describes it as a curtained-off cubicle. ↩

Vassakāra was no dawdler, as he preceded the Buddha to Pāṭaligāma. And not long after, he returned to Rājagaha to build more fortifications there (MN 108:6.2). | Nagara here means “citadel, fortress”, not “city”. It has the same sense as pura. The construction is defensive and may well have begun before Ajātasattu began thinking of invading. ↩

The relation between deities and building sites (vatthu) appears only in this passage in the early texts (repeated at Ud 8.6:15.2 and Kd 1:28.7.3). Divination and geomancy (vatthuvijjā) for building sites is said to be a wrong livelihood at DN 1:1.21.2. ↩

From this point, later texts always refer to Pāṭaliputta, but the reason for the change of name from Pāṭaligāma is not explained in the commentary. Putta is a suffix indicating the people of a certain clan or place, so pāṭaliputta means “a person from Pāṭalī (village)” or as we might say, “Pāṭalian”. As the city became well known and its identity as a village receded, it must have become known as the “city of the Pāṭaliputtas” and hence simply Pāṭaliputta. Compare the uses of ñātika below. | The commentary explains that puṭabhedanaṁ refers to the “opening of packages”, signifying that it was a center of trade. This usage is attested as late as the 13th century Jain Vividhatīrthakalpa of Jinaprabhasūri. | “Civilized region” is ariyaṁ āyatanaṁ, the cultural region defined by use of the Ariyaka language (cf. AN 6.96:1.3, Ud 8.6:17.9 and note to DN 26:4.8). ↩

Excavations reveal that Pāṭaliputta was constructed of wood, so the danger of fire was real. It is situated on a low-lying flood plain of the Ganges, so flooding would also have been an obvious danger. As for dissension (mithubheda), Vassakāra had indicated that this was a means of bringing down the Vajjis, so it would seem that kamma was lying in wait for them. ↩

This is the anumodanā recited for the meal offering. Other examples are found at Snp 3.7:34.3 = MN 92:25.6, SN 55.26:20.1, Kd 1:15.14.4, and Kd 1:1.5.1. | It is worth noting that no early anomodanā uses the imperative verb form -tu signifying giving a blessing (eg. bhavatu sabbamaṅgalaṁ, “may all blessings be”). They strictly use the indicative -ti to teach cause and effect: if you do this, that happens. ↩

Buddhism promotes good neighborliness with all beings, seen and unseen. Making an offering to the local spirits helps create a positive and healthy sense of place. ↩

At AN 4.67:8.3 a similar sentiment is expressed for animals. ↩

The “ford” (tittha) is symbolic; those who forge a path to salvation are called titthakara, such as the six leading ascetics of DN 2. Today there is a 5.7 km bridge at this crossing, which is appropriately called the Mahatma Gandhi Setu. ↩

“Dinghy” translates uḷumpa. ↩

In this stock phrase, we sometimes find paccuṭṭhāsi (“landed”) and sometimes pāturahosi (“reappeared”). ↩

Aṇṇavaṁ cannot mean “sea” here, since it is to be crossed with a bridge. ↩

Koṭigāma lay a short distance from the Ganges. The Buddha’s stay here must therefore have followed the events of SN 47.14 at Ukkacelā on the Vajjian bank of the Ganges, where he laments the passing of Sāriputta and Moggallāna. He would have heard of Sāriputta’s passing before then, while on the road from Nāḷandā to Pāṭaligāma, even though that is implausibly said to have happened at Sāvatthī (SN 47.13). ↩

Also at SN 56.21. ↩

Ñātika (also spelled nātika, or nādika; Sanskrit jñātṛka; Prākrit nāyika) was the clan to which the Jain leader Mahāvīra (called Nāṭaputta, i.e. Ñātiputta) belonged. Here it is unusually spelled in plural, which means “the land of the Ñātika clan”. | Despite the variant spellings, the commentary supports Ñātika, explaining that it is one of two villages by a lake originally settled by the sons of two brothers, hence being “of the relatives” (ñātika). ↩

Here Ñātika is in singular and appears to be the name of a town. Thus Ñātika is first of all a name of a clan, then the land they live in, then their chief town. | Over a millennium previously, the Indus Valley Civilization had built cities of fired brick with standardized size and construction methods, but in the Buddha’s day most buildings were wood. This is the only brick building mentioned in the suttas; brick construction is also discussed in the Vinaya. ↩

It is unprecedented to discuss the spiritual destinies of an entire town like this. Normally this question is only asked when specific individuals known to the Buddha have passed away. Likely the passage was created in the wake of the passing of Mahāvīra to show that even his own people were enthusiastic Buddhists. This portion of the text is also found at SN 55.8. ↩

SN 55.9 inserts another series on a monk, nun, layman, and laywoman all called Asoka. ↩

This portion of the text is at SN 55.10. I spell names consistently with there. ↩

The suttas consistently depict lay folk as attaining the third stage of awakening, non-return, but not the highest stage of arahantship, except in rare cases on the deathbed. The tradition extended this by saying that if a lay person becomes an arahant, they must ordain or die that day, but this is not supported in the early texts. The point is not whether you receive an ordination, but whether you let go of attachments. ↩

The commentary to the Saṁyutta attributes the large number of deaths to a recent plague (ahivātaroga, “viper’s breath disease”). This deadly contagion was known to kill off entire families (Kd 1:50.1.1). According to the commentaries, the same disease once afflicted Vesālī, prompting the teaching of the Ratanasutta (Snp 2.1, Kp 6). ↩

Mirrors are for doing makeup (DN 1:1.16.2) or admiring oneself (MN 77:33.18), which a mendicant should not do (Kd 15:2.4.1). In the Dhamma a mirror is for self-reflection (MN 61:8.2), while the mind is purified like polishing a mirror (AN 3.70:13.4). ↩

The four principles that follow are elsewhere identified as four factors of stream-entry (AN 9.27). At SN 12.41, understanding of dependent origination is included. ↩

“Experiential” is avecca, literally “having undergone”. “Experiential confidence” is the faith of a stream-enterer, who has seen for themselves. ↩

They have experiential confidence in the Buddha as a teacher because they have followed his path and realized the results that he speaks of. ↩

A stream-enterer has direct experience of the four noble truths, so they have confirmed that the teaching is indeed realizable in this very life. ↩

The suttas distinguish between two senses of Saṅgha. The “mendicant Saṅgha” (bhikkhusaṅgha) is the conventional community of monks and nuns. The “Saṅgha of disciples” (sāvakasaṅgha) is classified as fourfold according to the stages of awakening: stream-entry, once-return, non-return, and perfection. Each of these stages is further subdivided into those of the path who are practicing for realization and those of the fruit who have realized. These are referred to as “noble disciples”, four of the path and four of the fruit, making eight individuals in total. ↩

This entails keeping the five precepts at a minimum. ↩

Ambapālī means “protector of mangoes”. Here the text just says she had a “grove”, but it is identified as a mango grove below (DN 16:2.14.1). ↩

In some versions, the Buddha is said to have taught the monks mindfulness in anticipation of the arrival of the beautiful courtesan. ↩

In the Gradual Training the mendicant “establishes mindfulness” to begin meditation. Here this practice is expanded, and in DN 22 it is expanded even further. ↩

The locative idiom kāye kāyānupassī indicates that the meditator focuses on a particular aspect of body contemplation, such as observing the breath, awareness of the body parts, or reflection on the four elements. | “Rid of desire and aversion for the world” refers to clearing the mind through the previous practice of sense restraint. ↩

Dhammā here refers to the “principles” of cause and effect and the four noble truths which are understood by reflecting on the psychology of meditation itself. In this context dhammā does not mean “mental objects” or “phenomena” or “mental qualities”. ↩

A gaṇikā was a trained entertainer and escort whose company commanded a high fee (Kd 8:1.1.7). It was a respected position, as we see the city guild of Rājagaha, with King Bimbisāra’s blessing, appoint the young woman Sālavatī in a similar position (Kd 8:1.2.13). ↩

The text spends more time on the Vajjis’ appearance than on Ambapālī’s. At Thig 15.1:12.1 the nun Isidāsī recalls how she used to do the makeup for her husband every day, like his own personal beautician. ↩

There are various reading for paṭivaṭṭesi. The commentary glosses with pahari (“struck, collided”). ↩

The derogatory indeclinable vocative je is otherwise used of the “naughty maid” Kāḷī at MN 21:9.13. “Wench” is a term meant to insult on the basis of servitude or promiscuity, so it seems appropriate. The Licchavis are not distinguishing themselves here; given their youth, wealth, licentiousness, and evident familiarity with Ambapālī, it seems safe to conclude that they had been her clients. ↩

Dassatha is second future plural of dadāti. The Vinaya parallel at Kd 6:30.4.5 uses optative forms instead. | “With provinces” is sāhāraṁ (literally “with food”, commentary: sajanapadaṁ) refers to the holdings around the city that supplied food and other necessities. ↩

Despite the context, ambakā has no etymological relation to amba (“mango”) but is a term for “woman, mother”, used here as a play on words. ↩

This demonstrates that a woman of Ambapālī’s profession could own land and control significant resources. ↩

An ārāma is a tended and pleasant ground, a “park”. Here it has previously been referred to as “grove” (vana) and “mango grove”. Usually in the suttas, however, it is a name for a place where monastics live. In English, monastics don’t live in parks, they live in monasteries. So once a place has been dedicated for the Saṅgha, I translate ārāma as “monastery”. ↩

Pali texts waver between beluva (“wood-apple”) and veḷuva (from veḷuvant, “full of bamboo”). ↩

The Buddha was travelling with a large retinue, which could become burdensome on a small village if they were to stay the three months of the rains residence. The texts note several monasteries and places to stay around Vesālī. ↩

Here upaṭṭhāka refers to the lay devotees, who the Buddha informs below. | Apaloketi (“take leave”) also has a literal sense of “glance back”; both senses are found in the sutta (see DN 16:4.1.2). ↩

“Life force” is jīvitasaṅkhāra whereas below we find āyusaṅkhāra (DN 16:3.10.1). They are evidently synonyms; Ps 1.6:4.3 refers to the three jīvitasaṅkhāras from MN 43:24.2, but there the text has āyusaṅkhāra. The sense is not “will to live” but “life force”, i.e. the vital energy that sustains life (SN 20.6:3.2, MN 43:23.1). This leans on the old use of Sanskrit samas kurva or saṁskāra for the “reviving” or “rejuvenation” of the god Pajāpati when he is depleted by the act of creation, like a fire run low or a man after sex (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 7.2.1.5 et passim). ↩

This is the first indication of Ānanda’s fragile emotional state in the days to come. | Read diṭṭhā (Sanskrit diṣṭyā), “fantastic, how fortunate”, per DN 26:21.9 and Ja 81:1.4. ↩

Previously the Buddha had spoken of “taking leave” of the Saṅgha, but here something more specific is meant. Udāharati is typically used when a previously-mentioned matter (often unpleasant) is “brought up”, as at the monastic procedures for confession or invitation to admonish (Kd 1:16.2.5, Kd 1:2.1.9). Ānanda is implying that there is some unfinished disciplinary business that needs attention. Despite the Buddha’s response, he did in fact go on to make a number of statements and rulings. ↩

For forty-five years he had been teaching and supporting the community. ↩

A principle not followed by some contemporary Buddhist schools that harbor “secret teachings”. ↩

“Closed fist of a tutor” is ācariyamuṭṭhi. Compare Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 6.2.4: “I have taught you all that I know.” ↩

Pariharissāmi needs careful parsing with regard to tenses. The general meaning is to “carry about” or “maintain, nurture”. The Buddha elsewhere said that he “leads” the Saṅgha (DN 26:25.6: pariharāmi). When the Buddha was about to go on retreat, Moggallāna said that he and Sāriputta “shall lead” (pariharissāmi), to which the Buddha said they “should lead” (MN 67:13.7: parihareyyaṁ). Devadatta, on the other hand, ensured his downfall when he determined that he “shall lead” the Saṅgha, having taken over from the Buddha (AN 5.100:2.3, Kd 1:2.1.23). Thus the future tense indicates the determination to lead. But at this point, the Buddha’s mind is already set on letting go. He is not saying that no one should lead the Saṅgha, but that it is up to whoever leads it to address the issues. ↩

The reading and derivation of veṭhamissakena are unclear. As a form of violence we find veṭhamissena at Thag 2.12:1.1, notably also in instrumental. Veṭha means “twist, strap, turban”. Missa means “mixed” or “plaited” (Bu Ss 2:2.1.21). Thus it probably refers to a kind of strong twisted material used to tie or bind, i.e. rope. ↩

Compare Rig Veda 8.48.5: “As leather binds a chariot, soma knits my joints together.” Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.3.35 compares the labored breathing of one near death with the creaking of a heavily-laden cart. Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 13.2.7.8 says a handsome cart is well-finished with ropes. Indian carts were bound with ropes down to modern times. See too SN 41.5:5.5 and note. ↩

The suttas say little about this signless (animitta) meditation. Its defining characteristic is that consciousness does not “follow after signs” (nimittānusāri viññāṇaṁ, eg. AN 6.13:5.3). This is explained in MN 138:10.2 as not being distracted or affected by the features of sense impressions, as the “signs” are created by greed, hate, and delusion (MN 43:37.1). It is distinguished from the four kinds of mindfulness meditation (SN 22.80:8.4). The mental unification (ekattaṁ) based on this practice is listed after the form (and formless) jhānas, so it is very advanced. It is nonetheless a conditioned state (MN 121:11.4), so it is possible that a mendicant might fall from it and disrobe (AN 6.60:8.10). However it may also be used to describe the meditation of an arahant (SN 41.7:6.12). It is clear from MN 121:10.5 that the six senses are still functioning, unlike in deep serenity meditations. It seems that in such a state, the Buddha was able to function normally while seeing through the pain in his body. ↩

This central theme of the Buddha’s teaching—that each of us is responsible for our own salvation—becomes even more important as the Buddha’s days grow short. ↩

Read tama(t)agge with tama as superlative, literally “at the peak of the best”. ↩

This detail is often mentioned in texts of the Sarvāstivāda school, but rarely in Pali. ↩

Normally kappa as a period of time means “eon”, but the late canonical texts Kathāvatthu (Kv 11.5) and Milindapañha (Mil 5.1.10) argue that it means the “lifespan”, an interpretation followed by the commentaries. Support for this comes from DN 26:28.3, which says that “long life” for a mendicant is the four bases of psychic power which enable you to remain for the kappa. Here it is surely talking about a full lifespan. Underlying this is the idea that in different epochs the “proper lifespan” varies; in the Buddha’s day it was one hundred years (DN 14:1.7.7). We can resolve the problem if we read kappa here, not as a period of time, but as “proper, fitting”, i.e. the “proper” lifespan of a hundred years. ↩

Here Ānanda’s mind is “as if” possessed (yathā), but in the Vinaya yathā is missing: he is possessed (Kd 1:1.10.17). Remember, Ānanda is telling this story about himself. ↩

Māra (see SN 4.1:2.1) is the Buddhist deity of death, sex, and delusion; his aim is to trap beings in transmigration. He appears in many guises, both real and metaphorical, throughout the canon, but this sequence is his only direct appearance in the Dīghanikāya. Here he feigns compassion, urging the Buddha to find his final peace; but he has an ulterior motive, for with the Buddha’s passing Māra’s job will be much easier. ↩

Parinibbāna means “extinguishment”, as of a flame. Here it appears as both noun (“extinguishment”) and verb (“become extinguished”). It is not a particularly difficult term to translate. Linguistically it has nothing to do with “attachment”, so renderings such as “unbinding” are untenable. It should be translated rather than just keeping “Nibbāna”, not least because English resists verbifying adopted words, resulting in such constructions as “enter Nibbāna”, which reifies it in a way that the Pali does not. ↩

Māra is citing the Buddha’s words for his own purpose. ↩

This passage makes it clear that it was the Buddha’s intention from the beginning to establish an order of nuns (bhikkhunī). This passage lists the four assemblies that constitute a full dispensation; a similar pattern was recognized by the Jains. ↩

This passage is the narrative inverse of the occasion when Brahmā begged the Buddha to teach (SN 6.1:5.5, etc.). Throughout, the sutta artfully preserves a degree of narrative ambiguity. Here it almost appears as if the Buddha assents to passing away because of Māra’s request, although his intent was clear earlier. Māra’s reasoning, moreover, is based on the Buddha’s own words. ↩

It seems that at this point, the Buddha is still spending the rains in Beluva village, from where he would sometimes go to nearby Vesālī for alms, or to a local shrine for meditation. He left Vesālī only after holding a meeting for all the Saṅgha, which probably signified the completion of the rains (DN 16:4.1.2). If this reasoning is correct—and the text is not explicit—then he made this statement during the rains retreat. If, however, this reasoning is incorrect and we are already after the rains, it could not have been long after. Thus it is probably September/October, meaning that the final extinguishment was to take place in December/January. This conflicts with the tradition of ascribing his final extinguishment to the full moon of Vesak, in May. ↩

The Cāpāla shrine is unknown outside of this context. The Udāna commentary says that it was named after the yakkha who formerly lived there. Now, cāpalla means “fickleness, propensity to tremble” and is from the same root as earth-“quake” (bhumicāla; capala = pacala via metathesis). It is no great leap to cāpāla. If this is correct, it suggests that the shrine was dedicated to an earth spirit who commanded earthquakes; a fitting setting for the events to follow. ↩

Northern India lies in the shadow of the seismically active Alpide Belt, so the occurrence of earthquakes is realistic even if the causes are not scientific. ↩

For this difficult verse, I generally follow Bhikkhu Bodhi’s long discussion in Connected Discourses of the Buddha, note 255 on the Mahāvagga. | Sambhava means “production, creation”, and here I think it refers to the prolonging of life which the Buddha had just rejected. ↩

Bhavasaṅkhāra (“life force”) here is equivalent to āyusaṅkhāra and jīvitasaṅkhāra. ↩

Attasambhava (“self-creation”) harks back to sambhava in the first line. ↩

So far as it goes, this is a naturalistic explanation. The “water element” has the quality of softening, while the “air element” is traditionally understood as “movement”. Thus in modern terms this means, “When underground forces disturb a region of instability.” ↩

The might of ascetics was legendary in ancient India (eg. MN 56:14.2). The meditation described here might be compared with the “dimensions of mastery” below (DN 16:3.25.1). ↩

At DN 14:1.17.7 and MN 123:7.6 it is, rather, the entire galaxy that trembles, perhaps indicating that the enhanced miracle is a later development. ↩

There are many accounts of the Buddha’s awakening in the suttas, but none, so far as I know, that mention an earthquake. ↩

See SN 56.11:13.2. ↩

This refers to the Buddha’s death. The Pali here uses both nibbāna and parinibbāna. Sometimes it is said that nibbāna is the attainment of arahantship, while parinibbāna is the death of an arahant, but this distinction is not consistently applied in the suttas. | Regarding nibbānadhātuyā (“the element of extinguishment”), in Pali the case is ambiguous. It is sometimes translated “by means of” or “through”, which assumes the instrumental; but the Sanskrit is nirvāṇadhātau, which must be locative. ↩

As at AN 8.69. The following series of “eight things” seems arbitrarily inserted here and breaks the flow of the narrative. They are absent from the Sanskrit Sarvāstivāda text edited by Waldschmidt, which goes directly to the conversation where Ānanda realizes that the Buddha is going to die. ↩

These “assemblies” were formal deliberative meetings, not just gatherings. Thus “householders” here does not mean “lay folk” in apposition to “ascetics”; rather it means “home owners”. Some of these assemblies are depicted or alluded to in the Dīghanikāya. At DN 6:1.3, brahmins assemble in Vesālī; while at DN 3:1.13.3, Ambaṭṭha speaks of an assembly of Sakyans, who were aristocrats. At DN 18:12.1, we get a glimpse of the proceedings at a meeting of the gods of the thirty-three. ↩

There do not appear to be any records of this happening in the early texts, although that is perhaps to be expected. It does feel out of character for the Buddha, as normally he is very up front. The commentary says that this ruse was adopted so the Buddha could plant subtle seeds (vāsanā) for the future. At Kena Upaniṣad 3, Brahma appears to the gods and tests them, but they do not know him. ↩

These are another way of describing the different experiences of jhāna. Also at AN 8.65, AN 10.29:6.1, DN 33:3.1.142, DN 34:2.1.160, and MN 77:23.1. ↩

“Perceiving form (rūpa) internally” refers to someone developing meditation based on an aspect of their own body, such as the breath or the parts of the body. The “forms” (rūpā) seen externally are the lights or other meditation phenomena that today are usually called nimitta. An “ugly” form is the mental image that arises in such contemplations as the parts of the body. A “beautiful” image arises from practices such as mindfulness of breathing. ↩

“Not perceiving form internally” refers to meditations such as the external elements, or the decaying of another’s body. ↩

This is the meditation where one contemplates an external color, either a prepared disk or a natural phenomena such as the sky or a flower, which eventually gives rise to a “counterpart” image. Today such meditations are called kasiṇa following the Visuddhimagga, but in the early texts kasiṇa means “totality” and refers rather to the state of samādhi that results. ↩

Already encountered at DN 15:35.1. ↩

This period is depicted in the Pali text of the first Khandhaka of the Vinaya (Kd 1), but this event is not recorded there. However, the Sanskrit Sarvāstivāda Catuṣparisatsūtra, which depicts the same period as a Sutta, includes it immediately after the encounter with the merchants Tapussa and Bhallika. ↩

Note that this is the idiom that Ānanda uses when directly quoting the Buddha. ↩

“Misdeed” is dukkaṭaṁ. This term is familiar as the most minor class of offenses in the Vinaya. Here we see an informal use of the term as something that has been wrongly done, rather than a legal violation. It is used in a similar way by Mahākassapa at the First Council, who accuses Ānanda of several misdeeds. As a legal term, dukkaṭa is late; the category of offenses is not found in the Vinayas of the Mahāsaṅghika group of schools, which use vinayatikkrama for a similar idea. ↩

The Buddha goes on to list multiple places where he hinted to Ānanda, but the only record of such a conversation is at the Cāpāla shrine. ↩

The following group of places are all near Rājagaha, and collectively illustrate the variety of dwellings and environs enjoyed by the mendicants practicing there. | The Gotama banyan tree-shrine is mentioned only here. Gotama is a common name, and this shrine does not appear to have any connection with the Buddha. ↩

A cliff from which bandits were tossed as a means of execution. ↩

The Sanskrit form is Vaibhāra or Vaihāra. The Pali tradition says the First Council was held near the entrance to this cave (Dīpavaṁsa 4.19, Mahāvaṁsa 3.19, Samantapāsādikā Paṭhamamahāsaṅgītikathā). The Vinayas all agree that it was at Rājagaha, but traditions vary as to the exact location. ↩

A large open area where Jains did their penances (MN 14:15.2) and the Buddha taught occasionally (SN 8.10), but it is most famous as the place the monks Godhika (SN 4.23) and Vakkali took their lives (SN 22.87). ↩

Mentioned several times in the suttas as a pleasant place to meditate, it is notable as the site of the conversion of the Buddha’s chief layman disciple Anāthapiṇḍika (SN 10.8). But the most famous event there was when the Buddha moderated the monk Soṇa’s excessive striving (AN 6.55). ↩

The hot springs near Rājagaha were a popular place for monks to bathe, so much so that they prompted a rule ensuring that the monks did not monopolize the springs (Bu Pc 57). They are still in use and just as popular as ever. ↩

A personal gift of King Bimbisāra, this was the first permanent monastery offered to the Buddha and his Saṅgha (Kd 1:22.17.3). ↩

Mahākappina stayed here (Kd 1:5.3.1), and the Buddha rested there when his foot was first injured, apparently by Devadatta, before Jīvaka offered his mango grove (SN 1.38, SN 4.13). ↩

The following group of places are all in the Vajjian country near Vesālī. Whereas the varied sites around Rājagaha reflect the rugged terrain there, at Vesālī all the sites are tree-shrines, as the surrounding land is flat. DN 24:1.11.5 indicates where they lay relative to Vesālī; the Udena shrine was to the east, and the next three to the south, west, and north respectively. | Udena is an epithet of the “arising” sun (Rig Veda 1.48.7), although here it may have the sense “prosperity”. ↩

Named after the local yakkha, to whom offerings would have been made. It could get cold enough to snow, prompting the Buddha to lay down a rule permitting three robes (Kd 1:13.2.1). A short but galaxy-shaking discourse was once taught there (AN 3.125:0.3). ↩

The Pali has amba (“mango”) and ambaka (“maiden”) as variants. The commentary supports the latter, saying it was named for seven legendary princesses of Varanasi in the time of Buddha Kassapa, all of whom went on to become great disciples of our Buddha. I made this translation on the small island of Qimei off the south coast of Taiwan, where there is a shrine to the “seven maidens” who gave the island its name. Stories of “seven maidens” are widespread in myth and folklore all over the world, including Aboriginal Dreamtime stories. The archetype descends from the constellation known in English as Pleiades and in Sanskrit as Kṛttikā. Since there are six main visible stars in the cluster today, the stories often tell of how the youngest of the seven sisters was lost. In the Buddhist telling this is Visākhā, the only sister not to become an arahant in this life. ↩

This was, obviously, a fertility shrine. ↩

Previously mentioned as the place where the seven principles of non-decline were taught to the Licchavis. The meaning of Sārandada is obscure and variants profligate, but it might be derived from the Munda word sara, “funeral pyre”. The commentary says it was taken over from an old shrine to a yakkha of that name. ↩

“Take back” is paccāvamissati, which has several variants. It occurs in Ja 69 and Ja 509, where it is the opposite of vamati, to “expel, vomit”. ↩

This was the major Saṅgha residence near Vesālī. The Great Wood, according to the commentary, stretched as far as the Himalayas. Later tradition says that a town should have three woods: a “great wood” for wilderness (mahāvana); a “prosperity wood” for resources (sirivana); and an “ascetic wood” for spiritual practice (tapovana). ↩

Compare the earlier request to gather all the mendicants around Rājagaha (DN 16:1.6.2). ↩

Memorization was considered an essential basis for learning. In similar passages, we also find the injunction to “recite” the teachings, thus authorizing the recitation of the Buddha’s teachings after his death, which was later formalized in the Councils (saṅgīti). ↩

These are the sets of practices later called the 37 bodhiyapakkhiyā dhammā, the “wings to awakening”. Here they are presented as an essential summary of the Buddha’s teachings. They form the backbone of the final book of the Saṁyuttanikāya, the Maggavagga (or Mahāvagga). It is likely that the Buddha was referring to the earliest recension of this text. They are found as a summary of the Buddha’s teachings at DN 29:17.3, MN 103:3.2, MN 104:5.3, and AN 8.19:17.2 = Ud 5.5:25.2. ↩

This is perhaps the briefest summary possible of the Buddha’s teaching. The world as it is, and all the beings in it, are created and sustained through conditions. Since the conditions that sustain them are finite, the conditioned phenomena are also finite and must come to an end. Reflecting on this gives rise to gratitude for the life we have and the opportunities it grants us, and determination to live and practice dedicated to the realization of the unconditioned, Nibbāna. ↩

“Ripe old age” is paripakko vayo. ↩

“Well-settled thoughts” is susamāhitasaṅkappā. Compare asamāhitasaṅkappo at AN 4.22:5.3. ↩

Nāgāpalokitaṁ is the “elephant look”. There is a similar Sanskrit term siṁhāvalokana, the “lion look”, said to be the slow glance back that a lion makes as he leaves his kill. There is a nuance in meaning here, because while apalokana literally means to “look back”, it is used in the sense to “take leave” before setting out on a journey. ↩

Bhaṇḍagāma, where bhaṇḍa means “wares”; it must have been a trading post. It seems the villages in this passage were named after their chief economic activity, so I translate them to highlight this pragmatic system. ↩

These four also found at AN 4.1:2.3 and AN 7.66:14.4. ↩

Here the text refers to the Buddha in the third person; compare the previous set of verses in first person. Although the text states that these verses were spoken by the Buddha, it is possible that, as with many similar cases especially in the Aṅguttaranikāya, the verses were added by redactors. ↩

Note the use of “quenched” (parinibbuto) here while the Buddha is still alive. ↩

Hatthigāma, probably a village which specialized in training elephants. ↩

Ambagāma. ↩

Jambugāma. ↩

Departing from the economic naming scheme, here bhoga does not mean “wealth”. Rather, the Bhogas were one of the clans of the Vajji Federation. ↩

“Great references” is mahāpadesa; also at AN 4.180. A different set of four mahāpadesas are Kd 1:40.1.1, which provide criteria by which mendicants may judge what is and is not allowable. ↩

The phrase used in the suttas when reporting a teaching heard directly from the Buddha, eg. SN 55.52:5.1, SN 22.90:9.1, MN 47:10.7, etc. ↩

Dhamma, vinaya, and satthusāsana are used in the suttas in the general sense of the entirety of the Buddha’s teachings. In his advice to Mahāpajāpatī (AN 8.53) and Upāli (AN 7.83), they are said to be whatever conforms with letting go. A stream-enterer who is a lay person is grounded in them (AN 6.16:7.2). They are more frequent in the Vinaya, being used as a general qualifier of a legitimate legal procedure (Bu Pc 63:2.1.8). Due to this, the fact that there are three items, and the fact that dhamma and sutta are different words, we should not take dhamma and vinaya here as equivalent to sutta and vinaya below. Rather, they are a general claim to authenticity and do not specify particular texts. ↩

As at MN 112:3.1, DN 29:18.4, and AN 4.180:2.5. ↩

It is tempting to assume that sutta here means the Suttapiṭaka and vinaya means the Vinayapiṭaka, or at least an earlier version of these texts; but this is not supported by tradition. The late canonical Netti explains sutta as “the four noble truths” and vinaya as “the removal of greed, hate, and delusion” (Ne 6). The commentaries discuss many interpretations; ultimately they agree with the Netti for vinaya, but say sutta means the entire Tipiṭaka. I think the Netti is correct: teachings should “fit in” with the four noble truths (like other footprints fit in to an elephant’s footprint, MN 28), and they should “be exhibited” in that the results of practice should be apparent (sandiṭṭhika). | “Memorize” (uggahetvā), because in an oral tradition a text is not learned until it is known by heart; such claims must be taken seriously. | “Fit into” is osāreti or otāreti per AN 4.180; the two words have a similar meaning, “to flow down into”. ↩

The text has ca (“and”) rather than vā (“or”), which would be expected if they were to be found in one or other textual collection. This is urging that any teaching fits in with the fundamental principles of the four noble truths, and is effective in removing defilements. ↩

The Pali text appears to say that one should remember the mahāpadesa, whereas the Sanskrit clearly says one should remember the passage (ayaṁ dharmo’yaṁ vinaya idaṁ śāstuḥ śāsanam iti viditvā dhārayitavyāḥ). It seems as if this pattern should underlie the Pali too, for if the passage is false, one “should discard it” (chaḍḍeyyātha). In the case of a correct passage we should expect a parallel injunction that one “should remember it” (dhāreyyātha). But if this applies to the mahāpadesa there is no such injunction. Thus it seems as if the Sanskrit is correct here and the Pali corrupt. I restore it by reversing the order of the phrases. ↩

Each of the four references is a little less solid than the previous. Here one hasn’t heard from the Buddha, but from the Saṅgha. The fact that one hears it from the Saṅgha implies a kind of formal group recitation such as a saṅgīti or “council”. ↩

Now one learns not from a unified Saṅgha, but from several learned elders. This is a stock description of learned mendicants (eg. AN 3.20:6.2). | “Inheritors of the heritage” is āgatāgamā, where āgama means “what has come down”, namely the scriptural heritage. Āgama is a synonym for nikāya in the sense of “collection of scripture”. | The “outlines” (mātikā, literally “matrix”) are the summary outlines of topics that served as seeds for the development of Abhidhamma. DN 16:3.50.5 features one of the earliest of such lists, the 37 path factors that the Buddha “taught from his own direct knowledge”. These serve as outline for the section on the path in the Saṁyutta, from where they were adopted in various Abhidhamma texts such as the Vibhaṅga. ↩

Finally the testimony of a single mendicant, which is the weakest of all. Nonetheless, the procedure is the same. ↩

The parallel at AN 4.180:9.11 omits dhāreyyāthā, which I take to be the correct reading. See my note on dhāreyyāthā at DN 16:4.8.13. ↩

Pāvā, a town of the Mallas, has more significance for this narrative than appears at first sight. It was, according to Buddhist texts, the place where Mahāvīra had recently died, plunging the Jains into chaos. (The Jains, however, say this was another Pāvā, east of Nāḷandā.) Pāvā became associated with especially ascetic monks: thirty Pāvā monks became awakened on hearing a particularly strong discourse (SN 15.13); Mahākassapa heard the news of the Buddha’s passing at Pāvā; and monks from Pāvā allied with monks of “Avanti and the south” arguing for strict Vinaya in the Second Council (Kd 22:1.7.11.1). ↩

This passage also at Ud 8.5. ↩

Cunda was apparently a metal-worker, which was an advanced form of technological craftsmanship. ↩

This is, according to the commentary, preserved as the other discourse taught to Cunda, which deals with proper asceticism (Snp 1.5). ↩

The exact meaning of sūkaramaddava is unclear. Sūkara is “pig”, but some Chinese translations suggest the sense “mushroom”; and it is true that there are several names of plants or plant dishes that begin with sūkara or other animals. At Dhp 377, flowers are described as maddava, meaning “overripe, withering on the vine”. It is a common practice to allow meat to sit for a while to become tender and “high” for extra flavor when cooked. But this can lead to a proliferation of dangerous bacteria unless properly cooked, and such seems to have been the case here. In any case, this disputed term is marginal in a consideration of meat-eating in early Buddhism, which is discussed more fully elsewhere. ↩

If the Buddha knew the meal was dangerous, why ask to be served it? This is even more striking in light of the fact that it is a Vinaya offense to request fine food, including meat, and nowhere else is such a request recorded (Bu Pc 39:2.10.1). Such narrative ambiguities serve to escalate a sense of wonder. ↩

The Buddha’s illness is sometimes diagnosed as mesenteric infarction. The Buddha’s body rejects the world of conditioned existence entirely. ↩

The commentary says that these verses were added by the elders at the Council. ↩

The saṅghāṭi (“outer robe” or “cloak”) is double-layered, and served both for warmth and as bedding. The Buddha has not recovered fully from his illness. ↩

The Buddha was an exemplary patient. He did not complain, but made his needs known clearly to his carer. ↩

It would seem that, since the Buddha was enduring his illness without complaint and with dignity, Ānanda did not fully realize how weak he has become. ↩

The bowl (patta) was used both for eating and drinking. ↩

Pukkusa is not elsewhere mentioned. The reference to Āḷāra Kālāma recalls the narrative of the bodhisatta’s practices before awakening. There are several details that indicate the stories of the first part and the last part of the Buddha’s life were unified by such callbacks. We meet the Malla clan later on. ↩

Niśraya in the sense of “near” occurs at Śatapathabrāhmaṇa 3.1.2.17. ↩

In deep meditation the senses cease to function. ↩

As were Mahāpajāpatī’s limbs (AN 8.51). ↩

A nearby town where the Buddha had stayed previously (Kd 1:37.4.2). ↩

Siṅgīvaṇṇa, or else siṅgīsuvaṇṇa (AN 3.70:38.3), is gold from a mountain peak (siṅgī). Kauṭilya mentions a form of gold that is śṛṅgaśūktija, “occurring on mount Śūkti” (Arthaśāstra 2.13.3). The commentary to that passage says it had the color of red arsenic, so it would have been a rose gold color. ↩

Closing the narrative circle with the story of awakening. ↩

The commentary says this verse was added by the senior monks at the Council. ↩

The monk Cundaka makes an abrupt appearance here; this is the only mention of this name. The commentary to this passage calls him cunda, while the gloss to the parallel passage at Ud 8.5:14.3 has cundaka throughout. The diminutive ending -ka is perhaps meant to differentiate him from the smith Cunda. There are various Cundas whose connection is unclear. Mahācunda was one of the great disciples (MN 8, MN 118, AN 6.17), who later brought the Dhamma to the land of the Cetīs (AN 6.46, AN 10.24). He once stayed with Channa and Sāriputta (MN 144:4.1, SN 35.87:1.2); the commentaries say he was in fact Sāriputta’s younger brother. They also identify him with the “novice Cunda” who reported the deaths of Sāriputta (SN 47.13:1.3) and Mahāvīra (DN 29:2.1, MN 104:3.1), explaining that the title “novice” was a nickname that persisted from the time he ordained as a young novice. It is unclear whether the commentaries take the Cundaka of this passage to be the same person, but he is here performing a similar role as carer adjacent to the Buddha’s death. Later there appears a Cūḷacunda (Tha Ap 52:13.3). Thus there may have been one person known by different names, or several people whose stories have become conflated. ↩

These verses were also added at the Council according to the commentary. ↩

Adopt PTS and BJT reading satthā pavattā. ↩

The text addresses Cunda with the respectful āvuso. ↩

Again, the narrative circle. ↩

The text uses āyasmā here for Cunda, as does the Sanskrit, whereas it is normally reserved for mendicants (see below, DN 16:6.2.1). ↩

This became a point of discussion in later Buddhism: can it be that the merit of a gift grows after it is given? ↩

Known today as Kushinagar, it is a popular site for pilgrims, with many ancient stupas, Buddha images, and a peaceful park for meditation. ↩

Normally when the Buddha lies down, his mind is focused on getting up. But now he knows that he will not rise again. ↩

Sal trees blossom in April/May. This detail agrees with the Buddha’s final extinguishment in December/January, rather than in May (Vesak) as is currently celebrated (see note to DN 16:3.9.3). ↩

This calls back to the description of the fourfold assembly in the Māra section above (DN 16:3.7.4). ↩

This kind of narrative elevation is characteristic of the Buddha’s teaching. He did not try to deny or eliminate any belief in the miraculous, or in the power of devotion, but rather to show that such things were of limited worth compared with practice. ↩

Like Cundaka above, Upavāṇa shares the duties of an attendant with Ānanda; at DN 29:41.1 he is also fanning the Buddha. At AN 5.166, Ānanda goes to Upavāṇa for support when he feels he has disappointed the Buddha. ↩

In SN 7.13 Upavāna fetched hot water and molasses for the Buddha, an event he remembered in his own verses at Thag 2.33. ↩

For this usage of phuṭo, see AN 3.56:1.3. ↩

Elsewhere, pathavīsaññī refers to those who develop a form of meditation where they are “percipient of earth” (AN 10.6:1.2). Here, however, it simply means those deities who are aware of events on the ground. | Read chinnaṁpādaṁ viya papatanti. ↩

The Buddha as “eye” evokes the common (eg. Rig Veda 1.164.14, 5.40.8, 5.59.5, 10.10.9) Vedic image of the Sun as the “eye of all” (viśvacakṣāḥ, 7.63.1), the “eye” for “eyes to see” (10.158.4), moving as an unaging wheel through the sky (1.164.14). See Snp 3.9:11.1 = MN 98:7.23. | Pali has cakkhuṁ loke (“eye in the world”), Sanskrit has cakṣur lokasya (“eye of the world”). ↩

These two reactions—grief and equanimity—are depicted often in Buddhist art and narrative. They stimulated the two poles of development of the Buddhist community. The devotional tradition, feeling the need for an emotional connection with the Teacher, developed art, story, and doctrines to, as it were, keep him alive, resulting in the Jātakas and the Bodhisattva doctrine. A cooler, rational tradition developed a comprehensive system analyzing the impermanence of “conditions”, leading to the Abhidhamma. ↩

As for example at MN 24:2.1. ↩

Manobhāvanīya is explained in the commentaries as “those who, when seen, cause the mind to grow in what is skillful.” ↩

These four sites are the primary destinations of modern Buddhist pilgrims in India. | Saṁvejanīya is “stirring, provoking inspiration or urgency” such as when seeing an astonishing, disturbing, or amazing sight. ↩

Lumbinī in modern Nepal, which today is a well-maintained and quiet place for devotion and meditation. The site is marked with an Ashokan pillar dated perhaps 150 years after this time. On the pillar is inscribed in Brahmī characters hida bhagavaṁ jāte ti, which is a direct quote in Māgadhī of the Pali phrase here, idha tathāgato jāto ti. (Tathāgata “realized one” is how the Buddha referred to himself, while bhagavā “blessed one” is how his followers referred to him.) This is the oldest direct quote from the early canon preserved in the archaeological record. ↩

Bodhgaya in modern Bihar, which is called Uruvelā in the Pali texts. It is a bustling center for pilgrims from all over the Buddhist world, at the center of which is the great stupa next to the Bodhi tree. ↩

Isipatana is modern Sarnath, in the northern part of Varanasi on the Ganges. In the temple next to the park, the first sermon is recited every night. | Note the passive voice, whereas the parallel at AN 4.118 is active. ↩

The phrase nibbānadhātuyā parinibbuto, “fully quenched in the element of extinguishment” shows how the Pali uses two roots simultaneously for Nibbāna. The better-known term, nibbāna (Sanskrit nirvāṇa), is from the root vā (“to blow”), with the basic sense of going out through being deprived of air. The past participle form nibbuta (Sanskrit nirvṛta), from the root var (“to check or restrain”), has the basic sense of freedom from obstacles and constrictions. Generally, the Pali treats nibbuta as the past participle form of nibbāna, and for the most part the difference is purely verbal. Yet I believe the ambiguity is deliberate, as each captures a slightly different nuance of Nibbāna. “Quenched” means both to go out like a flame and to be satisfied like a thirst. This positive feel appears in Sanskrit passages using nirvṛta, such as Manusmṛti 1.54, where it describes the blissful absorption of all beings into the great divinity. By using “extinguishment” for nibbāna and “quenched” for nibbuta I hope to express this subtle distinction, or at least to alert the reader that it exists. ↩

This passage is absent from the Sanskrit parallel and it is probably a late interpolation. Ānanda was handsome, and many stories of his encounters with women are preserved, for example at Bu Pc 41:1.1.5. ↩

As it stands, this appears to contradict MN 152:2.10, where the Buddha ridicules the idea that sense restraint implies not seeing. The commentary, however, explains it as not looking at a woman who is standing in the doorway of a monk’s hut, so as not to give rise to lust. Thus it restricts this apparently general rule to an unusually intimate encounter. ↩

The verb changes from paṭipajjāma (first person plural) to paṭipajjitabbaṁ (future passive participle), a shift that mirrors the following passage regarding the funeral proceedings. There, the shift to future passive participle indicates that the subject is the lay folk who carry out the funeral, whereas here that does not apply. This suggests that this passage has been derived from that later passage. ↩

The commentary refers to AN 5.55:6.5, which speaks of chatting alone in private with a woman, a circumstance also dealt with in Bu Pc 45. ↩

Ānanda does not hesitate to let the Buddha know he has no intention of following his advice. ↩

The commentary says, quoting SN 35.127:1.6, that when a woman has sincere motivations, one should speak while thinking of them as a mother, a sister, or a daughter. ↩

“Corpse” is sarīra. ↩

For abyāvaṭā (“don’t get involved”), compare samaṇena bhavitabbaṁ abyāvaṭena (“a monastic shouldn’t get involved” (in domestic matters)) at Bu Ss 5:1.3.34. ↩

Read sadatthe (“own goal”) rather than sāratthe (“essential goal”). ↩

An iron case was also used for Queen Bhaddā’s body at AN 5.50:1.6. The second iron case does not “enclose” the first; rather it “crooks” (paṭikujjati) like a lid to “close it up”. ↩

This is a rare mention of the thūpa (“sepulchral momunent”) that became a major feature of the Buddhist landscape. Buddhist monuments were round in shape, which was apparently a characteristic of the lands around Magadha. Śatapathabrāhmaṇa 13.8.1.5 says that the correct form of such a monument was square, and that round monuments were built by godless “easterners”. ↩

Here the Buddha is said to be explicitly instructing his followers to adopt the building of monuments from the local customs. ↩

“Independent Buddhas” are sages who discover the Dhamma and are awakened independently, but who do not themselves go on to found a dispensation or establish a monastic order. Text has paccekasambuddho rather than the usual paccekabuddho. ↩

This refers to the “eight individuals” who make up the “Saṅgha of disciples”, namely those who have achieved the four stages of awakening and those on the path. ↩

In contrast with Ajātasattu. ↩

Like Queen Subhaddā, wife of Mahāsudassana, at DN 17:2.8.7 and DN 17:2.12.1. | Kapisīsa is door-jamb, not lintel. | For vihāra (“building”) the commentary has “pavilion” (maṇḍalamāla), which may have been a temporary construction for the occasion (compare MN 92:4.6). ↩

At this point Ānanda was a stream-enterer. ↩

When admonishing Ānanda, the Buddha first gently but firmly restrains him, then gives words of support and encouragement. ↩

The phrase “undivided and limitless” (advayena appamāṇena) normally describes kasiṇa meditation (AN 10.25:1.3); here it is also found in the Sanskrit: ānanda maitreṇa kāyakarmaṇā hitena sukhenādvayenāpramāṇena. ↩

On the eve of the First Council—in about six months time—Ānanda devoted himself to meditation and achieved arahantship. ↩

The same is said regarding the chief disciples Sāriputta and Moggallāna at SN 47.14:2.4 and regarding assemblies of deities at DN 20:4.3. ↩

Tittha, literally “ford”, is a path to salvation, used as a term for a non-Buddhist “religion”. Titthakara is a “religious founder” (literally “ford-maker”); titthiya is a “monastic of (another) religion” (for example at Bu NP 22:1.2.5); titthiyasāvaka is a “disciple of a monastic of (another) religion”. ↩

As at AN 4.130:6.4. Ānanda was in awe of the “incredible and amazing” qualities of the Buddha, and spoke of them often. Here, when Ānanda is at his most vulnerable, the Buddha turns the teaching around, pointing out that Ānanda is incredible and amazing too. ↩

This anticipates the story to follow. ↩

Campā, Rājagaha, Sāvatthī, and Kosambī were the capitals of Aṅga, Magadha, Kosala, and Vaccha respectively. Sāketa was the former capital of Kosala. Varanasi was formerly the capital of Kāsi, but at this time was contested by Kosala and Magadha, and had recently been won from Ajātasattu (SN 3.14, SN 3.15). ↩

This story is also found in DN 17. It seems that the Pali tradition extracted the story and greatly expanded it in an independent long discourse, whereas the Sanskrit tradition kept it at a more moderate length within the Mahāparinirvāṇasūtra itself. ↩

Kusāvatī features in the Kusajātaka (Ja 531), where the ugly but wise prince Kusa, son of the legendary Okkāka, wins the hand of the radiant Pabhāvatī. The Rāmāyaṇa also tells the story of a Kusa, son of Rāma, who ruled the city of Kusāvatī, although this city was located far to the south in the Vindhya ranges. Both stories are united by the detail that kusa grass, a prominent feature of Vedic ritual, ensured the kingly lineage. ↩

A “league” (yojana) is usually estimated at around fourteen kilometers (see MN 24:14.11). By way of comparison, even at its greatest extent under Ashoka, Pāṭaliputta was less than a league per side, so the dimensions of Kusāvatī here are strictly legendary. ↩

According to DN 32, Āḷakamandā was one of the many cities of Kuvera in Uttarakuru. ↩

Vāseṭṭha is a Vedic priestly clan. The Mallas adopted the name of their priest’s lineage, which was the normal custom for initiated khattiyas. Other examples in the Pali are Saccaka who is called Aggivessana (MN 35:4.2), and the Buddha and his family who are called Gotama. ↩

Attadutiyo “with self as second” is also at MN 146:4.6 where Nandaka visits the nuns. Sanskrit has bhikṣuṇā paścācchramaṇena (“with a mendicant as accompanying ascetic”). It was apparently evening (the “wrong time”, vikāla), when it is inappropriate for a monk to be wandering the town alone. ↩

Evidently the Mallas, like the Vajjis, met frequently. ↩

This is the second Subhadda we have met in this discourse, the first being a deceased devotee of Ñātika (DN 16:2.6.13). The corrupt monk who, after the Buddha’s death, urges the rejection of the Vinaya rules is another person of the same name (DN 16:6.20.1). The Mahāsudassanasutta also features a Queen Subhaddā (DN 17:2.5.9). ↩

While some such as Mahāvīra the Ñātika (MN 14:17.2) and Pūraṇa Kassapa (AN 9.38:2.1) claimed to have direct knowledge, others such as Ajita Kesakambala denied that such knowledge was possible (DN 2:23.2). ↩

The Buddha responded the same way when asked this question by the brahmin Piṅgalakoccha (MN 30:2.6), and to a similar question at AN 9.38:3.2. ↩

The four ascetics are defined at AN 4.241:1.1 as those on the four paths. ↩

While many aspects of the eightfold path are shared with others, some details may be missing (such as not-self or Nibbāna), while others are added (such as the belief in the efficacy of rituals, an eternal soul, or a creator god). ↩

The Buddha points to the mendicants who have gathered there. ↩

This is the only place in the early texts where the Buddha identifies his age when going forth. ↩

Detailed in such suttas as MN 36. ↩

This verse appears to be corrupt. The sense can be restored through two extra lines in the Sanskrit: “Ethics, immersion, conduct, and knowledge, and unification of mind have been developed by me, teacher of the references for the noble teaching.” | For padesavattī, the Sanskrit has pradeśavaktā, where vaktā means “speaker” and pradeśa has the sense “pointing out”. I think it means, “I am the one who taught the four great references (mahāpadesa)”. ↩

The commentary says this line was added at the Council. ↩

This is similar to the idea of the Four Great references, and sets the scene for the First Council at which the teachings were recited. | Paññatto here means “pointed out” rather than “laid down”, as can be seen from DN 9:33.21, where the same phrase refers to the four noble truths. ↩

Āvuso is from the root āyu (“age”) and thus has a respectful sense and does not mean “friend” as it is often translated. Like bhante, it is an indeclinable vocative of address that may be used with or without the name (see eg. MN 5:31.2). ↩

I render bhante as “sir” when it stands alone and “honorable” when it prefixes a name. | Unlike bhante, āyasmā (“venerable”) is declinable, so it is used in parts of speech other than direct address. It is from the same root as āvuso but more Sanskritic and hence elevated in tone. The difference between āyasmā and āvuso is like that between the English “governor” and “guv’nor” or “my lord” and “m’lud”. ↩

These are not defined here, and the senior monks at the First Council were unable to agree on them (Kd 21:1.9.3). Nonetheless, the Pali Vinaya consistently labels the Pācittiya rules as “lesser” (khuddaka; Bu Pc 92:2.2.22, Bi Pc 96:2.2.22, Pvr 1.1:219.3), which would make the Pātidesanīyas “minor” (anukhuddaka). The Sekhiya rules are also “minor”, but they were not at this point reckoned among the training rules for recitation. ↩

“Divine punishment” is brahmadaṇḍa. Channa features often in the Vinaya as a monk who refuses correction and acts disrespectfully. The Saṅgha had already imposed an act of “ejection” (ukkhepanīyakamma) on him due to his persistent bad behavior, but that was still not enough (Kd 1:25.1.1). The brahmadaṇḍa was imposed at the First Council (Kd 1:1.12.1), upon which Channa finally saw the error of his ways. Brahmadaṇḍa is encountered in a different sense at DN 3:1.23.21. ↩

Vattabba in such contexts means “advise, correct” rather than more generally “speak to”. Thus the brahmadaṇḍa is not the “silent treatment”. ↩

The commentary says this line was added at the Council. ↩

Even on his deathbed, the Buddha retains mastery over his mind. ↩

Ānanda’s question is prompted by the fact that it is very difficult to tell the difference between one who is dead and who has attained cessation (MN 43:25.1). Anuruddha can answer due to his mastery of psychic powers. | Note that Ānanda and Anuruddha have immediately adopted the forms of address recommended by the Buddha above. ↩

Each of these characters reveal something of themselves in their verses. Sahampati, as a royal deity, emphasizes the universal nature of the teaching and the grandeur of the Buddha. ↩

“Bag of bones” is a loose rendering of samussaya. ↩

The ten powers of a Realized One are detailed at AN 10.21 and MN 12:9.1. ↩

Less creative than Brahmā, Sakka repeats a famous verse spoken by the Buddha at SN 15.20:8.1 and DN 17:2.17.5. ↩

Anuruddha was a reclusive meditator who specialized in mindfulness of breathing. Here he remarks on the fact that, since breathing ceases in the fourth absorption (SN 36.11:2.19), the Buddha’s breathing had already stopped before he died. ↩

Ānanda has the most emotional reaction. While Anuruddha speaks only of peace, Ānanda empathizes with those who were distraught. ↩

Text omits “with hair disheveled” (kese pakiriya) when describing the shaven-headed monks. ↩

“Still on the same business” (teneva karaṇīyena) calls back to DN 16:5.20.1, where they were said to be “on some business” (kenacideva karaṇīyena). They had been discussing all night. ↩

An uplifting response to tragedy, full of beauty and celebration. ↩

It seem unlikely that everyone simply forgot. It was probably the custom to wait seven days before the cremation. ↩

“Unworn” is ahata, as at DN 14:1.33.9 and Kd 1:1.6.2. ↩

“Coronation” is makuṭabandhana, “the binding of the crown”. The commentary says there was, fittingly, an auspicious decorative royal hall there; perhaps too the name was felt to pun with muktabandhana, “freedom from ties”. ↩

I think sandhi here means “covered without gaps”. ↩

With the passing of Sāriputta and Moggallāna, Mahākassapa was the most senior of the remaining leading mendicants. As a solitary recluse, it was unusual for him to be travelling with such a large group, or with anyone at all really. He was to cite the events depicted here at the start of the First Council (Kd 1:1.1.1). ↩

A follower of the Bamboo-staffed Ascetic Gosāla (DN 2:19.1). | This may be an inspiration for the so-called “Flower Sermon”, a medieval Zen story that depicts the Buddha holding up a flower and Mahakassapa smiling. ↩

Compare Bu Pc 72. The syntax is clumsy here, perhaps deliberately so. ↩

Here sarīrāneva is plural and so must mean “relics”, whereas previously it was singular, “corpse”. ↩

As when he was born (DN 14:1.28.1). ↩

Ajātasattu would have learned of the news from spies. It is a 600 km round trip to Rājagaha and back, which a mounted messenger could make in fourteen days. ↩

A bold move, considering that his designs on the Vajjis were no secret. Perhaps he was seeking a pretext for war. The justification for taking a share of relics is caste, rather than practice of the Dhamma. ↩

Both the tribe and the town are exceedingly obscure, mentioned nowhere else in early texts. They must have been a small clan nearby. ↩

The Koliyans were south-eastern neighbors of the Sakyans, and several of their towns and people feature in the early texts. ↩

This brahmin is mentioned nowhere else. ↩

Dassāma (“we shall give”) is the future second plural of dadati. ↩

The brahmin Doṇa appears suddenly in the narrative, a reminder that there were many more people than the ones who are mentioned. The suttas record two encounters with a brahmin of this name: one is the wondrous story of seeing the Buddhas footprints (AN 4.36), while the other discusses the five kinds of brahmin (AN 5.192). ↩

The fear of war was justified and the resolution achieved by Doṇa probably marks the last time these parties achieved a diplomatic outcome. The relative peace that had lasted most of the Buddha’s life was crumbling. We hear of war or threats of war between the Kosalans and the Magadhans, the Magadhans and the Vajjis, the Sakyans and the Koliyans, the Kosalans and the Mallas, and the Kosalans and the Sakyans. It is probably because of the latter two conflicts that Viḍūḍabha—Pasenadi’s son and the newly crowned king of Kosala—did not send an emissary to the funeral. By sparking conflicts with former allies the Sakyans and Mallas, Viḍūḍabha undid the successes of his father and fatally weakened the Kosalan Empire. When the dust cleared a few decades later, all these lands had been consumed by Magadha. ↩

Thus begins the practice of establishing Buddhism by interring relics in a stupa. ↩

The Moriyas were a minor clan of the region, unmentioned outside of this passage, but their obscurity was not to last long. About a century after these events, Chandragupta the Moriyan, having won the Magadhan crown from the Nandas, proceeded to rout the Greeks in the west. His empire, which covered most of northern India, was further expanded to the south by his son Bindusara and grandson Ashoka, under whom the Mauryan Empire became the greatest of all Indian empires. Thus Ajātasattu’s expansionist dreams were ultimately fulfilled beyond his imagining. ↩

The commentary says this summary was added at the Council. ↩

The commentary says this line was added at the Third Council, which was held about 150 years after the Buddha under Ashoka. The Buddha’s life was already fading into legend. ↩

According to the commentary, the remainder of the text was added by the monks of Sri Lanka. Note, however, that this verse and the next are fairly similar to those in the Sanskrit text. Since that is a northern text, it seems unlikely these verses were composed in Sri Lanka. ↩

The tidiva was the realm of Indra/Sakka (DN 21:1.12.22, DN 30:2.27.12, Thag 10.1:8.4), as it was from the time of the Vedas (Rig Veda 9.113.9, Atharva Veda 10.9.5, 17.1.10). In Buddhist cosmology, this agrees with the fact that Sakka’s realm is the third of the heavens (after the earth gods and the four great kings). Thus the Third Heaven is the heaven of the Thirty-Three. Both ideas spring from an old association of Indra, or divinity generally, with the number three. Agni Purāṇa lists tridiva as a synonym for “heaven”, as does Amarakośa 1.1.11. Kṣīrasvāmin clarifies that three here means “third”, while also adding that some connect it with the Brahmā realm (Amarakośodghāṭana 1.1.6; see SN 7.18:4.2). ↩

“Offering” is āyāga. ↩

The context requires that this line lists three kinds of celestial beings, in contrast with humans in the next line, yet nara in Pali normally refers to a human. Monier-Williams, however, acknowledges that Sanskrit nara may refer to a class of beings allied to the gandharva and kinnara. ↩

Picking up the story of the Buddha’s past life as King Mahāsudassana from DN 16:5.17.1. ↩

From here we leave DN 16 behind and with it any semblance of realism. Some of these details are shared with SN 22.96, which however does not mention the name Mahāsudassana. ↩

Readings vary. The Sanskrit text has saptapauruṣā ardhacaturthapauruṣāś ca nikhātā. ↩

I think the point is that they listened to the music rather than doing bad things. ↩

This is specific instance, so I use past tense. Where it is an abstract description of a legendary past, I use the present tense to denote an eternal or mythic present. ↩

The wheel is firstly the sun and secondly the wheel of the chariots that drove the Indo-Europeans in their conquests. It is the manifestation of unstoppable power. The solar imagery is reflected in the name Mahāsudassana (“Great Splendor”). The whole story reflects the Indo-European dream of universal domination. ↩

Many of the details in this myth echo the Brahmanical horse sacrifice. Since the horse was the primary source of Indo-European dominion, its sacrifice served to authorize the power of a king. It was a costly and dangerous rite that was attempted only by the greatest of sovereigns. | Bhiṅkāra (“ceremonial vase”) and abbhukkirati (“besprinkled”) are elevated terms. ↩

In the horse sacrifice, the horse is released for a year, while the king follows it with his army, claiming any land that it wanders on as his. ↩

Read bhuñjati at MN 98:10.30 with yathābhuttañca bhuñjatha at DN 17:1.9.4, DN 26:6.7, and MN 129:35.7. These have sometimes been rendered “eat”, “enjoy”, or “govern”. But compare the archaic English “use” meaning “the benefit or profit of lands”. Thus yathābhuttañca bhuñjatha means “use as has been used”, i.e. “maintain the current level of taxation”. ↩

The Wheel plunges into the seas, while the sacrificial horse is born in the western and eastern seas (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 10.6.4.1). ↩

Historically, India has usually been divided into squabbling realms, but from an early age there was a dream of a unified and peaceful continent. ↩

“At the High Court” is uncertain. Read aḍḍa (variants attha, aṭṭa) which in Sanskrit has the senses “solve, infer, argue, discern”. The commentary interprets aḍḍakaraṇa as the “place of judgment” i.e. the court, which is clearly the case here (see also SN 3.7:1.5, MN 89:13.3). The affix -pamukha here does not mean “entrance”. Rather, it describes the attributes of a wheel-turning monarch in the sense of “finest” (eg. DN 17:2.5.1). ↩

The white elephant is a symbol of royalty to this day. The description anticipates the elephant Indra acquired in later legends, Airāvata the “cloudy”, white and huge and moving through the sky. | For sattappatiṭṭho, the commentary has susaṇṭhitaaṅgapaccaṅga (“well-grounded on each and every limb”), a sense confirmed by the Mūlasarvāstivāda Bhaiṣajyavastu which has saptāṅgaḥ supratiṣṭhito (“well-established on seven limbs”). The subcommentary lists the four feet, trunk, tail, and penis (varaṅga). ↩

The sacrificial horse is likewise white with black head or forequarters. It is identified with the sun, thus being a “sky-walker”. “Thundercloud” (valāhaka; Sanskrit balāhaka) is the name of one of the four horses of Kṛṣṇa’s chariot in the Mahābharata. The description here also recalls the Vedic sacred horse Uccaiḥśravas. ↩

The “commander” (pariṇāyaka) is mostly found in Buddhist texts of this context, and is not a regular term of governance. This passage shows that he was responsible for management of the realm, while below he appears as commander of the army (DN 17:2.8.2). Elsewhere he is said to excel in strategy (AN 5.134:2.5). ↩

The jarring inclusion of “women” (itthī) in this list probably refers to state-sponsored prostitution. ↩

As at DN 5:19.1. ↩

The palace is named “Principle” (dhamma) in recognition of the king being subject to a higher law. Normally I translate pāsāda as “stilt longhouse” but here something grander is meant. ↩

For kūṭāgāra as “chamber” see MN 37:8.10. ↩

Thus denying the doctrine of Pūraṇa Kassapa at DN 2:17.5. This is the recognition, at least partially, of right view. ↩

These are the three factors of right thought. The king skillfully uses a transition in physical space to set up his intention to meditate. ↩

Here as in DN 1, jhāna is not a uniquely Buddhist practice. ↩

“Palace” is pāsāda, literally “stilt longhouse”. ↩

“Chamber” is kūṭāgāra, literally “building with peaked roof”. Normally this means “bungalow”, but in a similar description at MN 37:8.9 we hear of a “palace” with a hundred “towers” (niyyūha), each of which has seven hundred “chambers”. Thus the kūṭāgāra must be a structure many of which can belong to a palace, namely “chamber”, while viyūha (spelled byūha at SN 22.96:3.4) must have the same meaning as niyyūha, i.e. “tower”. ↩

This segment breaks the expected pattern of “foremost” things. ↩

Not the British car of the same name. The chariot is the source of victory in battle. ↩

Read dukūlasandanāni, where dukūla is “fine cloth, silk” and sandana is “cord, tether”. ↩

An odd detail. Maybe the sound of the elephants disturbed his meditation? ↩

Like Ānanda at DN 16:5.13.1. ↩

He makes it clear that this will not be an intimate visit. ↩

The aorist is not past tense, as it is governed by mā. ↩

“Desire” is chanda, the first of the four bases of psychic power, which in DN 16:3.3.1 are said to lead to long life. By urging him to live long, she inverts the Mahāparinibbānasutta where Ānanda fails to do the same. ↩

Implying that Ānanda was right to not beg the Buddha to live long. ↩

At AN 6.16:2.2 this advice is given by Nakula’s mother. ↩

Like Ānanda at DN 16:5.13.1. ↩

This contrasts with the Buddha’s last meal at DN 16:4.20.1, which caused sickness and distress. The Buddha was rejecting existence entirely, whereas Mahāsudassana was continuing in a pleasant form of conditioned existence. ↩

After DN 5:21.16, this is the second Jātaka in the Dīghanikāya. ↩

Readings here and at SN 22.96:4.8 are confused, and further complicated at Tha Ap 411:4.1. I read velāsikā due to the passage’s similarity DN 23:15.4, where a “coquette” is also serving a royal. I believe the variant velāmikā is a ghost word contaminated from AN 9.20:4.1. ↩

This picks up from the events of DN 16:2.5.1, which however discusses only the Ñātikans (who are reckoned among the Vajjis). Like DN 17, it bears many signs of a late sutta. The overall theme is the presence of a cosmic order where the liberating teaching of the Buddha is reconciled with the requirements of worldly power. ↩

This list of ten nations is unique. The omission of the Aṅgas and Magadhans is noted below. The more famous list of “sixteen nations” adds Avanti and Assaka in the south, and Gandhāra and Kamboja in the north-west (eg. AN 3.70:28.3). The Buddha did not visit these lands, which explains why they are omitted. ↩

“Devotees” is paricāraka, which normally means “servant”. It is not in the relevant passages of DN 16. This sense is found in only a couple of other places, both late (Snp 5.18:1.2, Kd 1:22.14.8). ↩

Bearing in mind that none of the nations were actually mentioned in the relevant Mahāparinibbānasutta passage, this whole introduction is framed to emphasize the importance of Magadha to Buddhism, especially given the problematic character of Ajātasattu. In the decades following the Buddha’s death, the Buddhist community adapted to a new political landscape which for a time saw the entirety of Buddhism contained within the sprawling Magadhan empire. ↩

As we known from DN 2, Bimbisāra had recently been murdered by Ajātasattu. ↩

A not-so-subtle hint of the changes under Ajātasattu. The passing of Bimbisāra signifies the crumbling of the social order that prevailed in the Buddha’s lifetime, bringing with it the immediate threat of war and chaos. This sutta establishes a timeless order that persists while worldly conditions fluctuate. ↩

Elsewhere the suttas say that Bimbisāra went for refuge (DN 4:6.33), while the Vinaya says he was in fact a stream-enterer (Kd 1:22.9.1), which is confirmed below. The Jains, however, claim him as one of their own but say he went to hell for committing suicide. Like his son Ajātasattu, it is likely that he frequented several teachers in his realm. ↩

Near the town of Uruvelā on the bank of the Nerañjarā River at the place known today as Bodhgaya. ↩

“Suggestion” is parikathaṁ, which elsewhere occurs in the Vinaya (Kd 7:1.5.16) and the Abhidhamma Vibhaṅga (Vb 17:43.2) in the sense of “hint”. ↩

Normally aṭṭhiṁ katvā manasikatvā sabbaṁ cetasā samannāharitvā describes listening to Dhamma. This whole process seems unusually laborious. ↩

Nāmadheyyaṁ means “name (borne by someone or something)”, not “one who bears the name” (MN 50:22.1). ↩

Janavasabha is “chief of men”, spelled janesabha at DN 20:10.10 and DN 32:10.9. The synonym narāsabha is an occasional poetic epithet of the Buddha (Snp 3.11:6.2, Snp 5.1:21.3, SN 11.3:14.2). In Sanskrit we find puruṣaṛṣabha in the same sense. ↩

Uḷāravaṇṇa describes beautiful people at MN 96:7.8. ↩

Read ito. I think this implies what is stated more explicitly in Anuruddha’s partly parallel verses at Thag 16.9:23.1: after each of seven rebirths under Vessavaṇa he can become a king of men. This explains the name Janavasabha. ↩

It is rare to see saṁsāra used as a countable noun, but see Thag 2.48:2.2. ↩

As a stream-enterer he is freed from any lower rebirths, yet he still aspires to a higher realization. ↩

In this idiom, the verb for “aware” varies between sañjānāti, jānāti, pajānāti, and sampajānāti. ↩

Compare SN 1.50:5.1 and SN 2.24:6.1. ↩

It is not just the Vajjis and the Buddhist Saṅgha who meet frequently in a hall to discuss business, but the gods as well. Here we get a rare glimpse into how the heavens work, or more to the point, how depictions of heavenly proceedings act as a template for how things should be on earth. ↩

The thirty-three and the Four Great Kings are both present; the heavenly realms are not shut off from one another. ↩

In the Suttas, sudhamma (“clear right”) is used in two main contexts: as the name of the hall of the gods, and in this expression (it is also a personal name). Both are found in this Sutta, suggesting they have the same meaning. Dhammassa ca sudhammataṁ echoes Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 14.2.2.29, dharmāsi sudharmeti (“You are a well-supporting support”). This is a ritual invocation of the Sun as that which supports everything here in this world. In Pali, it is something we are frequently urged to “behold” (eg. Thag 4.2:4.2), suggesting the metaphorical link with the Sun’s brilliance is not entirely lost. And as the hall of the gods, the sense of the “Sun” is also fitting. The idea is that the Sun is regular and lawful, and by shedding its light on all of us, it is a clear visible manifestation of what is right and just. ↩

For vipakkamati compare MN 127:11.1. ↩

Compare DN 11:80.12. ↩

For vipāko bhavissati in discerning the results of signs, compare DN 1:1.24.2. ↩

See AN 3.127:2.3. ↩

This phrase is also at DN 19:16.8, but apart from that the words pakativaṇṇa (“normal appearance”), anabhisambhavanīya (“imperceptible”), and cakkhupatha (“visual range”) are all unique in the early texts. ↩

For the unique term “human form” (mānusaṁ viggahaṁ) compare the Vinaya phrase manussaviggahaṁ (Bu Pj 3:2.49.1). ↩

Also appearing in DN 21:1.8.3, DN 20:10.11, and SN 35.119, Pañcasikha (“Five-Crest”) was a handsome and virile deity of the gandhabbas. ↩

Bhāsittha is 3rd singular aorist middle voice. ↩

Compare MN 91:21.4. ↩

Everything Sanaṅkumāra says is just a bit off. Here he adopts an idiom commonly used by the Buddha, but in third person rather than the Buddha’s second person; and he asks only rhetorically, where the Buddha engages with his audience. If it were only this one example it would mean nothing, but similar changes happen throughout. I believe this is a subtle literary device that tells two narratives to two audiences. To potential converts it sounds like Sanaṅkumāra is giving a ringing and learned endorsement of Buddhism, while to knowledgeable Buddhists he appears as less than well versed in the teachings. I note these eccentric wordings as we proceed. ↩

The sutta began by recounting those who have achieved various stages of awakening. But escape from rebirth threatens the gods; this potentially fraught relationship is played out in MN 49. Sanaṅkumāra is preempting such arguments by pointing out that many of the Buddha’s followers are reborn among the gods and do not escape transmigration, at least not for now. This is no trivial metaphysical argument. In order for Buddhism to prevail, it must show that its radical soteriology is compatible with worldly prosperity, lest it face opposition from kings and other temporal powers. The gods act as proxies to demonstrate the appropriate behavior for terrestrial kings. This is why the leading character is Bimbisāra/Janavasabha, who straddles the two realms. ↩

Sanaṅkumāra begins sharing the Buddha’s teaching with the gods, starting with the bases of psychic power that featured prominently in DN 16. Here, however, he focuses on the worldly dimensions of psychic powers, ignoring the liberating dimension that was central to the Buddha. This sets the pattern for the teachings to follow, except for the very last. | “Corporeal form” is attā in its old sense of “body”. Compare Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.2.3, “He divided this corporeal form (ātman) into three …”. ↩

Yāva supaññattā, which is also at MN 51:4.3, is a variation of the common exclamation yāva subhāsita. The phrase iddhipahutāya iddhivisavitāya iddhivikubbanatāya is unique. The Paṭisambhidāmagga draws on this passage to explain vikubbana both as a general term for development of psychic powers (Ps 3.2:4.3) and as specific kind of psychic power, namely the transformation of one’s apparent form as demonstrated by Sanaṅkumāra (Ps 3.2:15.1). ↩

These “three opportunities” are not found elsewhere. ↩

This unique term is the reverse of the phrase that begins the first jhāna. The passage, however, speaks only of lifestyle rather than deep meditation. ↩

“Aloof” (asaṁsaṭṭha) is a synonym of “secluded” (vivicca). The jhāna formulas are extremely stable and it is rare to find them played with like this. ↩

Since jhāna arises from pleasure, it cannot be meant here. ↩

“Coarse physical, verbal, and mental processes” (oḷārikā kāyasaṅkhārā …vacīsaṅkhārā … cittasaṅkhārā) is another unique term. They are probably to be identified with the three “processes” of MN 44:14.2. ↩

This builds off DN 1:2.24.1, but the full phrase is only here and DN 19:7.2. ↩

Normally satipaṭṭhāna is taught “in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to end the cycle of suffering, and to realize extinguishment” (eg. DN 22:1.7). Here, in yet another unique phrasing, a more humble goal is sought. ↩

Again the liberating dimension is ignored in favor of worldly psychic abilities. This is another unique formulation. ↩

Also found at AN 7.45:1.1. At MN 44:12.4 the four right efforts are said to be the “prerequisites of immersion”. Here at last Sanaṅkumāra introduces the liberating dimension of the path as a whole. ↩

Also at SN 45.1, etc. ↩

To the standard passage on the qualities of the Dhamma, Sanaṅkumāra clumsily tacks on the line spoken by the Buddha when he was persuaded by Brahmā to teach (SN 6.1:10.1, DN 14:3.7.13, MN 26:21.6, MN 85:45.6). ↩

Finally the question is answered, although the number of deaths is obviously exaggerated. We cannot estimate the population size at the time with any confidence. But we know that Pāṭaliputta under Ashoka covered about 25 km², which suggests a population somewhere around 250,000. Probably there were a few million people in the whole of Magadha. ↩

The commentary identifies these as non-returners, but this is unlikely as puññābhāga (“share of merit”) indicates those who do good for the sake of a good rebirth rather than liberation (AN 6.63:30.2). There would have been countless more of such good folk than stream-enterers, whereas the number of non-returners, as indicated by the count of the Ñātikans, would have been small, not “countless”. This verse is also at SN 6.13:7.1, where the commentary says nothing of non-returners. ↩

Sanaṅkumāra lives longer than the lesser gods so he has a broader perspective. He emphasizes the long-term stability of cosmic order, which prevails through the crises that afflict the short-lived kingdoms of men. ↩

Astonishingly, this sutta traces its textual lineage directly to Brahmā, exactly like the Brahmanical texts (eg. Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 6.5.4). Of course, Brahmā gets his teaching from the Buddha, but this is clearly copying the Brahmanical model. ↩

Here Ānanda plays a key role as the linchpin of the oral tradition. It is likely that not just the Mahāparinibbānasutta itself, but all these suttas of this cycle were composed by Ānanda or his students. ↩

With this unique ending, there is no claim that this sutta was heard by the mendicants in the usual way. Rather it makes its purpose explicit, to act as a means to widely propagate the Dhamma. The Mahāparinibbānasutta also speaks of the spread of the Dhamma, and the Janavasabhasutta indicates some of the means by which that was achieved in the decades following the Buddha’s death; in particular, by allying itself with the ascendant power of Magadha. ↩

We were introduced to Pañcasikha in DN 18, which is similar to the current sutta in many other details as well. Thus this sutta can be considered as a distant cousin to the Mahāparinibbāna cycle. ↩

The council of gods described by Janavasabha at DN 18:12.1, while otherwise similar, took place at the entry to a rainy season, whereas this one is at the end of a rainy season. This cannot have been the Buddha’s last rains, for he was already in Vajji by then. ↩

For “genuine praise” (yathābhucce vaṇṇe), see DN 1:1.28.1. ↩

This set of eight is not found elsewhere. | “Proffered” is payirudāhāsi, a unique term in early texts. ↩

Sakka adopts the same rhetorical style as Sanaṅkumāra (DN 18:20.2). ↩

Compare DN 18:25.1. ↩

Paṭipadā is instrumental. ↩

I don’t think this idea is found elsewhere in quite this way. Normally it is said that the path leads to Nibbāna like the rivers lead to the ocean (eg. SN 45.114:1.1). ↩

This item is unique. ↩

Another unique item. ↩

This is normally true, but in some cases the Buddha left a badly-behaved community (MN 48), dismissed misbehaving monks (eg. AN 8.10:2.2), or even dismissed a large community (MN 67). | The “joy of solitude” is ekārāmataṁ . ↩

Also at DN 29:29.5, AN 4.23:4.1, and Iti 112:5.1. ↩

Pariyositasaṅkappo (“achieved all he wished for”) is a synonym of the more common paripuṇṇasaṅkappo (eg. MN 29:2.5). ↩

This impossibility is also at AN 1.277:1.1 and MN 115:14.1. | “In one solar system” (ekissā lokadhātuyā): a single lokadhātu encompasses a single terrestrial world with a single moon and sun. ↩

It is not common to wish for the Buddha’s long life, but we do find this sentiment expressed in a conversation between Sāriputta and Ānanda (SN 21.2:3.5). ↩

“Having appraised” (saṅkhāya) is glossed by the commentary with “having known” (jānitvā). Compare the discussion on “judgmentalism” at DN 1:1.3.1. ↩

Disampati means “head of the directions”, i.e. king of all the land. He and his story are found nowhere else in the early texts. ↩

“Steward” is Govinda, literally “lord of cows”. The “high priest” (purohita) was a hereditary office, a learned ritualist and adviser attached to a specific family. For royal families the post could be highly contested. The closeness of the role is shown in that aristocratic families could be referred to by the lineage of the high priest. ↩

While the current sutta does not explicitly identify their realm, Dīpavaṁsa iii 40 records Disampati and Reṇu as kings of Kāsi. This fits with the geographical layout depicted in this sutta, with Kāsi at the center. The story, then, depicts the establishment of Brahmanical kings across India from Kāsi. ↩

Jotipāla means “guardian of the sacred flame”, i.e. someone who maintains the Vedic fire ritual (see below at DN 19:47.26). There was another Jotipāla in the time of Buddha Kassapa at MN 81:6.2, and another who was a religious founder of the past (AN 6.54:18.1, AN 7.73:2.5). Despite the popularity of the name in Pali, it does not seem to appear in Sanskrit sources. Given that it appears in Pali only in legendary contexts, it is probably a vocational epithet. ↩

The king’s only care, it seems, is not for the passing of his friend, but that he no longer gets to indulge in whatever he wants. ↩

This shows that Govinda is an office rather than a personal name. ↩

Following the Mahāsaṅgīti reading rather than the PTS (nānusāsi … nānusāsati). It seems required by the context that he does more than his father. ↩

Following PTS reading sukhaṁ edheyyātha. ↩

Sakaṭamukhaṁ (“front of a cart”) is clarified by comparison with the parallels. T 8 is identical (其界廣闊。正南南隅，其界狹略，猶如車形), while DA 3 expresses a similar idea more briefly (此閻浮提地， 內廣外狹). The Mahāvastu (Mvu 85.17) confirms this sense with dakṣiṇena saṁkṣiptā śakaṭamukhasaṁsthitaṁ. These appear to demonstrate a knowledge of the shape of the Indian subcontinent. Below it says that each of the kingdoms is shaped like the front of a cart, just as India is as a whole. ↩

Neither Rhys Davids nor Walshe translate this line, but it receives an extensive discussion in the commentary. It says that six kingdoms were arranged around Reṇu’s kingdom in the middle, like an umbrella (vitānasadisaṁ). ↩

The verses tell the realms starting with the rising sun at Kaliṅga in the east and proceeding clockwise (padakkhiṇā) until the circle is complete with Aṅga on the Kaliṅga border. Thus the original center was probably the last place on the list, Kāsi, which is indeed geographically central. ↩

Kaliṅga was a coastal realm in modern Odisha and Andhra Pradesh. There is no consensus on the exact location of Dantapura. ↩

Assaka stretched from Kaliṅga’s western border across the interior. Potana is modern Bodhan in Telangana state. ↩

Mahesaya of the Pali editions is a variant spelling for māhissatī; Mahāvastu has māhiṣmatī. It is in present-day Madhya Pradesh, on the banks of Narmada River, and is perhaps to be identified with modern Maheshwar. ↩

Sovīra was on the lower Indus, and Roruka is identified with modern Rohri in Sindh province, Pakistan. It is implausible that they received Aryan culture from Kāsi. ↩

Mithilā was the capital of Videha, to the north east of the Vajjian federation, nestled against the Himalayas. Mithilā was a dominant kingdom before the Buddha, its king Janaka featuring prominently in early Upaniṣads. It features rarely in the suttas (MN 91, Thig 6.2, Thig 13.4) and had apparently declined in importance. Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 1.4.1.10–19 depicts its origins in terms of the spread of fire-worship from the west by its founding king Māthava Videgha with his priest Gotama Rāhūgaṇa. ↩

Campā is modern Champapuri near Bhagalpur in Bihar state, not far from West Bengal. Aṅga lay between the Chandan river to the west and the Rajmahal hills to the east. In the centuries before the Buddha it expanded its dominion to the sea on the south-east and Magadha in the west. But with the Kaliṅgas pushing back from the coast and the rise of Bimbisāra in Magadha, they were pushed back to their ancestral lands and fell under Magadhan dominion. ↩

Varanasi, one of the oldest cities in the world, was the capital of the Kāsī kingdom. It lost its status as an independent kingdom shortly before the Buddha, when it was taken over by Kosala. It appears in countless Buddhist stories of the past as the dominant city of the region in what appears to be a timeless and ageless past. However, despite its great antiquity, it is a historical settlement, of which the discovered remains date back to perhaps 1200 BCE; it was a capital city from perhaps 800 BCE. ↩

The names of the aristocrat kings—most of which are difficult to identify from other sources—are listed in an abruptly-inserted verse. The names are missing from the parallels in Mahāvastu and DA 3, but T 8 appears to have the same list of names in the same order, except with Reṇu at the start. Rhys Davids proposes to assign each one to a kingdom as listed in the same order. This seems to work for the first four names, as Ja 424, invoking this sutta, identifies Bharata as king of Sovīra. But it falls apart with Reṇu, who as we have seen, belongs in Kāsi rather than Videha. ↩

“Bharata” is the name of an individual king, while they are collectively known as “Bhāratas” (with a long initial ā due to secondary derivation). Ja 424, invoking this sutta, identifies Bharata as king of Sovīra. ↩

Here bhāratā means “kings of India” or perhaps, if read together with the preceding verses, “kingdoms of India”. India was called Bhārata after the legendary King Bharata of Hastināpura (Delhi), founder of the Lunar dynasty, conqueror of India, and sire of the warring tribes of the Mahābharata. His story is told in the Saṁbhavapara of the Mahābhārata. The name represents the success of Vedic culture across the subcontinent. ↩

In spiritual circles, such rumors spread like wildfire in an Australian summer. ↩

The ancient Brahmanical teachers are invoked to justify the Buddhist rains retreat. | Compassion is one of the “meditations of Brahmā” (brahmavihāra). Normally the suttas speak of the absorptions (jhāna) and of the meditation on compassion (karuṇā), but the idea of an “absorption on compassion” is unique to this sutta. ↩

Compare MN 51:10.3, where the same construction is a site for the sacrifice. ↩

“Deathless” from a Brahmanical perspective, but very much within the realm of saṁsāra from a Buddhist perspective. ↩

Brahme is the normal vocative for brahmā. However in verse it is sometimes used as vocative for brāhmaṇa (eg. Snp 5.1:7.3, Snp 5.19:3.4). ↩

These factors are explained as a summary of the Gradual Training. ↩

“At one” (ekodibhūta or more commonly ekodibhāva) normally describes deep meditation, and is part of the formula for the second jhāna. Here it is explained as equivalent to “seclusion” (viveka). ↩

“Putrefaction” (āmagandha) is the smell of (moral) decay or corruption (AN 3.128, Snp 2.2). ↩

“Desire” is icchā. PTS reads vicikicchā (“doubt”), but this must be incorrect as the commentary explains it as “craving” (taṇhā). ↩

“Easy to quell” (sunimmadaya) is unique to this passage. ↩

As noted in the comment to DN 16:5.19.2, kingly clans adopted the lineage name of the high priest (purohita) during initiation. ↩

This is a rare use of the verb sikkhati in the sense “bestow, present”. ↩

“True teaching” (saddhamma) normally describes the Buddha’s teaching. ↩

“Leads to rebirth in the Brahmā realm” (brahmalokūpapattiyā), just as the teaching of Āḷāra Kālāma, based on the even more refined formless meditations, leads to rebirth in the dimension of nothingness (MN 36:14.14). ↩

Echoing the ancient hermit Araka at AN 7.74:2.2, who said life is evanescent like a dewdrop. ↩

It is regarded as normal that women should renounce. ↩

Compare with the mass renunciation under Vipassī (DN 14:2.16.6). ↩

His meditation expands from compassion to include all four of the brahmavihāras. ↩

The Aṅguttara (eg. AN 6.54:13.9) uses “path” (magga) instead of “Dhamma” here. Compare the Bodhisatta’s rejection of his former teachers, whose dhamma only led to rebirth is a high realm, not to escape from rebirth (MN 26:15.35). ↩

This is the third and final Jātaka in the Dīghanikāya, after DN 5 and DN 17. ↩

According to the doctrine of the “perfections” (pāramī), which emerged around two to four centuries after the Buddha’s passing, the practices he undertook in past lives laid the foundation for awakening in this life. Here, however, the Buddha states that his former practices did not lead to awakening. Rather, since they were based on the wrong view of eternal bliss in the Brahmā realm, they only led to a good rebirth so long as that kamma lasted. It is the eightfold path, which the Buddha discovered in his final life, which leads to awakening. The same saying in a similar context is found at MN 83:21.7. ↩

This discourse gives an extensive account of divine beings. Some are familiar from elsewhere in the Pali texts, others found in various Brahmanical sources, while still others occur only here. For the names we can compare the edition of the Sanskrit text by Waldschmidt and Sander and available on SuttaCentral as SF 140. ↩

The Pure Abodes are inhabited entirely by non-returners. ↩

“Great congregation” is mahāsamaya. ↩

A village (Bu Pj 2:3.8) or royal compound (Bu Pc 83:1.3.56.1) was marked with a “boundary-post” (indakhīla). It symbolized a fixed and immovable point, either in a good sense (SN 56.39:4.1) or, as here, an obstacle. The Sanskrit indrakīla is a two-foot long iron bolt securing a fort, presumably fixed in the ground (Arthaśāstra 2.3.26), or else a mountain in the Himalayas. The warrior Arjuna, journeying beyond the Gandhamādana, is stopped at the Indrakīla mountain by Sakra/Indra disguised as a brahmin ascetic, at whose urging Arjuna undertakes asceticism in order to gain the power he would need (Mahābhārata 3.3.37). The symbolic sense of “stopping” relates to the Pali sense of immovability, and suggests that the underlying metaphor is the irresistible power represented by Indra. | For Mahāsaṅgīti’s ūhacca manejā read ūhacca-m-anejā. ↩

Nāga can refer to a class of semi-divine beings in a powerful serpentine form (“dragon”); a large and powerful snake, especially a king cobra; a bull elephant; or any powerful and mighty being (“giant”). ↩

The discourse up to here is also found at SN 1.37. ↩

This recalls DN 14:1.10.1, where the relative sizes of the mendicant congregations of different Buddhas are tallied. That sutta, in another point of similarity, also featured a conversation with deities of the Pure Abodes. ↩

“Paean of praise” is siloka, a rare case where this means “verse (of praise)” rather than “fame, renown”. Siloka is also a poetic metre, the most common form in Pali. | Anukassāmi is present tense from the root kass, “to draw (up), to drag”. Compare Sanskrit anukarṣa in the sense “invoking, summoning by incantation”. ↩

This gives a hint as to one of the purposes of this sutta. Living alone in remote forests can be terrifying. Such places were widely believed to be haunted by all manner of supernatural creatures, not all of them friendly. While for an arahant this posed no threat, there would have been then, as there are today, many young or aspiring meditators who faced such challenges with trepidation. These verses offer succor, surrounding them with powerful, albeit invisible, allies. ↩

“Spirit” is yakkha. In later legend they appear as monstrous figures, but in the suttas they are ambiguous and may often be friendly to the Dhamma. Early statues of yakkhas at Madhurā (circa 100 BCE) depict noble and powerful kings, not ogres. Yakkha is also sometimes used more generally in the sense of an individual or deity. ↩

Colorful like the nymphs of MN 50:25.6 or Susīma’s gods at SN 2.29:7.1. ↩

Mount Sātā is unidentified, but according to the commentary it was in the middle region. ↩

Vessāmitta (“friend of all”) is the name of a Vedic hermit. Legend has it that he was a khattiya who earned brahminhood due to his intense austerities in the remote Himalayas. Perhaps this is a mountain named for him, although I can find no trace of it in Sanskrit. ↩

Kumbhīra means “crocodile”. ↩

For this mountain, see SN 15.10:2.2, SN 15.20:2.3, and notes. ↩

We met two human King Dhataraṭṭhas (“Strongrealm”) in the Mahāgovindasutta. ↩

“Centaur” is gandhabba. Gandhabbas are wild, sexual beings who, being first to yoke the horse (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 5.1.4.8) and riding the steed called “Racer” (vājin, 10.6.4.1), “take the reins” from Indra (Rig Veda 1.163.2) as his charioteer Mātali. It is likely the Sanskrit gandharva stems from the same root as the Greek kentauro, and the ultimate origin of the idea comes from the proto-Indo-Europeans, who rode the horse, creating a potent entity that was invincible in battle. At Sanchi Stupa No. 2 there are images of men and women riding centaurs, although this may be a later Greek borrowing. ↩

By implication, they are renowned as being powerful as Indra, the king of gods who in Pali is more commonly called Sakka. It is also a nod to the multiplicity of divinities in the Vedic system, where one becomes many and many become one. ↩

Virūḷhaka is “growth”; he was probably a god of the fertile crops. In the Pali it is spelled Virūḷha here due to the meter. ↩

“Gnomes” is kumbhaṇḍa (Sanskrit kuṣmāṇḍa), “pumpkin-belly”, a race of lesser deities often depicted as pot-bellied, ugly and misshapen. But see SN 19.10 for another interpretation. ↩

One of the “royal snake families” at AN 4.67:3.2. His name means “multiple eyes” (virūpa-akkha) for the false eyes on a cobra’s hood. ↩

Also known as Vessavaṇa (DN 32:7.43, Snp 2.14:6.1), which means “Son of the Renowned” from his father Viśrava. These two names appear together elsewhere in contemporary literature (Atharvaveda 8,10.28c, Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 13.4.3.10), where, although the passages are obscure, he appears to be associated with wickedness, concealment, and theft. Although a god of wealth (dhanada), the name Kuvera is explained by lexicographers as “deformed”. Probably he was originally a god of the underground, blessed with the earth’s riches, yet deformed by its great pressure. ↩

The following verses are a treasure-trove of ancient Indian mythology, recording the names of deities otherwise lost to history. Many of the names are obscure and variant readings are recorded in manuscripts and noted in the commentary. My spellings follow Ānandajoti’s translation, The Discourse on the Great Convention, unless there is a reason to change. I try to identify the deities as best as I can, but many of them remain speculative. ↩

These deities are called dāsa, which normally means “slave” in Pali. But here, it seems, we have a singular instance of the old Vedic meaning, an uncivilized foe. The dāsas Vṛtra, Namuci, and Vṛṣaśipra are described as “deceivers” (māyin, Rig Veda 1.53.7; 2.11.10; 7.99.4; 10.73.7). This epithet is also used of the closely related dasyu (Rig Veda 1.33.10; 4.16.9; 8.14.14; 10.73.5; see note on DN 5:11.5). Such beings are said to be “godless” since they oppose the Vedic deities (Rig Veda 2.19.7; 3.31.19; 7.1.10; 10.11.6; 10.138.4, etc.), so we can translate as “heathen”. ↩

I am not able to identify any of these names with confidence, but perhaps kuṭeṇḍu and viṭeṇḍu could be traced to indu (“moon”), thus “crooked moon” and “defective moon”. Compare khaṇḍendu, a later term for Śiva as the crescent moon. ↩

The Sanskrit names are kiṭi, vikiṭi, bhṛgu, and bhṛkuṭi. Only bhṛgu is attested in the Vedas, but he was a sage, not a “crafty heathen”. ↩

Candana appears in MN 134:6.4, SN 2.15, and SN 40.11:1.1, and together with Kāmaseṭṭha in DN 32:10.4. Candana means “sandalwood”, although the name of the god might also relate to its root “shining”. | Kāmaseṭṭha means “Chief of Sex”, i.e. “Eros”; he does not seem to appear in a Brahmanical context. ↩

Panāda (“roarer”) was the name of an ancient king who performed the horse sacrifice (Thag 2.22:1.1, DN 26:26.1). In Ja 265 he is said to have been the son of Vessavaṇa (Kuvera). | Opamañña is a descendant of the ascended sage Upamanyu (“zealous one”; see note on MN 99:10.3). ↩

Mātali is the charioteer of Sakka (i.e. Indra; SN 11.6:1.5, MN 83:14.1, etc.), a role he plays throughout Brahmanical literature as well. He appears here as one of the centaur lords, and is father to the centaur Sikhaṇḍī, Pañcasikha’s rival in love DN 21:1.6.8. | A sūta was a high-ranking officer attending the king, close in meaning to the (admittedly obscure) military term “equerry”, in contrast with the regular charioteer, sārathi. ↩

The gandharva Citrasena (“Brightspear”) appears in the Sanskrit Purāṇas as a friend of Arjuna in various adventures. ↩

Nala means “reed”. There was a King Nala of Vidarbha whose love for his Queen Damayantī is celebrated in the Mahābharata. | Janesabha is an alternate spelling of Janavasabha (DN 18). ↩

In DN 21 we shall learn of how the centaur Pañcasikha (“Fivecrest”) wooed Timbaru’s daughter Suriyavaccasā (“Sunshine”). ↩

Read nābhasa, which means “celestial, heavenly”. The commentary says this was the name of a lake, which agrees with the legend that a Nābhasa was a son of Nala (“reed”) and father of Puṇḍarīka (“lotus”). The Sanskrit here, however, has sahabhuṁ nāgo. ↩

Vesālā is from the adjectival form vesāla (“of Vesālī”). | Pali taccha can represent Sanskrit takṣa, and the Sanskrit does indeed have takṣakaḥ here, so Tacchaka is probably “of Takṣasilā”. This famous city, normally spelled Takkasilā in Pali, is Taxila in West Pakistan, an ancient center of learning. ↩

These nāgas are frequently mentioned together in Sanskrit literature such as the Mahābhārata (1.31.1a, 2.9.9a, 5.101.9c), where they are also said to come from Pāyāga (3.83.72a: prayāgaṁ sapratiṣṭhānaṁ kambalāśvatarau). ↩

Payāga (modern Prayagraj, formerly Allahabad) is the sacred ford at the confluence of the Ganges and the Yamunā beside Kosambī (see Bu Pj 1:4.18). ↩

The Dhataraṭṭha and Erāvaṇa nāgas also appear frequently in Sanskrit literature, and often in association with other deities in our text as part of a loose cluster of divinities (eg. Harivamśa 3.112–117). Erāvaṇa also appears at Snp 2.14:5.1. Here he is a nāga as in “dragon”, but later tradition saw him as a nāga as in “elephant”, in which role he became the mighty mount of Indra/Sakka. ↩

The enmity between snakes and birds is legendary (Ja 518), its origins related in the story of Suparṇa and Kadrū, mother of dragons (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 3.6.2). It is rooted as much in the common sight of birds attacking snakes as it is in the cosmic opposition between the solar and the chthonic, the forces of light in the sky and darkness beneath the earth. ↩

Birds are called “twice-born”, once from the mother, once from the egg. “Twice-born” is also an epithet of brahmins (Thig 15.1:31.3). ↩

The supaṇṇa (Sanskrit suparṇa, “bright-feathered”), later garuḷa (Sanskrit garuḍa, “devourer”), is to the eagle as the nāga is to the cobra. He has been falsely compared with the loathsome harpy; but his golden wings, closeness to the sun (eg. Rig Veda 5.47.3), and role as bearer of the nectar of immortality (RV 4.26.4, 8.100.8) show that he is the Indian phoenix, the golden eagle of the sun. As the brother of the Dawn (Aruṇa, Matsya Purāṇa 174.47), his golden wings at sunset “devour” the sun. He disappears in darkness only to be born again the next day, just as the European phoenix combusts itself and is born anew. Thus he is both the older and the younger brother of Aruṇa, for which came first, sunrise or sunset? ↩

Upavhayati occurs only here and SN 7.9:4.3 in Pali. It is a Vedic term for invoking or calling up blessings in a whisper. ↩

The Buddha reconciles even such inveterate enemies. In the Buddhist view, all of these beings have their place in the great pattern of nature. ↩

Vajirahattha (“thunderbolt-in-hand”) is a synonym of vajirapāṇi (DN 3:1.21.3, MN 35:14.1). It is a frequent epithet of Sakka in the Vedas (eg. Rig Veda 1.173.10a indro vajrahastaḥ), an identification confirmed by the commentary here. ↩

Vāsava is another epithet of Sakka (see below, DN 20:14.9), meaning “endowed with wealth” (vasu; see for example Rig Veda 1.9.9a indraṁ vasupatiṁ “Indra, lord of wealth”). The Buddhist explanation of his name SN 11.13:9.1, rather, plays on the word āvasatha and calls him the “giver of a guesthouse”. Later Brahmanical texts enumerated eight Vasus, with Indra as their lord, who are reckoned among the thirty-three. | Sakka’s wife is the demon (asura) princess Sujā, daughter of Vepacitti, hence they are his “brothers”, technically in-laws (SN 11.12:6.1). ↩

The Kālakañja is the lowest class of titans (DN 24:1.7.19). Legend has it that they tried to build a fire altar of bricks (i.e. a mountain) to ascend to the heavens and contest with the gods (Taittirīya Brāhmaṇa 1.1.2.4–6, alluded to at Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 2.1.2.13). Three are mentioned as being godlike at Atharvaveda 6.80.2. The Mahābhārata (eg. 4.44.9) says they are Dānavas, an association supported in the next line. They seem to be associated with the ferocious Kālakeyas, children of Kālā. But a common Sanskrit spelling is kālakhañja, where khañja means “lame”. This calls to mind the lame smith-god Hephaestus, who also ascended to heaven. Kāla (“black”) then would be the black metal iron (cf. English “blacksmith”), yielding the sense “iron-lamed”. ↩

The Dānavas are a prominent group of asuras otherwise unattested in early Pali. The name stems from “rivers, waters” after their mother Danū. | Ghasa (“devourer”) is occasionally mentioned as the name of a rakṣasa (Rāmāyaṇa 5.22.36a praghasā nāma rākṣasī). The commentary treats them as a single class of arrow-wielding asuras. ↩

Vepacitti means “wise thinker”, Sucitti means “good thinker”. Vepacitti was the lord of the asuras and Sakka’s counterpart. Their relationship was complicated (SN 11.23). Brahmanical literature regards him as the eldest son of Danū and hence chief of the Dānavas. The Sanskrit form is vipracitti, but in Buddhist texts it is incorrectly Sanskritized to vemacitra. Vepacitti’s fame matches Sucitti’s obscurity, for he does not seem to appear elsewhere. ↩

Pahārāda the ocean-loving asura lord appears in AN 8.19. His name (Sanskrit prahlāda) means “mirth”. Later Brahmanical legends say he was a righteous son of the wicked Hiraṇyakaśipu, who hated him for his devotion to Viṣṇu. | The story goes that when Namuci stole the soma from Indra, Indra’s vengeance was frustrated by his vow not to harm him with anything wet or dry, in the dark or the light (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 12.7.3.1). Indra’s ingenious solution was to dismember him with foam (Rig Veda 8.14.13) at dawn. Namuci’s name is explained as na-muci, “not letting go” (the waters). In Buddhism, Namuci is a name of Māra, although here Māra appears separately below. ↩

According to legend, Bali was the grandson of Pahārāda and son of Virocana. His hundred sons were dread warriors (Bhāgavata Purāṇa 8.10.30). The word bali also refers to a kind of sacrificial offering, but the roots of the term are obscure. ↩

Virocana was their grandfather. He was another adversary of Indra, despite which they were both said to have sought knowledge from Prajāpatī, but Virocana misunderstood since he saw only the surface meaning (Chāndogya Upaniṣad 8.7.2–8.5). Here he is associated with Rāhu, while Gaṇeśa Purāṇa 2.29 says he was granted a crown by the sun which he then lost. These details hint at a connection with the eclipse, in which case virocana would be the rays that emanate during a solar eclipse. ↩

Rāhu is the mighty asura who “seizes” the moon (SN 2.9) or the sun (SN 2.10) to create an eclipse. He is the son of Vepacitti. It is strange to see him described as “auspicious” (bhadda), as he is a black planet and a force of darkness. ↩

These four are normally treated in the suttas as physical properties. Each of them is worshiped in the Rig Veda as a deity, and the Upaniṣads list them together along with other elements (eg. Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.4.5). I am not aware of any earlier contexts that group the four together systematically as deities in this way. ↩

Varuṇa is invoked frequently in the Vedas, and in the suttas he is associated with other leading deities such as Indra and Soma (DN 13:25.2, DN 32:10.2, SN 11.3:5.1). As one of the twelve children of Aditi he stood for a calendar month, and grew a wide and sometimes baffling array of associations—the oceans, water, the sky (at night), and justice. Vedic Varuṇa was the god of command, the king of tough rule. He was identified with the aristocrats, while his partner Mitra was the brahmins (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 4.1.4). ↩

Soma is the divine nectar that filled the ancient proto-Indo-Europeans with vitality. Its biological identity is disputed, but may have been ephedra. It is associated with the moon, hence the connection with Varuṇa as the night sky. | Yasa means “fame, glory”; so far as I know it is not personified in early Brahmanical texts, and rarely later. The connection between these two is illuminated by such passages as Rig Veda 7.85.3. To uphold Indra and Varuṇa in battle, there is an offering of Soma, which is described as svayaśasaḥ, “Self-Glorious”, i.e. the state of being high on speed, if speed were a god. ↩

In the Vedas, Mitra (“friend”) is almost always paired with Varuṇa, and the appearance of Mettā (“friendliness”) here echoes that closeness. He was the god of alliances. | Karuṇā in the sense of “compassion” does not occur at all in pre-Buddhist Sanskrit. It is probably introduced here as companion to Mettā by association with Mitra. The Sanskrit here, however, is maitrī varuṇikā. From a Buddhist point of view, these are deities reborn due to the development of jhāna based on love and compassion. ↩

Veṇhu (variant veṇḍu) is the Pali spelling of Sanskrit viṣṇu, who appears only here and at SN 2.12. In the Rig Veda he was a solar god who made three great strides (said to encompass the earth, the sky, and the heavens). | A deity named Sahalī (“with plow”) appears at SN 2.30:3.1 where he praises Makkhali Gosāla, but I cannot trace him anywhere else. ↩

Yama often refers to a god who guards the paths to the land of the dead (SN 1.33:10.3, MN 130:5.1), lord of the Yāma gods. Here, however, it refers to “twins” who in the Vedas are often identified with the Aśvins (the twin horses yoked to the chariot). In the Vedas, it seems asama (“unequalled”) is used as an epithet only, although the commentary says it is a name. | In Pali these lines lack a verb, while the Sanskrit supplies āgataś (“come”) instead of asamā, so perhaps we should read “the pair of Twins came”. ↩

Vāsava is above at DN 20:12.3. ↩

Purandara (“Fortbreaker”) is another epithet of Sakka or Indra (eg. Rig Veda 1.102.7). The Buddha reforms it to Purindada (“Firstgiver”) at SN 11.12:2.1. But Indra’s generosity is long renowned, eg. Rig Veda 1.10.6c: “He is the able one, and he will be able for us—Indra who distributes the goods” (sa śakra uta naḥ śakad indro vasu dayamānaḥ). ↩

Sanskrit has sabhikā. Most of the deities in the following verses do not seem to be met with elsewhere. The Sanskrit forms are often quite different but equally untraceable. ↩

Their names might mean “Unhurt” and “Hurter”. The Sanskrit implausibly has romā (“Romans”). ↩

For Varuṇa see above (DN 20:13.3). | Sahadhamma means “who share the same duty”. ↩

The “Unfallen” and the “Unshakeable”. ↩

The Sūleyyas might be “spear (or trident) bearers”; śūli is a name of Shiva. | Rucira means “brilliant, beautiful”. ↩

Vāsavanesi means “seekers of Vāsava”. ↩

“Equals” and “Great Equals”. ↩

“Humans” and “Superhumans”, but here perhaps “Descendants of Manu”. ↩

As per DN 1:2.7.2. ↩

DN 12.10.2. ↩

Hari means “yellow, green” and is the astrological color of the planet budha (“Mercury”). It came to have the general meaning of “sacred, holy” and was an epithet for various deities, which in the Rig Veda included Indra and Vishnu. However the astrological connection is suggested by the references to Mars and Venus below. ↩

“Dwellers in the Red Place (= planet)”, i.e. “Martians”. ↩

Pāraga means “one who has crossed over”. ↩

These deities represent the three lights that announce a new day: the morning star, the newborn sun, and the aura of the dawn. | Sukka (“Bright”) is the name of the planet Venus, the morning star. | Aruṇa is the dawn, a major Vedic deity signifying the arising of consciousness and order. | Karambha means “porridge”, which was offered to the sun under the name Pūṣan (Rig Veda 3.52.7, 6.56.1; Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 4.2.5.22; Kauṣītaki Brāhmaṇa 6.8.18; Maitrāyaṇī Saṁhitā 3.10.6; Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 5.15.1). Hence he became known as karambhād, “porridge-eater”. Apparently the sun lost its teeth and could only eat porridge (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 1.7.4.8). Being toothless like a baby, and lacking the risen sun’s “teeth” (i.e. “rays”), he probably represents the “newborn sun”. Compare for example Rig Veda 10.35, where Pūṣan is invoked, along with many other deities, in a hymn to the dawn. ↩

Mahāsaṅgīti has veghanasā, for which the Buddha Jayanthi variant vekhanasa is preferable. We meet a wanderer of that name in MN 80, and in Sanskrit vaikhānasa is a general term for ascetics; but this meaning seems unlikely in context. The astrologer Varāhamitra names it a constellation (Bṛhat-saṁhitā 47.62), but that is much later. The Sanskrit here is nīlakavāsinī (“Dwellers in the Blue”), which pairs well with lohitavāsino above. Nīlavāsa is a name for Saturn, whose color is blue. ↩

Odātagayha is probably “white planet”, i.e. the sun. Sanskrit has avadātakeśā (“white-haired”). Compare the description of solar gods Sūrya at Rig Veda 1.50.8 as śociṣkeśaṁ vicakṣaṇa (“flame-haired, brilliant”) and Varuṇa at Rig Veda 8.41.9 as śvetā vicakṣaṇā (“white, brilliant”). ↩

Sanskrit has pītakavāsinī, “dwellers in the yellow”, either Mercury or Jupiter. ↩

The sadāmatta (“everdrunk”) gods appear in some later Buddhist texts, alongside the māyādharas (or mālādharas), but they don’t seem to appear in a Vedic context. | I cannot find any reference to the hāragaja gods. Sanskrit has hāritakā, perhaps “sons of Harītī” (the yakkhinī; but see below, DN 20:20.12). ↩

“Assorted” is missaka, not elsewhere attested as a name of gods. ↩

Pajjuna (Sanskrit parjanya) is a Vedic god of thunderstorms closely associated with Indra/Sakka. His daughters appear in SN 1.39 and SN 1.40. Sanskrit has instead śuddhakā rucikā (“pure, bright”). ↩

The gods of Tusita and Yama are normal parts of the Buddhist cosmology. Neither khemiya nor the Sanskrit kṣemaka appear to be the names of gods elsewhere, and the commentary explains that they dwell in both the Tusita and Yama realms. ↩

The commentary acknowledges the variant readings kaṭṭhakā (from “stick” or “plowed”) and kathakā (“reciters”), while Sanskrit has kṛṣṇuktāś (“reciters of the black”). Perhaps related to Sanskrit kāṭhaka, a recension of the Black Yajur Veda taught by the sage Kaṭha. ↩

Perhaps from lamba (“hang, droop”) in reference to deities of the sunset (cp. Mahābhārata 4.31.4c sūrye vilambati). Sanskrit has lumbinī lumbinīśreṣṭhā, which is perhaps normalized to mean “of Lumbinī”. ↩

“Shining” (joti) is used widely of many gods, including the Sun and Indra. | The commentary derives āsavā from āsa (“wish”) not āsava (“defilement”), explaining that they achieved their status due to desire (chandavasena). This agrees with the Sanskrit svāśiṣā (“well-wish, prayer”), i.e. words of wishing or blessing uttered over the sacrifice (see Rig Veda 10.44.5; cp. 8.44.23). However, I think it’s more likely this stems from the common Vedic idiom of describing heavenly bodies as “yonder”, an idiom closely connected to the shining sun. The masculine nominative singular form is asau, and the Pali taddhita construction āsavā would mean “those who are yonder”. ↩

Pavuṭṭha (“shed”), from pavasati (“stay away”), seems to be unique in the Pali in this sense. Commentary glosses vigata, “disappeared”. | The first part of this verse, according to the commentary, addresses the Saṅgha as a group in the singular, but I translate in plural for clarity. ↩

Subrahmā appears as a godling at SN 2.17, but given his company this is likely the “independent divinity” of SN 6.6–8. | Paramatta appears only here in Pali. In Brahmanical texts it is a common term for the highest conception of Brahmā as the “supreme soul” (paramātman) of the cosmos. This term came into common usage later, but is found occasionally in earlier texts such as Maitrāyaṇī Saṁhitā 2.9.1. ↩

Sanaṅkumāra makes regular guest appearances in the suttas (DN 3, DN 18, DN 19, DN 27, SN 6.11, AN 11.10). | Tissa is a common name, meaning “born under the star Sirius”. Perhaps this is the former monk of that name who was reborn in the Brahmā realm (AN 6.34). ↩

The moniker “Great Brahmā” (mahābrahmā) is here used of an individual, but sometimes it is a class of leading Brahmās. ↩

“God Almighty” (issara) is a Brahmā god to whom the creation of the world is falsely attributed (DN 24:2.14.3, MN 101:22.5, AN 3.61:1.6). ↩

Sanskrit has hāritī, the name of the fabled yakkhiṇī of Madhurā converted by the Buddha. ↩

This late sutta exhibits considerable literary sophistication. The A-plot concerns Sakka’s rejection of his violent past and embrace of the Dhamma, while the B-plot concerns Pañcasikkha’s more modest growth from a libertine to a married man. This draws on such precedents as Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 3.2.4.4, where the centaur is urged to win his woman by seduction rather than force. | This discourse is quoted by name and a passage discussed at SN 22.4. In addition, the dialogue at MN 37 picks up directly where this leaves off and may be considered a sequel. A Sanskrit parallel published by Ernst Waldschmidt in 1979 is available on SuttaCentral as SF 241. A different discourse of the same name is found at SN 35.118. ↩

Rhys Davids follows the commentary in translating this “the cave of Indra’s Sāl Tree”. However the Sanskrit yāvacchailaguhāyām supports “hill cave”. ↩

Introduced in a minor role in DN 18, DN 19, and DN 20, Pañcasikha gets his moment to shine in this sutta. Outside of the Dīghanikāya, he appears only in SN 35.119. His name means “Fivecrest”, evidently in reference to his impressive hairdo; a nymph or group of nymphs bore the synonymous name Pañcacūḍā, “Five Topknots”. The centaur (gandhabba) was a wild rogue of music, dancing, and sex. He must be tamed, and here this is achieved through the power of love and filial respect. A less diplomatic approach is taken in Atharvaveda 4.37.7, where the gandharva with his “egg-crest” (śikhaṇḍino) is threatened with castration. ↩

The “arched harp” (vīṇa) was a stringed instrument held in the lap, whose form is clear from representations in ancient Indian sculptures in Bharhut, Amarāvatī, and Pawāyā, as well as the coins of Samudragupta. The strings, typically seven in number, were attached to the base of the soundbox and passed through holes in the parchment resonator to be tied with cords to the curved neck (these parts are listed at SN 35.246:4.17). It accompanied song or dance, and was played equally by men and women. It is not the modern Indian instrument called veena, which is a lute or stick zither, but rather is similar to the Burmese saung. | Gandhabbas are closely associated with music (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 3.2.4). Māra’s harp is described in the same way (SN 4.23:10.7), and tradition says they were in fact the same instrument. ↩

In the Buddhist hierarchy of divinity, gandhabbas occupy a more humble place than the gods of the thirty-three, yet here Pañcasikha appears with them in a position of honor. In DN 19:28.3 we saw that the even more exalted Brahmā takes the form of Pañcasikha. This fluidity is characteristic of old Vedic cosmology, where there is no clear hierarchy of divinity. The formalized hierarchies in Buddhism and Hinduism are a later conception. ↩

We will learn later of how Sakka’s appearance could be too disturbing for the Buddha while on retreat (DN 21:1.10.13). Pañcasikha, on the other hand, would appear alone, without a retinue. Note, however, that on subsequent occasions Sakka showed no such reticence, either because he was already a stream-enterer or because the Buddha was not in solitary retreat. ↩

The idea that the Buddha would be wooed by a love song seems like an absurd conceit, until you take into account the centaurs’ dangerous reputation as inveterate lechers. Pañcasikha wants to show that he is maturing and finally seeking a commitment in a respectable marriage. ↩

Suriyavaccasā (“Sunshine”) accords with the Vedic conception of the wife as the Sun (Sūryā, Rig Veda 10.85) who takes as husband Soma, the moon. She appears in Atharvaveda 8.10.27, which invokes the gandharvas with their female counterpart the “nymphs” (Pali accharā, Sanskrit apsaras). ↩

In Sanskrit literature, Timbaru (Sanskrit tumburu, “coriander”) was an elder gandharva musician in the courts of Indra and Kuvera. According to Rāmāyaṇa 3.4, he was cursed with a monstrous form by Kuvera due to an inappropriate lust for the nymph Rambhā. Upon his defeat at the hands of Rāma he was restored to his former status. Pañcasikha would have wanted to avoid a similar fate. Rather than Suriyavaccasā, the Sanskrit literature mentions his daughters Manuvantī and Sukeśī; the latter name (“fair-hair”) evokes the streaming rays of the sun (Vāyupurāṇa 69.49 = Brahmāṇḍapurāṇa 2.7.13). ↩

Aṅgīrasi means “shining one” and is etymologically linked with agni (“fire”). Suriyavaccasā earned the name due to both her radiant nature and her family connections: her father Timbaru was a son of Kaśyapa, who was (according to certain lineages) brother of Aṅgīras, from whom the Aṅgīrasas were descended. In the Arthavaveda—the only early non-Buddhist source for a nymph named Suriyavaccasā—aṅgīrasi is associated with witchcraft (Atharvaveda 12.5.52). Aṅgīrasa is also a patronymic of the Buddha (DN 32:3.14). ↩

“Saints” is arahantā, which I normally translate as “perfected ones”. ↩

Parinibbāpaya, “please quench me”. Pañcasikha subverts imagery employed by the Buddha—quenching thirst, cooling breezes, extinguished flames—to erotic effect. ↩

Pañcasikha is showing off his literary skill. The same image, the elephant, illustrates opposing qualities, peaceful and violent. In these two sides of sensual desire, he reveals, unconsciously perhaps, the rapacious side of his own nature. For Pañcasikha, the elephant bursting its bonds illustrates his crazed devotion, whereas later it illustrates breaking free of desire (DN 21:1.12.45). ↩

For how a married couple may stay together in this life and the next, see AN 4.55. ↩

Nipaka (“alert”) is explained in the Pali tradition as “wise”. The root pāl, rather, suggests the sense “on guard, alert”, which is supported by such phrases as “mindfully alert and on guard” (ārakkhasatino nipakkasatino, AN 5.114:3.1), where nipaka parallels ārakkha (“guarding”). Likewise, the Vedic sense is “one who keeps watch, a protector” (Rig Veda 4.45.6, 10.44.4). ↩

Pañcasikha is using the present participle jigīsāno in the historical present. ↩

A gandharva wedding is a pure love-match, without the blessing of parents or priests (Manu 3.32). Here, however, Pañcasikha wants to do the right thing and get the father’s blessing. ↩

If Pañcasikha was seeking the Buddha’s approval for his love-match, he was doomed to disappointment, as the Buddha and his mendicants do not involve themselves in arranging marriages. The Buddha sidesteps the issue by politely complementing Pañcasikha on his musicianship. ↩

“When did you compose” is also at MN 56:30.1. ↩

“Sister” (bhaginī) is a respectful term of address, but is normally used in a chaste sense. When Raṭṭhapāla calls his wives “sister”, they faint in shock (MN 82:23.4). ↩

Sikhaṇḍī (“egg-crested”) is the term for the centaur as seductive threat to women in Atharvaveda 4.37.7. It is also a poetic term for a peacock. ↩

It is rare for the Buddha to address a deity as “venerable” (āyasmā), a term usually reserved for monks. Moggallāna addresses Sakka as “the venerable Kosiya” at MN 37:10.6; Mahākassapa calls him Kosiya without honorific at Ud 3.7:3.12. | The word kosiya is explained by the commentaries as “owl”, which, if correct, would have been the totem for a clan of that name. It is, however, a patronymic: Rig Veda 1.10.11 has indra kauśika which means “Indra, son of Kuśika (or Kuśa)”. Kuśa grass is critical to the performance of Vedic rites, and the label probably initially implied “Brahmanized”, i.e. a king whose reign was authorized according to Vedic ritual. Kosiya is said to be a low class family name (Bu Pc 2:2.1.18). ↩

For salaḷa see note on SN 52.8:1.1. ↩

A paricārikā is a maid attending on a nymph (MN 37:8.12). | Bhūjati (variant bhuñjatī) does not seem to appear elsewhere. ↩

Sakka pointedly ignores this, but perhaps his shame at disturbing the Buddha’s meditation explains his oblique method of gaining an audience. ↩

This implies she was a stream-enterer. ↩

In Buddhism, sex is mutable between lives and even within one life (Bu Pj 1:10.6.1). Later Buddhists sometimes held that the status of a male was preferable. Here this is not stated outright, but the narrative implies that she thought her station was improved when becoming a male. Notably, it is not the Buddha who says this, but Sakka, relaying the story of another deity. That the proponent was a woman, at least formerly, is a trope of Indian literature: a woman is the ideal misogynist (see eg. Ja 61 or Śivapurāna chapter 4). Here, though, the situation is nuanced, because despite her (presumed) inferior status, she has better rebirth than the monks she served. ↩

The realm of centaurs is “inferior” because the centaurs are known for their ribald sexuality. ↩

Kutomukhā, which occurs only in this sutta, contrasts with sammukhā (“in the presence of”, “from the mouth of”). The commentary explains it as a rhetorical question, “Were you distracted or falling asleep?” Alternatively, it might mean “From whom did you learn the Buddha’s teaching?” It recurs later in the verses. This is not the only such case: duddiṭṭharūpaṁ and kāyaṁ brahmapurohitaṁ are other examples of terms found nowhere else in the Pali canon, yet found here both in prose and in verse. Clearly one has been copied from the other; it seems to me that the rarity of these terms and the greater coherence of the verses suggests that the prose is a (somewhat altered) summary of the verses. ↩

The commentary explains the verb “gained” (paṭilabhiṁsu) as serving dual roles here: “gaining” of “absorption mindfulness” (jhānasatiṁ), upon which they “gain” rebirth in the Brahmā realm. However, the verses below speak of “recollecting” (anussaraṁ) the Buddha’s teachings at this juncture. Compare Bu NP 23:1.1.20, where the king “remembered” his long-forgotten promise (vissaritvā cirena satiṁ paṭilabhitvā). AN 4.191:2.24 speaks of the “arising of memory” (satuppādo) in a deity when reminded of Dhamma passages they once recited as a monk. | The phrase kāyaṁ brahmapurohitaṁ is syntactically incongruous; I think it was clumsily copied from the verses below, where the required verb (ajjhagaṁsu) is present. The commentary explains it as “a Minister of Brahmā’s body” (brahmapurohitasarīraṁ), but in such contexts kāya usually means “host”. ↩

When bowing, it is a special sign of devotion to touch the feet of the one revered (eg. MN 89:9.1). ↩

Here Gopaka shifts from speaking about them in third person to speaking to them in second person. ↩

I.e. she was a lay person. ↩

Up until now, the verses have been spoken by Gopaka, but here a narrator appears. ↩

Normally rebirth is described as passing away in one realm then being reborn in another. Yet here the gods of the thirty-three—in their traditional abode on Mount Meru—were watching them literally fly from one realm to another. ↩

The truncated janind’ is not vocative janinda for Sakka, but nominative janindo for the Buddha. ↩

“Sakyan Sage” (sakyamuni) became a favorite epithet of the Buddha, but in early texts it appears only here and the Ratanasutta (Snp 2.1:4.2). ↩

“Sons” in a spiritual sense. ↩

The commentary says, “In this dispensation the explanation of the teaching is such that because of it, disciples become endowed with such qualities” (ettha sāsane evarūpā dhammappakāsanā, yāya sāvakā etehi guṇehi samannāgatā honti). This explains the feminine etādisī; pakasanā, which is normally neuter, is feminine here. This use is fairly common in later texts (it occurs at the conclusion of the Ṭīkā for this sutta). ↩

Kiṅkaṅkhati is a unique term for “doubt”. ↩

The end point of Gopaka’s speech is hard to determine, as there is no -ti to mark it. Various editions and translations either ignore the issue or end it in different places. The next line marks the beginning of Sakka’s direct speech to the Buddha, and I think it makes the best sense to assume that up to here he has been relating the story he was told. ↩

This question hints at Sakka’s own evolution from the battlegod of the Vedas to an acolyte of peace. ↩

Jealousy is wanting what others have, while stinginess is not wanting to share what you have. ↩

Compare with the side branch of dependent origination at DN 15:9.1, the origins of disputes at Snp 4.11, and the analysis of proliferation at MN 18. Note the constructive use of the “yes, and” method of questioning. Sakka finds wisdom due to his curiosity, neither being too-easily sated with a simple answer, nor quibbling that the answer is inadequate, but building on the foundations of understanding. ↩

Compare Snp 4.11:4.1. ↩

Here we depart from the normal sequence, which is that feelings give rise to craving (taṇhā). In Snp 4.11:6.1 it is said that pleasure and pain give rise to desire, not thought. ↩

“Judgments that emerge from the proliferation of perceptions” renders papañcasaññāsaṅkhā. Again the sequence departs from MN 18:16.1, which says that thoughts—which are normal and morally neutral psychological processes—give rise to “proliferation” (papañca), which is when craving and delusion cause thought to spin out of control. “Proliferation” then solidifies into “judgments” that fuel an individual’s delusion of “self” persisting through time. ↩

Jaññā is 3rd singular optative (cp. AN 9.6:3.4). ↩

That is, second jhāna is better than first jhāna. ↩

Overwhelmingly, the suttas speak of happiness in the path to liberation. They do, however, also acknowledge that sometimes temporary states of sadness leading to disillusionment can spur a person on the path. ↩

It is hard to know what the text is getting at here, as there is no “sadness” in any jhāna. ↩

Here the Buddha emphasizes the psychological and spiritual underpinnings of the “monastic code” (pātimokkha). ↩

The suttas frequently describe three kinds of search: for sensual pleasures, for continued existence, and for a spiritual path (eg. SN 45.161:7.3). The last search led the Buddha to awakening (MN 26:15.1). ↩

Sakka switches his term of address for the Buddha from mārisa to the more respectful bhante here, then back to mārisa below. This passage is found at MN 114:24.5, where bhante is used, suggesting it was imported from there. ↩

For a more detailed analysis of this, see MN 152. ↩

The Pali ekanta (“single”) here is a little tricky; it could mean either “the same” or “of one goal”. The Sanskrit has just eka (ekakāmā ekacchandāḥ, “one desire, one wish”), while the commentary explains the first and last terms as “one goal” and the middle terms as “one”. ↩

The Buddha points out that spiritual teachers, when faced with a world of experiential diversity, tend to prioritize their own experience or doctrine, dismissing others as less real or meaningful. ↩

Yogakkhema (“sanctuary from the yoke”) is a metaphor for Nibbāna that draws from the literal sense of khema as an oasis or sanctuary for men and beasts. After a hard day’s journey, a caravan would stop to rest, “unyoke” the draft animals, lay down the burden, and refresh themselves in the cool waters. ↩

This passage is quoted by name by Hāliddikāni at SN 22.4:1.4. The topic is picked up again in MN 31, where we see the extent to which Sakka has learned his lesson. | The text has “mendicants” here, but “ascetics and brahmins” immediately before and after. The quotation at SN 22.4:1.4 has “ascetics and brahmins”, so it is likely the text here is in error. ↩

This is the final substantive question of the series. It is picked up in MN 37:2.2 where Sakka, in a subsequent visit, inquires further as to the nature of those who have realized the ultimate goal. ↩

“Turbulence” is ejā, from a root meaning “motion, agitation”, and hence the opposite of the “imperturbable” (aneja) peace of the Buddha (SN 35.90). ↩

Compare Ajātasattu’s experience at DN 2:15.1. ↩

“Nectar” is ojā, in Vedic texts called soma or amṛta (“ambrosia” of immortality). The battle over nectar by gods (deva) and demons (asura) is a very ancient element of Indo-European mythology. ↩

Here Sakka makes a clean break from the violent delights he enjoyed in former (Vedic) times. ↩

Punarāyu is a unique term. It probably means that Sakka can extend his current fortunate birth due to the merit of Dhamma. ↩

To die “unconfused” or “consciously” is said to be a benefit of Dhamma practice (eg. AN 5.215:2.3). ↩

“Systematically” (or “according to method”, ñāyena) recalls ñāyapaṭipanno as a description of the noble ones. It means practicing according with the noble eightfold path, a “method” that yields definite results. ↩

This refers to the possibility of achieving perfection (arahattā). ↩

That is, after passing away as Sakka and being reborn as a human, he will subsequently return to the heaven realm. ↩

He predicts that his final life will be in this high realm that is inhabited by non-returners (AN 9.12:6.7). ↩

Karomasi is middle imperative 1st plural, “we should do”, glossed by the commentary as “we should pay homage” (namakkāraṁ karoma). ↩

Samaṁ is an indeclinable in the sense “likewise”. ↩

Sāmaṁ is an indeclinable in the sense “oneself, personally, one’s own”. ↩

A gandharva wedding must be a mutual love match. ↩

“Touching the ground with his hand” is a unique gesture in the early Pali, immortalized in later legend when the Buddha touches the ground to invoke the Earth Goddess as witness of his striving. ↩

Sakka is also said to have been accompanied by 80,000 deities at SN 40.10:4.4. This is one of many indications that this is a late discourse, several of which have been touched on above: late or unique terminology; fancy literary styles; adoption of doctrinal passages from elsewhere in a sometimes clumsy fashion; and so on. In determining whether a sutta is late or early, we do not rely on a single definitive reason, but on a cluster of independent criteria which taken together are most easily explained in terms of historical development. ↩

This discourse is copied from MN 10. The section on the four noble truths has been expanded with material mostly drawn from MN 141. These discourses are the most influential texts for modern Theravada meditation, prompting countless modern commentaries. Comparative study of the several parallel versions reveals that this discourse, while comprised almost entirely of early material, was compiled in this form as one of the latest texts in the Pali suttas (see SN 47.18 and note). | While mindfulness is always useful (SN 46.53:15.4), the “establishment of mindfulness” (satipaṭṭhāna) refers especially to a conscious development of contemplative practices based on mindfulness, i.e. “mindfulness meditation”. ↩

The phrase ekāyano maggo (“path to convergence”) is given multiple meanings in commentaries and ancient Chinese translations. Outside of satipaṭṭhāna, it is used in only one context in Pali, where it means to “come together with” (MN 12:37.5). At SN 47.18:3.4 the phrase is spoken by Brahmā, which suggests it was a Brahmanical term. Yajñavalkya—in a core passage full of details shared with the suttas—uses it for a place where things unite or converge (Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 2.4.11; in the same sense also at Chāndogya Upaniṣad 7.5.2; Mahābhārata 14.19.1–2). Thus satipaṭṭhāna leads to everything “coming together as one”. In other words, as seventh factor of the noble eightfold path, it leads to samādhi, the eighth factor (SN 45.1:3.9; see also MN 44:12.3). Ekāyana is also a name for a certain Sanskrit scripture (in a list of texts at Chāndogya Upaniṣad 7.1.2, 7.1.4, 7.2.1, 7.7.1; Puruṣottamasaṁhitā 1.10; Praśnasaṁhitā 2.38). Now, the latter text discusses the ekāyana as nivṛtti, “renunciation”, which is, in fact, introduced to the Vedic system by Yajñavalkya in the above-cited passage. Thus as a scripture it probably originally referred to that very passage exemplifying the Upaniṣadic teachings, which are otherwise omitted from the Chāndogya list. ↩

The idiom kāye kāyānupassī, literally “observes a body in the body” refers to focusing on a specific aspect of embodied experience, such as the breath, the postures, etc. | “Keen” (or “ardent”, ātāpī) implies effort, while “aware” (sampajāno) is the wisdom of understanding situation and context. | “Covetousness and displeasure” (abhijjhādomanassaṁ) are the strong forms of desire and aversion that are overcome by sense restraint in preparation for meditation. ↩

“Feelings” (vedanā) are the basic tones of pleasant, painful, or neutral, not the complexes we call “emotions”. ↩

“Mind” (citta) is simple awareness. In meditation contexts, “mind” is often similar in meaning to samādhi. ↩

“Principles” (dhammā) are the natural “systems” of cause and effect that underlie the “teachings”. The renderings “mind objects” or “mental qualities” are incorrect, as many of the things spoken of in this section are neither mind objects nor mental qualities. “Phenomena” is a possible translation, but the emphasis is not on the “appearance” of things, but on the “principles” governing their conditional relations. ↩

The context here—a mendicant gone to the forest—establishes that this practice takes place in the wider context of the Gradual Training. Indeed, this whole sutta can be understood as an expansion of this phrase, mentioned briefly at DN 2:67.3. ↩

The most fundamental meditation instruction in Buddhism. Notice how the Buddha phrases it: not “concentrate on the breath” as an object, but rather “breathing” as an activity to which one brings mindfulness. ↩

The stages of breath meditation are not meant to be done deliberately, but to be observed and understood as the natural process of deepening meditation. When starting out, the breath is somewhat rough and coarse. ↩

Over time, the breath becomes more subtle and soft. ↩

Contextually the idiom “whole body” (sabbakāya) here refers to the breath, marking the fuller and more continuous awareness that arises with tranquility. Some practitioners, however, interpret it as the “whole physical body”, broadening awareness to encompass the movement and settling of energies throughout the body. ↩

The “physical process” (kāyasaṅkhāraṁ) is the breath (SN 41.6:1.8). ↩

“Internally” is one’s own body, “externally” the bodies of others, or external physical phenomena. This distinction is applied broadly in Buddhist meditation, but it is more relevant in some contexts than others. In the case of the breath, one is focusing on one’s own breath, but when contemplating, say, a dead body, or the material elements, there is more of an external dimension. Starting with “me” in here and the “world” out there, this practice dissolves this distinction so that we see we are of the same nature as everything else. ↩

This is the vipassanā (“insight” or “discernment”) dimension of meditation, observing not just the rise and fall of phenomena, but also their conditioned “nature” as being “liable” (-dhamma) to impermanence. The meaning of this passage is explained at SN 47.42. Apart from these passages, vipassanā in satipaṭṭhāna pertains specially to the observation of principles. ↩

Mindfulness meditation leads to a range of knowledges as detailed by Anuruddha at SN 52.6 and SN 52.11–24. An arahant is “independent” of any attachment (eg. MN 143), but satipaṭṭhāna is also taught to give up dependency on views of the past and future (DN 29:40.1). ↩

In early Pali, this practice is found only in the two Satipaṭṭhānasuttas and the closely related Kāyagatāsatisutta (MN 119). It is practiced by developing a reflexive awareness of one’s posture and activity as it proceeds, often assisted by moving slowly and carefully. ↩

“Situational awareness” (sampajañña) understands the context and purpose of activities. The main examples here illustrate the activities of daily monastic life: leaving the monastery on almsround, restraint while in the town, care wearing the robes, then mindfully eating and going to the toilet. ↩

This practice is intended to counter sexual desire and obsession. The primary focus is on one’s own body, rather than another’s body, although that can be brought in also. By focusing on aspects of our body that we normally prefer to ignore, we move toward a healthy sense of acceptance and neutrality toward our body. ↩

Thirty-one parts are mentioned in early texts, later expanded to thirty-two with the addition of the “brain” (matthaluṅga). ↩

The “bag with openings at both ends” is the body. Not all the varieties of grains and beans can be positively identified. ↩

While meditation on the elements is commonly taught in early texts, this phrase is found only in the two Satipaṭṭhānasuttas and the Kāyagatāsatisutta. Detailed instructions are found in such suttas as MN 28 and MN 140. This meditation works in any posture, whereas breath meditation is best done sitting, to allow the breath to become still. ↩

The “elements” are the four states of matter as represented by their primary material example and their dominant property: earth as a solid with the property of resisting or upholding; water as a liquid with the property of binding; air as a gas with the property of movement; and fire (“heat” or “energy”) as plasma with the property of transformation. ↩

This gruesome image shows that butchery of cows was a normal feature of ancient Indian life. ↩

Cremation was expensive and not available to everyone. Bodies might be left in the charnel ground for a variety of reasons, such as local customs, lack of funds, or in cases of inauspicious death such as murder or execution. This is still seen in some places today, and monastics occasionally take the opportunity to practice meditation beside a corpse. However the wording of the Pali sounds like an imaginative exercise. ↩

The observed corpse is not gendered. The purpose is not to become repulsed by an objectified other, but to understand the mortality of one’s own body. ↩

It takes decades for bones to rot to powder, again suggesting it is an imaginative contemplation. ↩

Literally “a feeling among the feelings”; the practice shows that the meditator contemplates specific feelings as they occur. ↩

Pali employs direct quotes to indicate reflexive awareness: you feel the feeling and you know that you feel the feeling. It does not mean that you have to literally say “I feel a pleasant feeling”, although some adopt that as a meditation method. ↩

Feelings “of the flesh” (sāmisa) are associated with the body and sensual desires (SN 36.31:4.1). ↩

Feelings “not of the flesh” (nirāmisa) are associated with renunciation and especially with the jhānas and liberation (SN 36.31:5.1). ↩

This would include the feelings of loss, doubt, and dejection that can occur during the spiritual path (see MN 44:28.6). ↩

The feeling of the fourth jhāna and higher liberations (SN 36.31:8.2). ↩

In Buddhist theory, awareness of the presence or absence of qualities such as greed is explained on three levels. There is the simple happenstance of whether greed is present at that time or not. Then there is the mind freed of greed through the power of absorption. Finally there is the liberation from greed which comes with full awakening. ↩

The mind is “constricted internally” due to dullness and “scattered externally” due to the distractions of desire (SN 51.20:18.1). ↩

The following terms “expansive” (mahaggata), “supreme” (anuttara), “immersed” (samāhita), and “freed” (vimutta) all refer to states of absorption and/or awakening. ↩

The Satipaṭṭhānavibhaṅga of the Pali Abhidhamma only mentions the hindrances and awakening factors in this section (Vb 7). This, together with a range of other evidence, suggests that this was the original content of the observation of principles. ↩

Here causality is introduced. In the contemplation of mind, the meditator was aware of the presence or absence of desire in the mind. Now they look deeper, investigating the cause of desire and understanding how to be free of it forever. This contemplation of the “principles” of cause and effect is the distinctive feature of this section. ↩

The Buddhist schools debated whether this included physical tiredness or not. The Theravada argued that it was purely a mental laziness, as even the Buddha got sleepy. ↩

“Form” (rūpa) is one’s own body and the external material world experienced through the senses. More subtly, it represents the “appearance” of physical phenomena, even when experienced solely in the mind as color, visions, etc. ↩

“Perception” (saññā) is the recognition or interpretation of experience in terms of meaningful wholes. We see, for example, “color” yet we perceive a “person”. In the Vinaya we find many examples where a person perceived things in one way, yet they turned out to be something else. ↩

In the five aggregates, saṅkhārā is a synonym for “volition” (cetanā). The traditions later used it as a catch-all category for everything that does not fit in the other aggregates. In the suttas, however, the purpose of the aggregates is not to classify everything that exists, but to contemplate aspects of experience that we tend to identify as a “self”. ↩

At SN 35.232:3.2 the “fetter that arises dependent on both” is identified as “desire and lust” (chandarāga). ↩

These seven factors that lead to awakening (bojjhaṅgā, SN 46.5) are commonly presented in opposition to the five hindrances (eg. SN 46.2, SN 46.23, SN 46.55). ↩

“Mindfulness” includes the recollection of the teachings (SN 46.3:1.8) as well as mindfulness meditation. ↩

Likewise, this includes the inquiry into dhammas as “teachings” as well as “phenomena” or “principles”. ↩

Due to their development of the two wings of samatha and vipassanā meditation as described in this sutta, practiced in the context of the teaching and training as a whole, the meditator realizes the four noble truths at the moment of stream-entry. ↩

The sutta now proceeds in analytical fashion, digging deeper into the details of the four noble truths. The fundamental definitions were taught in the Buddha’s first sermon (SN 56.11:4.1). ↩

As at DN 15.4.3, jāti is invariably defined as the rebirth of beings, not as simple arising. The same applies to old age and death. ↩

In this and following definitions we mainly find mere verbal variations of the basic term. ↩

Dukkha (“pain”, “suffering”) is here restricted to physical pain. Elsewhere it may be any kind of painful feeling, while in the four noble truths it is suffering of any sort, including subtle forms of existential suffering. ↩

Domanassa normally means “sadness”, but sometimes it contrasts with desire, in which case it is a form of aversion. ↩

Piya often refers to those who are dear and beloved, but as shown here it can also mean simply anything that is liked. ↩

This is an example of “painful feeling not of the flesh”. The Buddha is here denying the efficacy of prayer, invocation, or magic spells. ↩

The following list of properties that relate to the senses gradually moves from the more basic to the more sophisticated. ↩

“Eye consciousness” is aware only of “light”; it sees colors but does not interpret them. ↩

“Contact” or “stimulus” happens when the sense base, the sense object, and the sense consciousness all occur together. ↩

“Perception” interprets the “light” that is seen, organizing it in meaningful wholes. For example, the eye sees the color white, while perception recognizes that it is “white”, and further, that that white color is in fact a “wall”. ↩

To continue the example, once the light has been interpreted by perception as a “wall”, we then make the choice to walk around it rather than through it. Choices therefore depend on perceptions. ↩

“Thought” is vitakka. ↩

“Consideration” is vicāra, a more sustained exercise of thought. ↩

From here we have the standard definitions of the items of the noble eightfold path (SN 45.8:3.2, MN 141:24.1). ↩

Mindfulness is not a path in and of itself, but rather is the seventh factor of the eightfold path. ↩

“View” (diṭṭhi, Sanskrit dṛṣṭi) is “seeing” and hence a term for “understanding” (Aitareya Upaniṣad 3.2). In Buddhism, it means a particular way of seeing or perspective, a theory or view through which one makes sense of the world. By itself it is neutral, although “views” in plural sometimes stands for the thicket of wrong views. ↩

The fourth noble truth is the path, while the first path factor is the noble truths. These two teachings are different perspectives on the same dhamma. | Ignorance is described in the opposite way (MN 9:64.1–66.7, SN 12.2:14.2). ↩

Saṅkappa is normally a synonym of vitakka in the suttas, hence it may be rendered “thought” (SN 14.8:3.3, MN 60:24.2). It is, however, not just verbalized thought, but the direction in which one applies the mind, hence “intention” (MN 41:14.3), “resolve”, or “purpose”. It has a directionality to it: in Rig Veda 10.164.5 it is the “evil intent” wished upon those who we hate, whereas in Atharva Veda 3.25.2 it is a quality of the arrow of love. For this reason, I usually render it as “purpose”. This factor is the emotional counterpart of right view, ensuring that the path is motivated by love and compassion. ↩

Abyāpāda is “non-ill-will” or simply “good will”. ↩

The factors of speech and action are defined in detail under the gradual training at MN 27:13.4, and under the ten pathways of skillful deeds at MN 41:12.4. ↩

The first three of the five precepts. | “Sexual misconduct” is the betrayal of trust or otherwise causing harm in a sexual relationship. ↩

Wrong livelihood is defined at MN 117:29.2 and AN 5.177:1.3, and in detail for renunciates at DN 2:56.1. ↩

Expanded to a full saṁyutta at SN 49. ↩

Detailed especially in SN 47 and MN 10. ↩

“Immersion” (samādhi) is treated in SN 53 and throughout the Suttas, eg. SN 12.23:2.15, MN 44:12.2 and notes. The primary sense is the mind “collected” or “immersed” inside itself, with a secondary connotation of radiant illumination. | Before the Buddha, we find samādhi and related terms in the sense of gathering kindling for the fire. The past participle samāhita occurs in the sense “collected, contained”, as the essence of waters are “contained” in the Sun (Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 5.1.2.7). Certain Upaniṣadic usages presage the Buddhist sense, though expressed in a mystical form designed to be as obscure as possible. A realized sage, being “collected”, sees only the self in the self and is free from evil, having become one with Divinity (Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.4.24). For such a one, the whole world is “contained” in the space within the heart—earth and sky, fire and wind, sun and moon, all beings and all desires (Chāndogya Upaniṣad 8.1.3–5). The hidden Self, finer than the finest, larger than the largest, may only be discerned by one who is peaceful and “collected” (Kaṭha Upaniṣad 2.24). ↩

Jhāna is a state of “elevated consciousness” (adhicitta), so all the terms have an elevated sense. | The plural form indicates that “sensual pleasures” includes sense experience, which the meditator can turn away from since they no longer have any desire for it. | The “unskillful qualities” are the five hindrances. | The “rapture and bliss born of seclusion” is the happiness of abandoning the hindrances and freedom from sense impingement. | “Placing the mind and keeping it connected” (vitakka, vicāra) uses terms that mean “thought” in coarse consciousness, but which in “elevated consciousness” refer to the subtle function of applying the mind to the meditation. ↩

Each jhāna begins as the least refined aspect of the previous jhāna ends. This is not consciously directed, but describes the natural process of settling. The meditator is now fully confident and no longer needs to apply their mind: it is simply still and fully unified. ↩

The emotional response to bliss matures from the subtle thrill of rapture to the poise of equanimity. Mindfulness is present in all states of deep meditation, but with equanimity it becomes prominent. ↩

The emphasis is on “develop in this way” (evaṁ bhāveyya), that is, with the full practice including deep absorption as the culmination of the path as a whole. ↩

A similar promise of results in at most seven years is found at DN 25:22.9, MN 10:46.3, and MN 85:59.3; and at most ten years at AN 10.46:7.3. ↩

Kumārakassapa was ordained at twenty (Kd 1:75.1.1). He features in the Vammikasutta (MN 23), and his verses are collected in the Theragāthā (Thag 2.41). He was declared the foremost of those with brilliant speech (AN 1.217), apparently on the basis of this discourse. | The Pāyāsisutta is the only major Buddhist text that has a Jain parallel, Paesi-kahāṇayaṁ, a similar dialogue between Paesi and Keśin in Setavyā. ↩

Setavyā was north-east of Sāvatthī. ↩

Pāyāsi was a khattiya yet he receives a brahmadeyya. The sense of brahmadeyya as a donation to brahmins is well attested in inscriptions, so I think this is likely a mistake in the text, rather than evidence that the practice was not for brahmins only. ↩

This is wrong view per MN 117:5.1. ↩

This idiom recurs at AN 6.38:1.5 where, as here, it refers to a well-known view and cannot mean that they have never heard of it. There the text and commentary read māhaṁ, which with the aorist is prohibitive not negatory. It is an idiom expressing dislike. ↩

While the world “down here” is bogged down in its messy and ephemeral issues, the heavenly bodies proceed in their serene, glorious, stately indifference. Ignoring gravity, self-luminous, and apparently eternal, they operate according to what appears to be an entirely different set of rules, a “meta-physics”. What Newton did in physics the Buddha did in spirituality: show that the heavens, despite appearances, operate with the same set of conditioned rules as apply down here. ↩

Kassapa’s argument here doesn’t directly establish his conclusion. It is possible that gods exist on an entirely separate plane that has nothing to do with kamma and rebirth. ↩

This is still a major factor in shaping belief. People will reject the opinions of experts and believe people that they know. ↩

Compare Jaiminīya Brāhmaṇa 1.42, where Varuṇa asphyxiated his son Bhṛgu in order to send him on a journey to the “other world”, inducing a near-death experience. Bhṛgu saw men cutting other men to pieces and eating them, and other sights both horrifying and beautiful, all the while wondering if what he saw was real, before his breath was returned to him. ↩

Follow PTS reading uddassetvā, which at MN 82:11.9 has the sense “visit”. ↩

Kassapa, however, has not established the existence of an afterlife, he has merely refuted Pāyāsi’s argument. Per Occam’s razor, the burden of proof lies on the one who wishes to establish the existence of the afterlife, not on the one who denies it. His arguments, however, become more persuasive if they are understood as building on the initial agreement on the divinity of the sun and moon. He knows that Pāyāsi accepts some form of other world, even if he says otherwise, so the argument hinges on whether Pāyāsi’s methods are sufficient to disprove the kind of other world that Kassapa proposes, i.e. one driven by kamma. ↩

Follow PTS reading ubbāhati. Cf. AN 3.93:6.4 for the sense “transport”. ↩

36,000,000 years. ↩

This recognizes the relativity of time. ↩

Pāyāsi makes a good point; he only relies on sources that he knows he can trust. ↩

Kassapa establishes the empirical method by which these truths are known. Science extends knowledge by means of external instruments, while meditation extends the scope of consciousness. A non-scientist cannot understand how a scientist establishes their conclusions, and can only rely on trust in the scientific establishment. Likewise a non-meditator cannot understand the capacity of expanded consciousness. ↩

The commentary explains opabhoggā (“reward”) as pādaparicārikā (“wife”). ↩

Read opāṭesi. ↩

Prefer Mahāsaṅgīti reading yāva vijāyāmi over PTS yāva jānāmi (“until I know”); it echoes yāva vijāyāmi above. The phrase is not fully coherent, which is understandable given the circumstances. ↩

“Irrationally” is ayoniso, literally “not sourcewise”. This passage gives a nice real world example of what it means: the means employed are unrelated to the end sought. ↩

Pāyāsi’s experiments were cruel, but no more so than many recorded in recent history. ↩

We assume that a soul must be immaterial and invisible, but clearly this was not always the case at the time. From DN 1 we know that there was an almost inexhaustible variety of views about the self or soul. ↩

This echoes Upaniṣadic discussions of the nature of the dream state and its relation to death. See for example Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 2.1.18, which says one might become a brahmin or king in a dream. ↩

Velāsikā (“coquette”) is literally “party girl”. ↩

Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.3.19 describes the soul returning to the body like a tired hawk returning to the nest. ↩

Aside from the cruelty, this echoes the dictum attributed to Galileo: “Measure what is measurable, and make measurable what is not so.” Given sufficient precision, this method could be effective in testing for the existence for a physical soul that has mass. ↩

A dead body will, if anything, weigh less due to excretion and dehydration. ↩

The misconception that iron is lighter when heated is repeated elsewhere (eg. SN 51.22:4.1). In fact, assuming there are no chemical reactions, it will be very slightly heavier due to relativistic effects, yet less dense and hence more buoyant. These changes are too small to be detected by Pāyāsi’s methods, though. ↩

The commentary explains āmato as addhamato (“half-dead”). ↩

At AN 9.37 this rather abrupt insertion more aptly describes a deep meditation. ↩

Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 2.4.8 employs the same metaphor in the search for the soul. ↩

Such “matted-hair ascetics” are apparently the “forest hermits” (vānaprastha) whose lifestyle Kauṭilya describes as “celibacy, sleeping on the ground, wearing matted hair and antelope skin, offering daily fire sacrifice, bathing, venerating gods, ancestors, and guests, and eating forest produce” (Arthaśāstra 1.3.11, Olivelle’s translation). ↩

Accept PTS reading gavesasi. ↩

Pāyāsi honestly acknowledges the role of social conformity and shame in shaping views. ↩

Although this became the first story of the Jātaka collection (Ja 1), here it is not a Jātaka, as it is not framed as a past life of the Buddha. ↩

While the places are not specified, the journey from “east to west” across desolate lands suggests they may have been venturing from the rich plains of the Ganges west across the Thar Desert of Rajasthan. ↩

Read with PTS gadrabharathena (“donkey cart”) for bhadrena rathena (“fine cart”). ↩

The obviously suspicious stranger depicts the genuine dangers of trade in unknown regions, warning the traveler of raiding tribes as well as supernatural creatures. ↩

Again the criteria that only those who are known may be trusted. ↩

The ancient Indian game of dice involved casting vibhītaka seeds (also known as “bedda nuts”, from Terminalia bellirica) in a hollow, from which the players would take a handful. A number divisible by four was “perfect” (kaṭa), so the fifth seed meant a “losing” hand (kali; cf. apaṇṇaka in MN 60 and notes). ↩

Pajohissāmi is related to Sanskrit juhoti, usually used in the sense “to offer as libation”, a meaning accepted by the commentary here. More likely it simply means to “roll out” (like pouring a sacrifice) by analogy. ↩

Gāmapaṭṭaṁ (variants -padaṁ, -paddhanaṁ, -patthaṁ, pajjaṁ) is explained by the commentary as an abandoned village site. ↩

The sunk cost fallacy. ↩

Say what you will about Pāyāsi, he had character. ↩

Compare DN 5:4.5. ↩

Bilaṅga is allowed with other medicinal fruits at Kd 6:6.1.4. It is Sanskrit viḍaṅga, identified as embelia ribes or “false black pepper”. | For guḷavālakāni, guḷa is “ball”, vāla is “tail”; compare macchavāḷaka (“fish-tailed”) at Kd 15:29.4.2. ↩

Cp. AN 5.147, AN 9.20. ↩

Gavampati also appears in SN 56.30; see note there for a detailed discussion. | Divāvihāra is the “day’s meditation”, while divāseyya is “siesta”. ↩

This late sutta satirizes the failings of Sunakkhatta in a fashion so broad that it borders on slapstick. The town of Anupiya is mentioned only here. ↩

The Bhaggava clan was descended from the ancient sage Bhagu (Sanskrit Bhṛgu). They received the gift of fire conveyed by Mātariśvan the wind from the god Agni (eg. Rig Veda 1.60.1). In Pali they appear as potters (eg. MN 81:19.3, MN 140:1.3, SN 1.50:11.2, SN 2.24:12.2). Archaeologists refer to the strata around the Buddha’s time as the Northern Black Polished Ware culture on account of the distinctive highly glazed polish that was achieved on the pottery of the time. This, together with the production of iron, marked a significant advance in the mastery of fire. Thus potters were no mere humble craftsmen, but leading technological innovators. ↩

Sunakkhatta’s dismal spiritual career began when he met the Buddha in MN 105. In DN 6:5.3 we learn that, after being ordained three years, he spoke of his limited success in meditation. The current sutta and MN 12 deal with Sunakkhatta’s bitter criticisms of the Buddha shortly after his disrobal. ↩

A candidate for ordination is expected to go for refuge to the Buddha, and may be said to live dedicated (uddissa) to him (Kd 1:23.4.1). Moreover, a noble disciple is unable to dedicate themselves to another teacher (AN 1.276:1.1). But when the Buddha called candidates to go forth, he spoke of practice rather than personal devotion: “Come, monk. The Teaching is well-proclaimed. Practice the spiritual life to make a complete end of suffering.” (Kd 1:6.32.3) ↩

He makes a similar criticism at MN 12:3.8. ↩

See detailed discussion of this idiom in MN 12:2.5. Here the form varies somewhat. The pronoun (mayā) in instrumental explicitly qualifies “Dhamma taught by me”. Elsewhere the pronoun in genitive qualifies atthāya, “the goal for him”. ↩

There are at least eight spellings for this tribe, including thulu, bumu and khulu. Below we meet a member of the ruling clan of the tribe named korakhattiya. I propose that kora is “of Kuru” by way of secondary derivation; cp. Koravya as a regular name for the kings of Kuru. Thus korakhattiya is not a personal name, but rather “the aristocrat of Kuru”. The name of the city uttarakā means “northern”, and Kuru is indeed northern. Occam’s razor would urge us not to assume the existence of an otherwise unknown tribe on such a dubious term when it can be explained more parsimoniously as an ancient misspelling of Kuru. The Chinese at DA 15 (T 1, 67a15) has 白土 (“white clay”), which does not seem to clear it up. ↩

This practice is further described, along with the “cow vow”, at MN 57. ↩

“Holy man” is sādhurūpo (cp. Dhp 263, AN 6.54:26.1). ↩

Alasaka is otherwise unknown in early Pali. Sanskrit medical texts describe it as flatulent indigestion. This agrees with the subcommentary’s ajīraṇena āmarogena (“indigestion”). | In this sutta, the Buddha is depicted as making specific predictions about the future, whereas normally he does not and probably cannot. Rather, he makes conditional predictions that if such courses are pursued, such results will follow. ↩

The terrifying Kālakañjas are mentioned at DN 20:12.5. ↩

This whole passage is unprecedented in early Buddhism. If Sunakkhatta was indeed able to revive the dead with three punches, it would explain why he thought so little of the Buddha’s powers. But the ease with which this information is obtained contrasts with the elaborate failures of Pāyāsi (DN 23). ↩

Spellings for Kaḷāramaṭṭaka vary greatly. ↩

In these practices we see some examples of the vows or observances (vata) that Buddha rejected as “grasping at precepts and observances” ↩

A diet of pure meat is still undertaken today by certain would-be gurus. ↩

Compare the “vow of restraint in the directions” in the Jain Tattvārthasūtra 7.1. ↩

Āsādimhase is middle aorist plural. Below Sunakkhatta again refers to himself in plural, but as usual I render with singular. ↩

The Burmese reading pāthikaputta means “son of a traveler”. However the commentary says Pāṭika (or Pāthika) was the name of his father. ↩

For ñāṇavādo (“one who speaks from knowledge”) see AN 9.38:3.3, AN 10.24:2.1, MN 26:15.7. ↩

“Ambiguous” is dvayagāminī, literally “two-going”. ↩

Apadāna means “what has been left over, leavings, traces”. ↩

This kind of elaborate display is commonly depicted in late texts, but is not otherwise found in early Pali. ↩

Compare DN 1:1.36.3. The following passage is largely adapted from the Brahmajālasutta. ↩

Text has suññaṁ, but this appears to be a mistake, since the mansion is no longer “empty” as Brahmā is already there. Follow DN 1:2.4.3, which lacks suññaṁ. ↩

This statement is not explicitly phrased as a question, but the Mahāsaṅgīti edition inconsistently punctuates it as one. It makes more sense in context, especially as a response to the initial question: Kathaṁvihitakaṁ (“How do you describe …”) … Evaṁvihitakaṁ (“Is this how you describe …”). ↩

This is adopted from DN 1:2.2.1. These philosophers belong with the “partial eternalists”. ↩

DN 1:2.7.2. ↩

DN 1:2.10.2. ↩

DN 1:2.31.1. ↩

The Buddha refers to the events of this sutta at DN 8:23.2, but apart from that Nigrodha (“Banyan”) appears to be unknown. A “wanderer” may or may not be Brahmanical, but in DN 8 Nigrodha is called tapabrahmacārī, which suggests he was a celibate student of a Brahmanical teacher. | The commentary describes udumbarikā (“Fig”) as devī (“Queen”), while DA 8 says she is a “brahmin lady”. She too does not seem to appear elsewhere. ↩

Sandhāna (“Conciliation”) was recognized as an eminent lay follower at (AN 6.120–139:1.14). ↩

“One-eyed cow” is gokāṇā. ↩

Orodheyyāma normally means “enclose, trap” like ox in a pen (AN 6.60:3.1), but here it is glossed in the commentary as vinandheyyāma (“twist around”). ↩

This discourse highlights the Buddha’s method of engaging with people of other religions. He is open-hearted and interested in their views. He prefers to build on common ground, but is not afraid to criticize when it is warranted. And his aim is not to win converts, but to help people be free of suffering. ↩

“Higher disgust of sin” renders adhijegucche. The idea is that people are tainted with corruption, somewhat comparable to the notion of “original sin”, although due to their own actions in the past rather than ancestral legacy. In “disgust” at that sin, they practice forms of fervent mortification (tapas) to burn out the corruption. ↩

The phrase kathaṁ santā is unique; it echoes evaṁ sante below. ↩

See the passage at DN 8:14.3 and notes thereto. ↩

The Buddha shifts attention from the external practice to the psychological state that accompanies it. ↩

“In expectation” (sāpekkho): when they give up something they cannot eat, they expect to be given more suitable food. ↩

Asanivicakkaṁ is “forked lightning”, see Rig Veda 4.35.2 where vicakra means “divided”. | Dantakūṭa is “the crown of the tooth”. ↩

“Sneaks” is attānaṁ adassayamāno, literally, “not showing himself”. They like to hang about with lay folk, but hide the fact that they do so. ↩

As here, this item typically follows “wrong view”. At AN 10.78:1.9 it is said to be a bad quality of Jain ascetics. Thus being “attached to one’s own views” refers both to the subjective clinging as well as the objective incorrectness of the views. ↩

A “fourfold restraint” (cātuyāma, or cāujjāma in Jain Ardhamagadhi) is attributed to Jain founder Pārśva in Isibhāsiyāiṁ 31, where it is an abbreviated list: “from refraining from killing to refraining from possessions” (pāṇātivāta-veramaṇeṇaṁ jāvā pariggaha-veramaṇeṇaṁ); the missing items are not stealing (asteya) and truth (satya). The Jain text Uttarādhyayanasūtra 23 shows that Mahāvīra added nakedness to make five. Five are also found in Yogasūtra 2.30 and the Jain Tattvārthasūtra 7: non-harming (ahiṁsā), truth (satya), no stealing (asteya), celibacy (brahmacarya), and non-possessiveness (aparigrahā). | A different “fourfold restraint” is said to be a Jain practice at DN 2:29.2. ↩

This extends the basic precept. The same analysis is applied to the “ten ways of performing deeds” at AN 3.163. | The distinction between one’s own action and another’s action is noted at Isibhāsiyāiṁ 31.42, although the wording and sense are different. ↩

Bhāvitamāsīsati is unique. In this and similar contexts, the Pali tradition says bhāvita (“reward”, normally “developed”) is the “five sense pleasures” as they see it (bhāvitaṁ nāma tesaṁ saññāya pañca kāmaguṇā; cp. MN 56 commentary: ettha ca bhāvitanti pañcakāmaguṇā), explaining that this is a usage of the sectarians (Saddanīti ch. 4: titthiyasamaye pana bhāvitoti kāmaguṇo vuccati). ↩

This passage sets a powerful template for sincere engagement. ↩

For appaṭibhāna in the sense “nothing to say”, see Chāndogya Upaniṣad 6.7.2. ↩

This whole ending sequence is unique. ↩

Mātulā means “maternal uncle”. This Magadhan village is mentioned only here and Cp 9:39.2. ↩

As at DN 16:2.26.1. ↩

Two parables on mindfulness expand this idea (SN 47.6, SN 47.7). ↩

Evamidaṁ indicates entailment, as at SN 56.21:1.3, MN 73:13.2, DN 16:4.2.4. ↩

We have heard the story of the wheel-turning monarch Mahāsudassana in DN 17. Daḷhanemi appears only here. His name means “Strong-rim”, such being one of the characteristics of the Wheel. His story of renunciation shares much in common with that of Maghadeva (MN 83). ↩

“Receded back” (osakkitaṁ): like a woman shrinking away from a man’s unwanted advances (DN 12:16.12). ↩

The same point of view is expressed at Bi Pc 21:1.4, where sex workers teased nuns, suggesting they enjoy themselves while young and ordain when old. The Buddhist position is that Dhamma can be practiced at any age. ↩

The signs of the renunciate predate Buddhism. ↩

The “royal seer” (rājisi, Sanskrit rājarṣi) is described by Kauṭilya (Arthaśāstra 1.7.1). Such a king should pursue pleasures in moderation, rely on good advice, and work energetically for the welfare and prosperity of his people. ↩

“Inherited from your father” (pettikaṁ dāyajjaṁ) calls back to the four satipaṭṭhānas that for a mendicant are “the domain of your fathers” (pettike visaye). In both cases they are to be earned, not conferred by lineage. ↩

“The noble duty of a wheel-turning monarch” (ariye cakkavattivatte; this is locative singular). Ariya (“noble”) qualifies “duty” (vatta), as it does in the title below, cakkavattiariyavatta, rather than “monarch”. Normally ariya is reserved for those who have attained the Buddhist path, but here we might have a rare use of ariya in reference to Indo-Aryan (Vedic) culture. Compare the use of ariyaka for Indo-Aryan language (Bu Pj 1:8.4.10), and ariyaṁ āyatanaṁ for the “civilized region” (DN 16:1.28.7, AN 6.96:1.3, Ud 8.6:17.9). However, the commentary says it simply means “flawless” (niddoso). ↩

Saṁvidahassu is second middle imperative. ↩

Pavattittha is aorist middle. (A)dhammakāra (“(in)justice”) doesn’t seem to occur elsewhere in early Pali. It is found in Ja 513 and Ja 498, both times in the context of just rule. ↩

“Provide” (anuppadeti) is used elsewhere in the sense of paying back a loan (AN 3.20:3.5), serving honored guests (SN 7.2:2.6), paying wages (DN 31:32.2), or a king supplying provisions for essential workers to do their job (DN 5:11.8). It is thus more about fulfilling a moral obligation of fairness than offering charity. ↩

Where the phrase “from time to time go to them” (te kālena kālaṁ upasaṅkamitvā) occurs elsewhere in the suttas, it is always followed by “ask and question” (paripucchati paripañhati). Here, however, the second verb is “you should learn” (pariggaṇheyyāsi). ↩

“Own ideas” is sa-mata. ↩

Pabbanti is unusual and probably unique in early Pali. It is related to Sanskrit parvati (“fill”) and is explained by the commentary as vaḍḍhanti (“grow, prosper”). | I assume janapadā (“countries”) is a misspelling of jānapadā (“people of the country”), as janapada is otherwise in singular. ↩

“Military officers” (anīkaṭṭhā) would have been standing officers in the army. According to both the commentary here and Monier-Williams’ Sanskrit Dictionary (anīkastha), it includes elephant officers, who would have stood at the head of the army. | “Professional advisers” (mantassājīvino) is explained by the commentary as those who make a living from giving wise advice. ↩

Ensuring citizens have enough to live on is not merely a matter of kindness and common decency, but is crucial to ensure stability and national unity. ↩

The origins of theft are told at DN 27:19.1. The myth recounted here overlaps, with points of both similarity and difference. ↩

The king uses the same procedure as the Buddha. When presented with an alleged wrongdoer, the first thing is to ask them whether they did it. ↩

Simply providing money is not enough, nor is simply expecting that people can just work for what they want. They need something to get started, together with the support and opportunity to build a life for themselves. ↩

Sadly, bad faith actors take advantage of kindness. ↩

While the king’s concern is legitimate, his overreaction escalates the problems. ↩

The violence of the state leads to an armed and violent citizenry. ↩

Today we can see that, even among developed nations, a degraded and violent culture leads to declining lifespans. ↩

Paresaṁ dāresu: both “others” and “wives” are in plural, so polygyny is assumed. Compare parassa dāresu (“the wives of another”) at SN 55.7:6.3. Note the significance granted to beauty in influencing human society. ↩

At this point, the three factors of wrong action—killing, stealing, and sexual misconduct—are present, as are the four factors of wrong speech—lying, backbiting, harsh speech, and nonsensical speech. ↩

This completes the three factors of unskillful thought: desire, ill will, and wrong views (which are a strong form of delusion). Here wrong view probably means moral nihilism. ↩

These three terms recur in a similar context at AN 3.56:2.1. The commentaries to the two passages give quite different explanations. | “Illicit desire” (adhammarāgo) probably refers to any form of desire that is illegal or transgressive, such as incest, rape, or pedophilia. | “Immoral greed” (visamalobho) implies excess and imbalance. Both are, however, explained in the commentary to AN 3.56:2.1 as desire for the belongings of others. | Micchādhammo is hard to pin down. The commentary here explains it as “men with men and women with women”, but this must be rejected as there is no hint anywhere in early Pali (or elsewhere in early Indian culture) that same sex relations were considered immoral; this is a peculiarity of Abrahamic religions. The commentary to AN 3.56:2.1 explains it as “indulgence in what is reckoned an inappropriate basis” (avatthupaṭisevanasaṅkhātena). This implies intercourse with one of the women mentioned at MN 41:8.4, which includes those who are “protected by principle” (dhammarakkhitā). This sense of dhamma is explained at Bu Ss 5:4.2.16 as “religion”. Here I think the sense is similar: customs or beliefs that legitimize immorality. ↩

This brings us to the Buddha’s present. ↩

Here the Buddha paints a devastating picture of societal collapse. Life expectancy as low as thirty years has been recorded in some countries in the 20th century. ↩

The age of onset of puberty has been dropping globally over the past century, with isolated cases as young as five. ↩

“Finger millet” (kudrūsaka; Pahari kodra, Garhwal koda) is a robust secondary grain in Asia and Africa, growing in places rice cannot. Due to its resilience in the face of global heating, 2023 was declared the International Year of Millets by the UN. ↩

The Buddha’s father gave this luxury food to servants and staff (AN 3.39:2.3). ↩

The narrative above traced the gradual disappearance of these ten factors. | Atibyādippissanti is a unique term. At AN 7.66:9.2 a sign of the end of days is the “erupting” (ādippanti) of volcanoes, suggesting “explode” for the intensive form here. ↩

“Skillful” is kusala, otherwise translated as “good” or “wholesome”. ↩

At AN 2.9 = Iti 42 the world is protected from this by conscience and prudence. ↩

For sambheda in the sense of “dissolving, leaking”, see DN 3:1.15.11, AN 5.103:6.4, AN 10.45:4.1. The commentary here says “mixedness, breaking of boundaries”. ↩

“Interregnum of swords” is satthantarakappo. Seven days seems optimistic. ↩

Dehumanization of the other is an essential precursor to genocide. ↩

“Let us neither kill nor be killed” (mā ca mayaṁ kañci, mā ca amhe koci) is an idiomatic phrase, the Golden Rule framed as a negative: “Let us not do unto others nor let others do unto us.” It is explained by the commentary as, “Let us not take even a single person’s life or let them take ours”. ↩

Sabhāgāyissanti = sabhāga + āyissanti = “will come together”. | Samassāsissanti = sama + sāsati = “cry in one voice”. The latter term is absent from some manuscripts. ↩

Diṭṭhā is Sanskrit diṣṭyā, “fantastic, how fortunate”, per DN 16:2.24.5 and Ja 81:1.4. | Sattā is nominative singular for sattar (“enemy”), not plural of satta (“being”), which disagrees with both verb and vocative in number. ↩

The first precept, and the first of the ten ways of skillful action. The Buddhist ethical principles are not just a part of Buddhist teaching, they are essential for the healthy functioning of human society. ↩

In the legendary past, too, only these three afflictions prevailed (Snp 2.7:29.1). ↩

Ketumatī means “adorned with flags”. ↩

Saṅkha is “conch shell”. ↩

This is the only sutta appearance of the future Buddha Metteyya (Sanskrit Maitreya, meaning “one full of love”). He became a prominent figure in later Buddhism. ↩

Throughout, the Buddha is concerned to emphasize that the future Buddha will offer no more or less than his own teaching and practice. He wanted people to practice now, not to establish a cult of a future savior. ↩

The maximum number of monastics cited in the suttas is 1250 at a single gathering. ↩

This event is found in Bhaddaji’s verses at Thag 2.22, expanded to a full story at Ja 264. The commentary explains yūpa as “palace”, but Bhaddaji’s verses clearly depict a sacrificial post, to which the animal would be tied for slaughter. Such posts are connected with the horse sacrifice, which establishes imperial power. This is but one aspect of the wheel-turning monarch to draw on imagery from the horse sacrifice. Here, of course, no horses are killed. ↩

Ajjhāvasati in this sutta means “reign” not “dwell” (DN 26:2.5). ↩

This sutta is the closest we come to a Buddhist myth of origins. It draws on features of Vedic mythology, while giving its own spin. Related stories may be found in DN 26 and Snp 2.7. The Buddha describes a natural process of evolution that requires no metaphysical intervention, yet differs strikingly from Darwinian evolution in prioritizing the role of desire over selection. ↩

After the Jetavana, this was the best-known monastery in Sāvatthī. It was offered by the lady Visākhā, known as Migāra’s mother. ↩

We met Vāseṭṭha and Bhāradvāja as the students of Pokkharasāti and Tārukkha respectively in DN 13, at the end of which they went for refuge. Some time later they must have asked for ordination. The commentary says that probation (paravasati) was required, not because they had previously gone forth in other sects (as the naked ascetic Kassapa at DN 8:24.1 or the wanderer Subhadda at DN 16:5.29.1), nor because they had committed an offense, but because they were not yet the required twenty years of age. ↩

Here as in DN 13 Vāseṭṭha takes the lead. ↩

This verse is also at MN 84:9.19 and MN 93:5.4. | For “best class” (seṭṭho vaṇṇo) see varṇaśreṣṭhaḥ at Mahābhārata 1.24.4c. ↩

Mahābhārata 12.181.5 says that brahmins are the white class, aristocrats red, peasants yellow, and menials black. Underlying this is an assumption of the superiority of the fair-skinned northerners of Indo-Aryan descent over the dark-skinned natives (see DN 3:1.10.3). ↩

I cannot trace this statement to Brahmanical texts, and indeed they have a strong tendency to push back against the idea that only brahmins can find purity. ↩

An allusion to the famous Puruṣasūkta (Rig Veda 10.90.12): “His (the cosmic Man’s) mouth became the brahmin, his arms became the ruler (rājanya, an alternate name for the khattiyas), his thighs became the peasant (vaiśya); the menial (sūdra) was born from his feet.” This belongs to the latest portion of the Rig Veda, and probably represents a time when the system of four castes was established in the late Vedic period, some centuries before the Buddha. Apart from this, the Rig Veda hardly mentions any of these as castes, let alone all four together. ↩

The Buddha gives a rationalist critique of Vedic myth (see also MN 93:5.9), the fairness of which is not easy to assess. Within the Brahmanical world, especially the progressive Kosalan brahmins to whom Vāseṭṭha and Bhāradvāja belonged, there had been a shift toward a more nuanced symbolic understanding of such claims. Yet the subtle distinctions of the philosophers rarely influence the more straightforward beliefs of the common practitioner. ↩

“Dark” (kaṇha) and “bright” (or “light”, sukka) are redefined in ethical not racial terms. ↩

This verse is also at MN 84:4.5 and MN 93:5.4. | For “best class” (seṭṭho vaṇṇo) see varṇaśreṣṭhaḥ at Mahābhārata 1.24.4c. ↩

Mahābhārata 12.181.5 says that brahmins are the white class, aristocrats red, peasants yellow, and menials black. Underlying this is an assumption of the superiority of the fair-skinned northerners of Indo-Aryan descent over the dark-skinned natives (see DN 3:1.10.3). ↩

I cannot trace this statement to Brahmanical texts, and indeed they have a strong tendency to push back against the idea that only brahmins can find purity. ↩

An allusion to the famous Puruṣasūkta (Rig Veda 10.90.12): “His (the cosmic Man’s) mouth became the brahmin, his arms became the ruler (rājanya, an alternate name for the khattiyas), his thighs became the peasant (vaiśya); the menial (sūdra) was born from his feet.” This belongs to the latest portion of the Rig Veda, and probably represents a time when the system of four castes was established in the late Vedic period, some centuries before the Buddha. Apart from this, the Rig Veda hardly mentions any of these as castes, let alone all four together. | “Bosom” (orasa) indicates a rightful heir; see DN 27:9.4 below for more details. | “Born of his mouth” indicates the special role brahmins take in reciting the Vedas; they are the vehicle for God’s word in the world. ↩

Vedic theory claimed that the caste system was part of the order of nature (dhamma) established by Brahmā, and hence to follow the obligations of caste was a duty (also dhamma). The Buddha posited a higher “principle” (dhamma) beyond caste. The English word “principle” carries the senses of a fundamental law; a code of conduct; a devotion to right living; a source; and an underlying faculty, all of which are aspects of dhamma in this passage. Given the nuances of this Sutta, much of it in a non-Buddhist context, I use “principle” throughout rather than my normal “teaching”. ↩

A great king such as Pasenadi ruled his central realm, while outlying districts pledged allegiance to him, enjoying royal protection while ceding some sovereignty. It is the same relationship described for the kingdoms subsumed under the Wheel-Turning Monarch (eg. DN 17:1.9.5). The Buddha described his people as natives among the Kosalans at Snp 3.1:18.4. ↩

The Mahāsaṅgīti reading na naṁ yields a better sense than the PTS nanu, which would make this a question. ↩

Vāseṭṭha was said to be a high family, while Bhāradvāja was low (Bu Pc 2:2.1.18). ↩

The Buddha adapts the Brahmanical passage (also at Iti 100:2.2.). | “Bosom” is orasa, signifying a natural heir to a legitimately married couple (Manusmṛti 9.159, Skandapurāṇa 223.5, Kauṭilya’s Arthaśāstra 3.7). While putta can mean “son” or “child”, in this case the gendered sense is required, since in Brahmanical context the concept is intended to explain how the male child takes precedence in inheritance (Manusmṛti 9.134). Thus the Buddha has both “bosom sons” (Thag 2.27:2.4, Thag 21.1:71.4) and “bosom daughters” (Thig 3.3:2.3, Thig 13.4:25.2). ↩

“The embodiment of principle” is dhammakāya. This is a term of unique occurrence in the suttas, which was seized on in later days to posit a metaphysical theory of a quasi-eternal Buddha. In the suttas, it means that he, having practiced the Dhamma to its fullest, embodies the qualities of the Dhamma to the highest degree. ↩

Here begins the story of origins. The Buddha begins his creation myth with the end of the world. For this passage, compare DN 1:2.2.1. ↩

In the Brahmajālasutta, beings pass from one Brahmā realm to another, but when they come to this world it is as a human. Here we have a different perspective, where beings apparently still like the Brahmā gods exist in the physical realm. ↩

The role of food is critical throughout this narrative. Food is a fundamental sustenance on which all creatures must rely, and the nature of the food reflects the type of creature that eats it. Taittirīya Upaniṣad 2.5.1 says the highest form of self is made of bliss (ātmā ānandamaya). ↩

Creation myths often begin with a dark, formless world of water, and describe the emergence of divisions and structures of the world. They do not differentiate the physical, biological, ecological, or social, as such distinctions came later. | Aitareya Upaniṣad 1.3.3 says the Divinity “brooded over the waters” and created food. ↩

Throughout, the discourse has a special interest in tracing the origins of language and how different usages came about. Here the term “beings” is presented as a natural choice: they are “beings” because they are alive. Later, words are selected to convey a certain political or moral stance. ↩

The reading and sense of samatani is obscure. I think it is connected with santānaka in the next line, in the sense of “networks” or tendrils appearing in the water as it curdles. The Sanskrit at SF 277 and Mūlasarvāstvāda Vinaya 17 has saṁmūrcchitaḥ saṁtanoti (“curdled tendrils”). | Rasapathavī (“earth’s nectar”) is also obscure. We would expect pathavīrasa (cp. phalarasa “fruit juice”, etc.), which is indeed found at SN 5.9:5.3 in the sense “nutriments in soil”. Since this reading also appears here in the Sanskrit sources, I assume it is the correct sense. For another example of a tappurisa compound with reversed order, see DN 4:6.46. ↩

Khuddā (literally “small one”) is said to be a species of small bee, also known in Sanskrit as kṣudrā. The “dwarf bee” (apis florea) fits the bill, as it is a small wild honeybee found in India. ↩

Ghee and honey were among the finest offerings to the gods. The soma was often described as “honeyed”. Our text is suggesting that the Vedic sacrifices led to the corruption of divinity. ↩

For acchadesi read assādesi (“enjoyed”) after Mu Kd 17’s āsvādayati. The commentary explains acchadesi as “becomes suffused”, so if it is a misreading it is an old one. ↩

At DN 26:17.2 it is the ugly ones who are at fault for jealousy. ↩

This is another veiled critique of the Vedic tradition. In DN 13:13.1 the Buddha told Vāseṭṭha and Bhāradvāja the Vedas were recited by people who did not understand them. This problem was well understood within the tradition of the Brāhmaṇas and Upaniṣads, which constantly emphasized that they are effective for “one who knows this” (ya evam veda). ↩

“Fungus” is pappaṭaka (Sanskrit parpaṭaka). At Bu Pj 1:2.2.5, Moggallāna suggests that, to alleviate famine, the monks might eat the pappaṭakojaṁ (“fungus-nutrition”) under the earth. Given that it is compared to a mushroom, I think it is the fungal mycelia of a mycorrhizal network. Such fungi spread like tendrils underground, sometimes appearing above the surface, sharing nutrients and information between organisms. ↩

Readings and meaning of padālatā are uncertain. It has usually been understood that the second element is latā (“creeper”). But this leaves padā unexplained, and the commentary’s gloss of bhaddālatā is unconvincing. It also leaves unexplained the connection with kalambukā. This is probably the fruit of the kadam tree—fleshy, yellow-orange capsules with about 8000 seeds that split apart when ripe. I think padālatā is related to padālana in the sense of “bursting”: a seed pod that splits open like a fig or pomegranate. ↩

The commentary to Bu Pj 1:10.6.1 explains “male characteristics” as “beard and whiskers, etc.” (massudāṭhikādi), so this is not just genitals but also secondary sex characteristics. ↩

Pali seṭṭhi is explained by the commentary as “ash” (chārikā), although this sense does not seem to be attested anywhere else. Mahāvastu has leṣṭu while Mu Kd 17 has loṣṭa, both explained as “clod”. Given that it is easier to throw a clod than ash, I think these probably convey the correct sense. ↩

Nassa could mean “die!” or “get lost”. I take the softer meaning, as killing has not yet appeared among these beings. | This behavior looks much like scapegoating rituals, where certain members of the community are deemed to bear the sins of all and are sacrificed to erase the sin. Often the victim was expelled from the community, temporarily or permanently. ↩

Mob shaming over perceived sexual transgression is the most primitive form of moralizing. ↩

“Carrying off” (nibbuyhamānā) like being swept away by a river. Mu Kd 17 says they throw powder, scent, garlands, and nets, while wishing the bride happiness and well-being. ↩

“Unprincipled” is adhamma. In the past the lovers were spurned, now they are celebrated in marriage. ↩

The sight of others having sex provokes strong reactions of arousal, jealousy, and disgust, often leading to violence. A culture of sexual modesty regulates these emotions, promoting the growth of larger societal structures. ↩

Human society evolves first from greed, second from sexual desire, and third from laziness. The effort to avoid manual labor drives cultural and technological innovation. ↩

Humans are focused on short term comforts and ignore long term consequences. ↩

The wild grasses used as grains evolve in adaptation to human needs. ↩

The beings tell their story within the story. The oldest myths, such as the Vedas or Gilgamesh, speak of myths that were already ancient for them. And the oldest story of all is the Fall: the death of God, the recession of divinity, how things were better in the old days. The story is a reckoning with the consequences of their actions, yet it is not sufficient for them to change course. ↩

Scarcity has arisen because of greed, giving rise to agriculture and land ownership. Up until now, the changes have been driven by individual choice, whereas now they are starting to make agreements among themselves, hoping to mitigate the irresponsibility of individuals. ↩

With ownership and inequality come theft. ↩

It turns out that moral scolding does not deter wrongdoers. ↩

The mob violence escalates. ↩

All a direct consequence of thoughtless greed and inequality. ↩

“Accuse” is khīyeyya. Here the beings are taking charge of their social evolution, deciding among themselves how to manage their society. They are active agents in their own story, not merely passive subjects of evolution. And the primary decision they make is to form a democracy by election (sammata). Doing so, they create a two-class system: rulers and subjects. ↩

The origin of upper class, white-collar workers who do not have to till the soil. Taxes are not coerced, but voluntarily offered in recognition of services rendered. ↩

The emphasis on appearance reflects a wider acknowledgement of the potency of beauty in shaping human conduct. The Buddha rejected the notion that beauty indicates worth (eg. SN 21.6), yet was himself regarded as especially beautiful. Unfair it may be, but beautiful people are listened to. ↩

The ehi formula echoes the original ordination method (Kd 1:6.32.3). ↩

Note that “popularly elected” (mahāsammata) is not a name but a term describing their position. The passage suggests that the prefix mahā does not mean that the elected one is “great”, but that they were elected by the “populace” (mahājana). | “Applied to them” (upanibbattaṁ) is unique. The Sanskrit texts have saṁjñodapādi, “arisen by agreement”. It is distinct from DN 27:11.2 above, where beings “come to be called” beings (saṅkhyaṁ gacchanti). Clearly it cannot mean the first word that appeared. I take it to mean this was a specialized term invented and applied just for them. The commentary says, na kevalaṁ akkharameva, “not just a universal term”. ↩

“Aristocrat” (khattiya; Sanskrit kṣatriya) is related to khatta (“authority”, “power”; in eg. Rig Veda 8.25.8 it is an adjective, “powerful”), hence “ruling class”. The sutta, however, relates it to khetta, “field”. The two senses possibly stem from the same root kṣi in the sense “owner”, “master” with the “field” being the dominion owned by the chief. In Pali suttas, the primary connotation of the khattiya was of an aristocratic land-owning class, so the connection with “field” is apt. Khattiyas are often said to be a “warrior” caste, but that is not a primary association in the suttas. They are rarely depicted as having anything to do with the military, which had become professionalized by the time of the Buddha. Nonetheless, at MN 96:10.7 a khattiya’s wealth is said to be the bow and arrow. At SN 3.24, the Buddha argues that someone from any caste could be as proficient a warrior as someone from the khattiya class. ↩

Modern linguists trace the Proto-Indo-European root of rāja as *reg in the sense “one who leads people in a straight line”, literally “ruler” or “regulator”. The pun rañjeti (“they please”) is meant to emphasize the obligations that a ruler has for their people. As here, rājā and khattiya can have the same meaning, although commonly a rājā is an actual king or chief, while khattiya is the class from which the rulers come. ↩

Read bāheyyāma. ↩

Bāhenti (“set aside”) sounds a bit like brāhmaṇa. Such puns which don’t quite land are sometimes used to infer a language underlying Pali. | Brāhmaṇa is a Sanskritic form, and the colloquial pronunciation may have been closer to bāhmaṇa. ↩

The phrase jhāyanti vītaṅgārā vītadhūmā pannamusalā works at a double level. Jhāyanti is to “meditate” but also is the light of a lamp. Vītaṅgārā vītadhūmā means “without coals and smoke”, implying that they do not light cooking fires; but as meditation it means their minds are free of corruptions. Pannamusalā is “with shovel put down”, i.e. they do not dig the soil (thus killing the creatures there). Not cooking or digging are also precepts for Buddhist and Jain mendicants. ↩

“Meditator” is jhāyaka. ↩

At DN 3:2.3.11 the brahmins come down from the forest and set up shrines in the town. Chāndogya Upaniṣad 5.10.1–5 compares the forest contemplatives destined for the Brahmā realm with the ritualists who are reborn on the moon before returning to earth. | The “texts” (ganthe) were the Vedas. ↩

Ajjhāyaka is from ajjhāyati (“to recite”), but here it is punned as the negative of jhāyaka (“meditator”). ↩

“Various” is visu, which loosely echoes vessa (“peasant”). The Sanskrit form is vaiśya, from viś, to “stay” or “settle” on the land. They were probably originally peasants who over time transitioned into more diverse livelihoods. In MN 96:10.10 they are said to engage in cattle-rearing and agriculture, and over time trade was added to that. ↩

Sudda (“menial”) rhymes with ludda (“hunter”) and khudda (“minor”). In MN 96:10.14 their wealth is said to come from the “scythe and flail”, i.e. seasonal manual labor such as threshing grain (SN 35.248:1.2). At MN 96:16.4, bamboo-workers, chariot-makers, and waste-collectors are cited as other low-class jobs. They may have originated as a distinct branch of Aryan peoples who were assimilated into Vedic culture (Ram Sharan Sharma, Śudras in Ancient India, 37). ↩

“Vocation” is dhamma, which is rarely used in the suttas in this sense; normally it is universal. ↩

The Buddha invokes Brahmā to support his contention that his own caste, the khattiyas, were superior, a sequence supported by Pañcaviṁśa Brāhmaṇa 13.4.7. Ultimately, however, the Buddha rejected the notion that caste tells us anything intrinsic about the worth of people. ↩

This discourse is expanded from the events of DN 16:1.16.1. ↩

Here the additional material begins. While they are all said to be teachings of the Buddha, some sections cannot be traced in the Pali Canon as it stands today. Perhaps Sāriputta was demonstrating his talent for creative rephrasing and synthesis. ↩

Perhaps a reference to his enlightenment experience in MN 74. | This passage plays on the different senses of dhamma as linguistic “teaching” and observable “principle”. ↩

Also at DN 16:3.50.5, etc. ↩

The primary source is the SN 35, the Linked Discourses on the Six Sense Fields. ↩

The Bodhisatta is said elsewhere to be conceived in awareness (eg. DN 16:3.15.1), but this systematic analysis is found only here and at DN 33:1.11.176. It seems like an abrupt shift from central Dhamma topics. ↩

Called “demonstrations of revealing” (ādesanāpāṭihāriya) at AN 3.60:9.1. ↩

Meditation is described in this way only in MN 136:9.1 and DN 1:1.31.1 where, as here, it is pursued by an “ascetic or brahmin”, who in those cases is not Buddhist. Here, however, it sounds like Sāriputta is talking about a Buddhist practice. The asubha contemplation of the parts of the body is described in several places in the canon (eg. DN 22:5.1), but never exactly like this. ↩

The remaining practices are unique to this passage. This is perhaps related to the contemplation of death, as it seems to imply looking at another person’s body rather than one’s own. ↩

This is a unique description of the process of rebirth. Consciousness is a “stream” in that it flows and moves, ever-changing, and is not a static self-same entity. To be “established” (patiṭṭhita) is to be attached because of craving. | The phrase “consistent on both sides” (ubhayato abbocchinnaṁ) is unique. Ubhayato is used of “both ends” of a pole Ja 533:37.4. I think the sense is that one’s consciousness is consistent with regards to this world and the next. If one is attached to this world, one will be attached to the next, and vice versa in the next section. ↩

As at AN 7.14:1.3. ↩

Normally we would expect the four kinds of right striving here. This is the only place the seven awakening factors are described in this way. ↩

As at AN 4.166. ↩

These descriptions are unique. | Vebhūtiya is also at (DN 30:2.21.2, where the context shows it is a synonym for pesuṇiya. See too Snp 1.9:6.4, Snp 3.10:16.1. ↩

The Mahāsaṅgīti omits a heading for this section. ↩

The sequence from “memory” (satimā) to “retention” (dhitimā) is related to the good qualities of Ānanda (AN 1.220:1.1), and pertain to textual fluency. Satimā here is “memory”, not “mindfulness”, which is sato at the end. ↩

We don’t find this exact passage elsewhere, but it is similar to AN 10.46. When the Buddha speaks of future consequences it is conditional. He is not a fortune-teller, but he understands the results of the practice. ↩

Paccattaṁ yonisomanasikārā occurs at SN 46.8:2.1 and MN 50:3.1, where it means “investigate inside oneself”. Here it is applied to another. ↩

Another unique passage, similar to MN 68:12.4. ↩

Compare the four kinds of eternalism at DN 1:3.1.1. The theories based on rationality are omitted. ↩

According to the PTS edition, the Sinhala-script manuscripts read na jānāmi (“don’t know”) against the Mahāsaṅgīti jānāmi. | The means of knowledge given here is solely based on the recollection of past lives, which agrees with the Brahmajālasutta that these are views based on the past. It seems the sectarian here is admitting the limits of their experiential knowledge, but nonetheless inferring eternalism in both past and future. ↩

Some manuscripts read “twenty” here. ↩

“Accompanied by defilements and attachments” (sāsavā saupadhikā) is unique, but compare sāsavā puññabhāgiyā upadhivepakkā at MN 117:6.3 and sāsavaṁ upādāniyaṁ at SN 22.48:2.2. ↩

Also at MN 152:11–15.3, AN 5.144:2.2, SN 52.1:4.2, SN 46.54:12.5, SN 54.8:7.1. ↩

From the first sermon at SN 56.11:2.3. ↩

Here the jhānas stand in the place of the path as a whole. In DN 29:24.5 the Buddha uses a similar framing. ↩

Here abhi- in abbhanujānāti conveys the sense “grant in respect of one”. ↩

Here Sāriputta is quoting the Buddha, yet this phrase is not found in the Pali Canon. ↩

At MN 115:14.1. ↩

There are several individuals called Udāyī. ↩

The Vedhaññās are not mentioned elsewhere; their name means “Marksmen”. ↩

When this event is mentioned at MN 104:2.1, the Buddha is also in the Sakyan lands, but near the village of Sāma. Both texts tell the story of Cunda conveying the news via Ānanda at Sāma, which was presumably near the Vedhaññā’s mango grove. It does seem strange that two distinct discourses are recorded from the same prompt, but then, why shouldn’t the Buddha give more than one teaching on such an important topic? At DN 33:1.6.1 the Buddha is at Pāvā in the Mallian lands, and the discourse is spoken by Sāriputta there. Given the evident lateness of DN 33, this is a less convincing framework. A parallel to MN 104 (MA 196 at T i 752c12) says he was in the Vajjian lands at the time; both Sakya and Vajji border on Mallā. Jain tradition holds Mahāvīra died after the Buddha, and it was at a different Pāvā in Magadha near Nāḷandā, perhaps the place known in Pali as Pāvārika’s mango grove (DN 11:1.2). The earliest Jain source for Mahāvīra’s death, the Kalpasutra, is, however, much later than the Buddhist sources, and does not say where Pāvā is. But it does say the events were commemorated by the rulers of Kāsī and Kosala, and the Mallians and the Licchavīs. The absence of Magadha and the presence of Malla sit better with the location of Pāvā in Malla rather than Magadha. ↩

While this description of the Jains might seem like sheer sectarian calumny, it is a fact that the Jain tradition is split into two sects, the “sky-clad” Digambara, whose male ascetics went naked, and the “white-clad” Śvetāmbara who wear an unstitched cloth. Jain tradition holds that the split occurred about a century later, in the reign of Candragupta Maurya. ↩

A slight on the movement whose signature virtue was non-violence. ↩

“With broken monument” (bhinnathupe) is used only in this context. When a great teacher or leader died, a “monument” was built to keep their memory alive. The breaking of a monument—whether physical or symbolic—was, in a way, truly killing them. ↩

Cunda took the time to complete his rains residence before conveying the news, reminding us of the speed with which news traveled in those days—slowly. | Apart from the events described here, we hear of Sāma only once (AN 6.21). The topic there is the decline of the Saṅgha, hinting at a connection with these events. ↩

This harsh critique is repeated at DN 33:1.7.4, but not at MN 104:5.1, where the Buddha’s response focuses on his own community. ↩

Normally we find vokkamma (“having turned away”) in the sense of straying from the Dhamma. But this passage shows the phrase is, in itself, neutral, as it is good to turn from a bad teaching. ↩

The Dhamma is primary, not the teacher. This is applied to Buddhism as well; for example, a student is expected to help a mentor who is falling away from Dhamma (Kd 1:25.20.1). ↩

Compare AN 1.320. ↩

“Collected sayings” is saṅgāhapada, a unique reference to a formal collection of scripture. Here, the sense seems to be that the process of gathering and organizing teachings is incomplete. Therefore I take the negative na to be distributed separately among the clauses. ↩

Compare DN 16:3.8.4ff. ↩

One of the Brahmanical sages under whom the Bodhisatta practiced before awakening (MN 26:16.1). Another of his enigmatic sayings is found at SN 35.103:1.2. When the Bodhisatta began his study, he first learned to recite the scriptures, and in these two passages we find examples of what those scriptures were. ↩

Sharp razors were known even in Vedic times (Rig Veda 8.4.16). ↩

This is a distorted reference to Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.4.7. There, the Self is said to be hidden in a body like a razor in its case. People do not see it (taṁ na paśyanti), for they only see the partial and incomplete functions of the Self, such as breathing, speaking, and so on. Seeing only the aspects, they do not see that each aspect is an expression of the one whole. This confirms that Uddaka was a Brahmanical teacher who was familiar with this passage. Similar phrases, but without the razor simile, are found at Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.3.23 and Chāndogya Upaniṣad 6.12.1. ↩

“Recite in concert” is saṅgīti. Reciting together affirms the mutual teaching and ensures the correctness of the text. The implication is that the entire Buddhist community participates, but in the saṅgīti after the Buddha’s death there were only monks. ↩

Here the Buddha outlines the topics to be recited, which are the main chapters of the Saṁyutta Nikāya. ↩

The “meaning” is the attha. Here we see the source of the atthakathā, which we translate as “commentaries”, but which are literally “discussions on the meaning”. Such discussions are undertaken through a civil and polite inquiry. ↩

Meaning and phrasing are interdependent, so care must be taken with both. Often it happens that when the phrasing slips, a new and unwarranted meaning is imputed. ↩

These are the four basic requisites for monastics, said to overcome defilements by usage (AN 6.58:4.1, MN 2:13.1). ↩

This repurposes the phrase used right at the beginning of the Buddha’s first teaching, the Dhammacakkappavattasutta (SN 56.11:2.3). There he was persuading hard-bitten ascetics that he did not indulge in sensual pleasures. While the affiliation of those five ascetics is not stated explicitly, clearly their practices were similar to the Jains. And given the context, no doubt the Buddha has the Jains in mind here. ↩

Again echoing the first sermon (SN 56.11:3.1), here the Buddha places the jhānas where, in the Dhammacakkappavattasutta, he put the middle way. He uses a similar strategy at DN 28:19.2. ↩

Some meditation teachers warn of the supposed dangers of becoming attached to the pleasure of meditation. The Buddha’s view was that the pleasure of meditation arises from letting go and leads to Nibbāna. ↩

At AN 8.19:3.1 the ocean is said to be ṭhitadhammo, “naturally stable”. Both places are glossed as ṭhitasabhāvā. It seems this is in reference to the fact that the Buddhist Vinaya is gentle and flexible. The Buddha was ready to alter and adjust details when circumstances required, yet the fundamental principles hold firm. ↩

As at AN 9.7:3.3, etc. ↩

It is possible to remember the past, but knowledge of the future is restricted to inferences in specific contexts and cannot be predicted in general. ↩

The Buddha claims no gift of prophecy, unlike some other sages, but he knows that which matters. ↩

See AN 4.23 and Iti 112. ↩

Here these questions follow on from the Buddha’s acknowledgment of epistemological limitations. Not everything can be known, and if it is, it is not always useful to speak of it. ↩

In the Brahmajālasutta (DN 1). ↩

The idea “made by oneself” (sayaṅkata) assumes a metaphysical “self” which creates “the self and the cosmos”. This implies the Vedic creation doctrine, whereby Prajāpati created the cosmos and all things in it from himself by an act of self-sacrifice. Thus the sacrificer offers to Prajāpati as the sun with the words, “You are self-made” (svāṁkṛta, Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 4.1.1.22, 4.1.2.21). For more details on this teaching, see SN 12.17 and notes there. ↩

The Brahmajālasutta describes the path to the end of these views in terms of understanding dependent origination through contemplation of contact in the six senses (DN 1:3.71.12). The Buddhist path is integrated, so one part always implies the whole. ↩

The marks of the “five great men” are discussed in the later astrological text, Bṛhatsaṁhitā 69. ↩

This is one of the latest suttas in the Pali Nikāyas. Typically this topic only comes up in relation to the Buddha’s fulfillment of Brahmanical prophecies. Here it is developed with a series of ornate verses, none of which have parallels. Nonetheless, it is worth noting that nowhere in the extensive discussions of the Buddha’s past good deeds is there any mention of the later concepts of the pāramīs (“perfections”) or the Bodhisatta path. ↩

The marks are elsewhere listed in DN 14:1.32.7 and MN 91:9.1. I discuss the translation of the marks in my comments to DN 14. ↩

The later astrological texts such as the Gārgīyajyotiṣa and Bṛhatsaṁhitā that discuss similar marks are more concerned with how they indicate character and destiny than their moral causes. ↩

The key terms here are daḷha (“firm”) and avatthita (“persistently”), which result in his firm stance. ↩

The commentary explain akhilamanimittamakaṇṭakaṁ as “free of bandits” (niccoraṁ). Bandits are also regarded as “pests” (abbuda, literally “tumor” or “cancer”) at SN 1.77:3.4. ↩

K.R. Norman’s series of five articles on The Metres of the Lakkhaṇa-suttanta discusses the verses in detail, and my translation is indebted to him. He notes that the 20 verse passages employ no less than seven distinct metres, all of them either new or updated styles. Such a display of poetic virtuosity is rare in the Pali canon. ↩

The commentary confirms the Mahāsaṅgīti reading khambhana (“obstacle”) here rather than PTS gabbha (“womb”). ↩

He “conveyed happiness” (sukhāvaho), like a wheeled cart would convey goods. | Parivāra means “surroundings, accompaniments”, and I follow the commentary, which takes it in the sense of the “trimmings” accompanying the food. Given, however, that the kammic result is a large parivāra (“following”), it might mean that he gave not just physical things, but was generous with his followers also, engaging them in such beneficial tasks. ↩

This refers to the late legend of the soothsayers seeing the baby Siddhattha, and as such kumāra should be taken as “prince”. ↩

Giving up killing results in long life. This seems to be applied by metaphor to having these long and elegant body parts. ↩

Whereas in the phrase brahmujugatto, brahm- means “extended, tall”, here brahmāva means “like Brahmā”, either as a play on words or by mistaken etymology. ↩

This verse spoken by the soothsayers. ↩

He receives bodily fullness as a result of giving food. ↩

Nandana, the celestial garden in the realm of the Thirty-Three. ↩

“Tender” because he treated people tenderly; “serried” because his fingers and toes are kept gracefully together, not splayed and separated. ↩

“Inclusive and well-managed” renders saṅgahita. It means “included”, as in those people who, due to the kindly actions, feel that they belong. For the sense “well-managed” see AN 8.49:2.3. Because of acting kindly and inclusively, people are well-disposed and work well together. ↩

Even though the community is geographically dispersed, it is still coherent. ↩

Perhaps the uprightness of these marks relates to his speech being beneficial, leading upwards. ↩

It seems that his “swift” teaching techniques evoke the antelope. ↩

Read anomanikkamo. ↩

Asking questions leads to wisdom, and the mind of wisdom does not get attached. ↩

Giving fine coverings leads to fine skin. Less obviously, anger is said to lead to discoloring and ugliness. ↩

For this positive sense of adhiṭṭhahi compare AN 6.52:8.2 and MN 140:11.1. ↩

There’s a play on abhivissaji (“gave away”) and abhivassa (“pouring rain”). ↩

Kanaka, one of the many Indic words for gold, is from the same Proto-Indo European root as the English word “honey”. ↩

Here mokkha = pāmokkha (“chief, best”). ↩

The penis is the generative organ and hence part-creator of family. Being covered suggests that his sexuality was moderated and contained. His role was more than having children, it was building family. ↩

The banyan tree is not just proportioned, it offers shelter to many creatures. Touching the knees indicates connecting with the manyfolk, who at AN 5.196:3.1 are likened to caterpillars reaching the knees. ↩

This is a rare usage of kara (“doer”) in the sense “hand”. ↩

A khema is a sanctuary where animals flourish in peace, without fear of the hunter. Likewise, the Buddha’s body flourishes and has a fullness to it. He is slim but not skinny. ↩

Decline in dhamma is missing here, but present both above and below in verse. ↩

The “ridged taste buds” are not merely for tasting, but support excellent digestion. Kammically, the rationale is that since he did not kill others, now nothing hurts him when he eats. ↩

Dark colored eyes give the impression of wide pupils and an open gaze, while the eyelashes of cows lend them a tenderness. ↩

Abhiyogino (“soothsayers”) is a unique term, explained by the commentary, “they are dedicated to the lore of marks”. ↩

The commentary says he took the lead in good deeds “unembarrassed, with head held high, his head filled with rapture and joy”. ↩

One hair per pore, because his words of truth have only one meaning. Likewise, the tuft conveys purity and integrity. ↩

The number four connotes “all around, complete, universal”, primarily from the four directions. It is multiplied to eight with the intermediate directions, and ten including above and below. Forty, then, is four times ten, a number of super-inclusiveness or super-universality. The lack of gaps corresponds with the lack of division between his followers. ↩

The commentary explains that those who flap their mouths with nonsensical gossip end up with weak or misshapen jaws. ↩

His teeth are not “crooked” or “stained” by corruption. ↩

Sigālaka only appears in this sutta. His name means “little jackal”. ↩

Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 5.5.1 recommends offerings to Agni in the east, Indra or Soma in the south, the All-gods in the west, Mitra and Varuṇa in the north, and Bṛhaspati in the middle. The quarters themselves are divine, since one can travel them and never reach the end (Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.1.5). Atharva Veda 12.3.7–10 gives a domestic prayer for the quarters; here Yama dwells in the south with the Fathers, while Soma is in the west, and the other directions are not associated with specific deities. Vājasaneyi Saṁhitā 22.24a worships the six directions. Maitrī Upaniṣad 7.1–6 details the spiritual meanings of the six quarters. In Buddhism, the quarters are said to be inhabited by the respective Four Great Kings as per DN 32. ↩

Sigālaka followed blindly without considering the meaning as urged by Chāndogya Upaniṣad 1.3.11. ↩

It is unusual to find “six” directions. Normally it is four, then eight (with intermediate directions), then ten (above and below). Praśna Upaniṣad 1.6 lists the six, then the intermediates. ↩

The Buddha outlines the contents of the discourse to follow. ↩

The teaching is structured to reinforce memorization. Give the number of items (twice), so you will notice if any are missing; list the items; recapitulate the numbers; then recapitulate the items once more in verse. ↩

First we learned what the bad deeds were, now we learn why people do them. ↩

“Drains on wealth” is apāyamukha, literally “openings for departure”. This is emphasized here since Sigālaka wants to be a good son and not squander the family fortune. ↩

The most common phrase in Pali for alcoholic beverages lists three items. Surā is brewed from grains with yeast (Bu Pc 51:2.1.2) Meraya is made from flowers, fruits, or sugars (Bu Pc 51:2.1.4). Madya is apparently a catchall. Together they correspond fairly well with the modern classification of alcoholic drinks as “beer, wine, and liquor”. See also Manu 11.94, Arthaśāstra 2.25, Suśrutasaṁhitā 1.45, Amarakośodghāṭana 3.6. ↩

Now each of the six drains on wealth are expanded and explained. ↩

A similar sentiment is at SN 1.53:1.3. These lines recall the English saying, “A friend in need is a friend indeed.” ↩

Vārunī is said to have been distilled from hogweed with palm sap, “toddy”. ↩

Assume vāruṇī is a truncated instrumental. ↩

Kāhiti is third person singular future of karoti. ↩

The subcommentary explains atthā as dhanā (“riches”). ↩

Having explained the six drains on wealth, the Buddha moves on to the next item in the table of contents. ↩

Parents are in the east because that is where the sun is born. Tutors are to the south (dakkhiṇā) as they are owed an offering (dakkhiṇā). Family is one’s legacy, so they lie with the setting sun in the west. Good friends keep you on the upright way to the north. Servants support you and make your life possible, like the earth below. And spiritual teachers lead you to heaven or transcendence above. ↩

“Protection in every region” (disāsu parittāṇaṁ) refers to when the student has completed their studies and goes off to travel, the teacher does what they can to ensure their safety in other regions. ↩

Marriage is based on mutual care and respect, not on dominance and obedience. ↩

This discourse bears similarities to the Mahāsamayasutta (DN 20). Thematically, that discourse is about the devotion of the deities, whereas this is about protection for the mendicants. | I believe this is only place in whole canon that lists the bhāṇavāra at the start. ↩

Here Kuvera is called Vessavaṇa, which our text below explains as being derived from the name of his city. ↩

“Protection” is rakkhā, which is a synonym of paritta. ↩

For these verses, I lean heavily on the translation by Ānandajoti, The Āṭānāṭiya Discourse. They are commonly recited in Theravada countries today. The recital begins with the seven Buddhas, for which see DN 14. ↩

Aṅgīras was one of the Vedic sages and the Aṅgīrasas are his descendants. They were priestly poets who assisted Indra in freeing the cows from the Vala cave, thus ushering in the dawn. Aṅgīras is regarded as the pravara or revered ancestor of the Gotama clan. Both names are associated with light: aṅgīrasa shares a root and is often synonymous with agni (“fire”), while gotama means “light dispelling dark”. ↩

Here begins a series of verses dedicated to the divinities in each of the four quarters, proceeding in the standard way: east, south, west, north. ↩

This is according to the commentary (taṁ rahadaṁ tattha evaṁ jānanti). ↩

This relates back to the basic problem facing the yakkhas: shame. They know what they do is wrong, but they like it and hence feel shame when hearing the Dhamma. But the Buddha treats them with respect, without shaming or bias, and thus is able to lead them to the good. The commentary implicitly connects this line with DN 30:2.1.2, where the Buddha “examines” (samekkhati) the population for their individual and shared traits. ↩

The south has the shortest and least auspicious description. To the extent that it relates to physical geography, this echoes the perception of northerners at the time that the south of India lay outside the “civilized” realms (āryāvarta). ↩

The description of the west mirrors the east. ↩

The description of the north is by far the most elaborate. | The “land north of Kuru” (uttarakuru) is mentioned in Sanskrit and Greek literature, where it sometimes appears as an actual country and other times as a place of fantasy. Attempts to locate it in a specific region in or beyond the Himalayas have proven inconclusive. ↩

Meru is another place that appears sometimes as a physical mountain and other times purely mystical. As home of the gods (Snp 3.11:4.3), its peak is accessible only by psychic powers (Thig 14.1:19.3, MN 50:30.1). It is the center of the world in Buddhist, Hindu, and Jain cosmologies. Today it is sometimes identified with Mount Kailash. See discussion of Sineru at SN 13.11:1.2. ↩

This agrees with the description at AN 9.21:1.3. ↩

They live in a kinder state of nature, which we selfish humans have lost (DN 27:16.1). ↩

Tuṇḍikīre is explained by the commentary as “firestone”. In the notes to his translation, Walshe suggests a relation with tandoor, which has been found as far back as the Indus Valley Civilization, a millennium before the Buddha. ↩

Cloven and uncloven was an important classification of animals in the Dharmaśāstras. ↩

The commentary says they were mostly carried on the backs of pregnant women(!). But the verb anuyanti indicates, rather, that they were “drawn along after”, which suggests a rickshaw. ↩

The discourse is named after the first of these cities. The name is hard to explain, but all the names in this series have the element nāṭa, which is probably the name of the people. One meaning of nāṭa is “dance”, and one of the unique features of this discourse is that each of the Four Great Kings is said to delight in song and dance. There is a long history of dancing divinities in India, and images of dancers go back as far as the Indus Valley Civilization. If we take nāṭa in the sense “the people of the dance”, kusināṭā would therefore be “dancers of the grass” after the kusa grass essential to the Vedic rites of kingship. Parakusināṭā is the “further dancers of the grass”, and parakusiṭanāṭā is probably a variation on that. Nāṭapuriyā is the “citadel of the dancers”. Each of these associates the people of the dance with the idea of protection or authority, agreeing with the context, where the cities are said to belong to a great king. Thus the prefix āṭā- probably stems from tāṇa (“shelter, refuge”; the same root as paritta), in the sense of the “refuge of the dancers”. ↩

Adopt the reading nāṭapuriyā found in Sinhalese-script manuscripts against the Mahāsaṅgīti’s nāṭasuriyā. ↩

“Abounding in monkeys”. ↩

“Flood of folk”. ↩

Navanavutiya is “the city of the ninety-nine” i.e. three times thirty-three. | Ambara is “sky”. ↩

Also encountered at DN 17:1.3.8 and DN 16:5.18.5. Alakā is the capital of Kuvera in Sanskrit sources. ↩

The city Visāṇa is not encountered elsewhere, but it means “horn”, possibly reinforcing the importance of “song and dance”. ↩

The commentary explains “searching” (paccesanto) as investigating the meaning of the teachings. It takes pakāsenti as “explain”: the spirits of the nation explain the teaching to spirits who are gatekeepers, who then explain it to the king. The terms below are the names of these spirits. However, pakāsenti also means “shine”, and the names below seem to be associated with solar or celestial phenomena. I think the phrase is a poetic description of the celestial bodies that shine as they search across the sky. This verse is especially obscure, and any explanation is speculative, but below I offer an analysis under the assumption that the names depict shining celestial bodies. ↩

Resolve tatola as tato + la (= Sanskrit las, to shine or glitter): “one who glitters from afar”, i.e. a star that shines across the distant skies. | Tattala would then have tatta in the sense “heated”, i.e. “one who glitters from heat” (unless it is a misreading from tattha, yielding “one who glitters from there”). | Tatotala is a reduplicated form, “one who glitters from farther”. ↩

Take oja in the sense “lustre”—attested in Sanskrit but not otherwise in Pali—rather than the more familiar “nutritive essence” (MN 36:27.5), yielding “lustrous one”. | Tejasi means “brilliant one” (used of the sun at Praśna Upaniṣad 5.5). | Tatojasi means “one whose lustre shines from afar”. ↩

These are a set of associated solar names. Ariṭṭha and Nemi appear compounded in Sanskrit, Ariṣṭanemi, which evokes the powerful chariot of a conqueror (“indestructible rim”, Rig Veda 1.89.6, 1.180.10, 3.53.17, 10.178.1). It was the name of the 22nd Jain tīrthaṅkara, and in Brahmanical texts of several figures, including a dragon (Mahābhārata 1.59.39a, 1114.62a, etc.) and an Asura king (Bhāgavatapurāṇa 8.6.31, 8.10.10). Along with the divine steed Tārkṣya, he is associated with Garuḍa, and was probably originally an epithet for the unstoppable wheel of the Sun, Sūra. This line, then, while a simple list of four names in Pali, appears to be a fragmented memory of a Vedic conception which might be translated: “King Sun, (the wheel) of indestructible rim”. ↩

Dharaṇī the “bearer” is also a pregnant woman or Mother Earth. ↩

Sāla means “hall” or “sal tree”, but the commentary says it was surrounded by creepers of that name. ↩

Kuḷīrakā appears to be the name of a crab-eating bird (kuḷīra). In honor of my native country, I name it after the kookaburra, which eats crabs and is renowned for its cry. ↩

In Ja 547:426.2 we find koṭṭhā pokkharasātakā, where the koṭṭha is evidently a woodpecker. Satapatta can mean woodpecker or lotus (or crane or peacock), and perhaps there is an association here, the “hundred-leaved [bird] of the lotus pond”. ↩

For these gods, see my comment on DN 13:25.2. Here I will comment on the names not discussed elsewhere, especially in DN 20. ↩

This is presumably Bharadvāja Bārhaspatya, the rishi ancestor of the Bhāradvāja clan, many members of which are encountered in the suttas. It is unusual to find him listed along with the primary Vedic gods. The Bhāradvāja verses are mostly collected in the sixth book of the Rig Veda, where they show a special devotion to the god Pūṣan. See also note on SN 7.1:1.2. ↩

These deities appear nowhere else. Puṇṇaka is “full”, guḷa is “lump”, and karatiya is unclear (“bean-like”?). ↩

The yakkha Sivaka (“blissful, auspicious”) helped Anāthapiṇḍika visit the Buddha (SN 10.8:1.12); he is possibly to be identified with Shiva. | The dragon king Mucalinda sheltered the Buddha after his awakening (Ud 2.1:2.2). ↩

Yugandhara is the tutelary deity of the mountain of that name. ↩

Gopāla is “cowherd”, an epithet of both Krishna and Shiva. | Suppagedha (or supparodha) is obscure. ↩

“Shame”, “conduit” (or “craving”), and “stupidity” seem like odd companions. ↩

A saying by Pañcālacaṇḍa at SN 2.7 is quoted by Udāyī and explained by Ānanda at AN 9.42. He would appear to be the fierce (caṇḍa) protector of the Pañcāla clan, but a Pañcālacanda appears as a brahmin teacher (Aitereya Āraṇyaka 3.1.6, Śāṅkhāyana Āraṇyaka 7.19, Gopatha Brāhmaṇa 1.1.27n). | Āḷavaka is the tutelary deity of Āḷavī (SN 10.12, Snp 1.10). ↩

Pajjuna is Parjanya, the Vedic god of rain, especially the thunderstorm. His daughters appear in SN 1.39 and SN 1.40. | Sumana is “Happyheart”, sumukha is “Fairface”. ↩

Dadhimukha is “Milkface”, and in the Mahābhārata is a name of a dragon. | Maṇi is “gem”. | Māṇivara is “fine gem”, although the commentary takes this as two names. | Dīgha is identified by the commentary with Dīgha Parajana of MN 31:21.1. ↩

Serīsaka means “of sirīsa wood”, perhaps the tutelary deity of a forest. ↩

This discourse picks up from DN 29:17.1, where the Buddha urges that the Saṅgha should gather and recite the Dhamma for the long lasting of the dispensation. There he lists the 37 factors of awakening, a standard early collation of practice-oriented teachings that are primarily collected in the Mahāvagga of the Saṁyutta Nikāya. This discourse is a late one, and appears to be an initial attempt to compile a more thorough list of the Buddha’s teachings. The Sarvāstivāda version of the same discourse formed the basis of one of their seven Abhidhamma books, the Sangītiparyāya. ↩

At AN 10.176 Cunda asks about the purity of the western brahmins; at DN 16:4.13.5 = Ud 8.5 he offers the Buddha’s last meal; at Snp 1.5 he asks about a true ascetic. ↩

The completion of a town hall was celebrated by a talk for the Sakyans SN 35.243:1.2 and MN 53:2.1. Such halls were community meeting places that played a central role in civic society and communal decision-making in democratic republics such as the Mallas and the Sakyans. The Buddha’s participation is a sign of his support for their civic and democratic process. ↩

As at DN 16:5.19.2, the Mallas are called Vāseṭṭhas after the family lineage of their priest (purohita). ↩

The Buddha likewise mentions his bad back and invites another monk to teach in both the other suttas where he is first to teach in a new hall (MN 53:5.3, SN 35.243:3.4), and also on the uposatha at Naḷakapāna (AN 10.67, AN 10.68). These were all occasions when the community was sitting late into the night. ↩

As at DN 29:1.3 and MN 104:2.1, in both of which the Buddha was in the Sakyan lands at this time. There, the news is conveyed to the Buddha by the novice Cunda. Perhaps he was confused with Cunda the smith. ↩

Sāriputta adopts the “Aṅguttara principle” of arranging teachings by number rather than the “Saṁyutta principle” of arrangement by topic. Thus this list of teachings has more in common with the Aṅguttara Nikāya than with the Buddha’s original list of Saṁyutta topics. I note unusual or rare terms, but the references here are meant to be indicative rather than comprehensive. ↩

AN 10.27:10.5, AN 10.28:4.5, Kp 4:1.2. | Compare Bṛhadāranyaka Upaniṣad 5.12.1, “for all these beings are contained in food”, Chāndogya Upaniṣad 1.11.9, “all these beings live when they partake of food”, Taittirīya Upaniṣad 2.2.1, “any creatures who dwell on earth are produced from food, and by food alone they live.” ↩

This phrase is unique, but here saṅkhārā (“conditions”) is a synonym of āhāra (“food, fuel, nutriment”). ↩

The paucity of teachings of “one” reflects the fact that the Aṅguttara Nikāya Ones consists mostly of longer teachings that have been split into atoms to artificially create “ones”. ↩

AN 4.254:3.2. ↩

AN 2.91:1.3, SN 22.80:9.2. ↩

These Vinaya concepts also at AN 2.97:1.3. ↩

AN 2.163:1.3. ↩

AN 2.96:1.3. ↩

MN 115:3.3. ↩

MN 115:3.3. ↩

AN 2.11:1.3. ↩

Samathanimitta at SN 46.2:14.2 and SN 46.51:11.2; paggahanimitta at AN 3.102. ↩

“Knowledge of ending” (khaye ñāṇaṁ) refers to the aggregates; it is discussed at SN 12.23. | “Knowledge of non-arising” (anuppāde ñāṇaṁ) is the knowledge that one will not be born again. ↩

SN 14.13, AN 3.76, AN 3.77. ↩

At AN 4.33:2.2 cessation is the middle, not an extreme. But SN 22.103 has four extremes. ↩

See SN 45.165 and notes for discussion. ↩

The “right way” is the eightfold path, the “wrong way” the opposite (SN 45.21). “Surety in the right way” is mentioned often (eg. AN 5.151), although I normally render it “sure path”. “Surety in the wrong way” seems to be found only in later texts. “Lack of surety” is impermanence. And elsewhere these are not said to be “heaps”. ↩

Despite the explanation, and the prevalence of reading kaṅkhā, the commentary requires the Mahāsaṅgīti reading tama. ↩

AN 7.58. ↩

AN 7.47:12.3. | For dakkhiṇeyyaggi, compare Sanskrit dakṣiṇāgni, a fire sacrifice for ancestors established in a hearth to the south. ↩

Elsewhere found only in Abhidhamma. “Visible and resistant” refers to material phenomena perceivable by the eye. “Invisible and resistant” is a shorthand for material phenomena that are not perceivable by the eye, but which nonetheless impinge on other senses, such as sounds or smells. “Invisible and non-resistant” includes form perceived solely in the mind (Vb 3:49.2). ↩

The last item is elsewhere found only in Abhidhamma texts. A “trainee” is a noble one who has at least entered the path to stream-entry; an “adept” (asekkha) has completed their training; one who is neither is yet to begin. ↩

Only found here. ↩

Iti 95. ↩

The first is unique, the next two from AN 5.170. ↩

These are Abhidhamma categories. ↩

Otherwise found only in Abhidhamma and other late texts. ↩

The “weapon of learning” is at AN 7.67:17.3, the “weapon of wisdom” in verse at Dhp 40:3 and Thag 16.3:17.3. ↩

Found at SN 48.23 and Iti 62, this went on to become a standard set in later Theravāda. | “The faculty of understanding that one’s enlightenment is imminent” is literally, “The faculty aware that ‘I shall know the unknown’.” | The verses at Iti 62 help explain the meaning; see notes there for a detailed discussion. In brief, I disagree with the traditional interpretation, and think the three faculties apply to: (1) one on the path to arahantship; (2) one on the occasion of realizing arahantship; (3) one living as an arahant. ↩

The first two at MN 36. ↩

MN 35:26.2. ↩

This threefold presentation of the process of absorption focuses on vitakka (“placing the mind”) and vicāra (“keeping it connected”), looking closely at how they cease (see also DN 34:1.4.7, MN 128:31.4, SN 43.3:1.2, and AN 8.63:3.1). The standard jhāna formula focuses more on the refinement of feelings, from which perspective the first two stages of immersion here fall under the “rapture and bliss born of seclusion”, while only the third qualifies as “rapture and bliss born of immersion”. Thus Analayo describes the two descriptions as “complementary perspectives on the same process of deepening concentration” (Comparative Study, vol. ii, pg. 739, note 263). ↩

AN 3.183–352:1.3. ↩

AN 3.121, Iti 66. ↩

AN 3.122, Iti 67. ↩

AN 6.79:1.3; explained at Vb 16:259.1. These passages, and Thag 2.19:2.1, are the earliest appearances of the phrase “skill in means” (upāyakosalla) that would become famous in later Buddhism. ↩

AN 3.39:6.3. ↩

AN 3.40:1.3. ↩

AN 3.67. ↩

Called “high and luxurious beds” at AN 3.63:5.3. ↩

AN 3.60:8.3. ↩

AN 4.41. ↩

These are described as “limitless” in the formula, but this is the only early text they are called the “four limitless states” (or “immeasurables”). This is a sign of systematization. ↩

Often described as “formless”, here is the only place we find “four formless states” (āruppā). ↩

AN 10.20:6.1. ↩

AN 4.28. The sequence of pahāna (“giving up”) and bhāvanā (“meditation”) is swapped as compared with AN 4.28:4.1. ↩

AN 4.14. ↩

“Knowledge of the teaching” is the understanding of the observable principles of the teaching. | “Inferential knowledge” applies that to the past and future, especially in understanding the minds and behaviors of others without reading their minds. | “Knowledge of encompassing” is the psychic ability to read or “encompass” the mind of another. | “Conventional knowledge” is explained as understanding that is not included in the former three (Vb 16:310.1). It would especially include Vinaya matters that are agreed on “by convention” (AN 8.90:1.2, DN 33:1.10.82). | The first two are found at SN 12.33:14.2; see notes there for further discussion. The four are found at DN 34:1.5.3 and Vb 16:307.1. ↩

These are four practices that are specially helpful for attaining stream-entry (also at SN 55.5:1.6, etc.). ↩

This discourse distinguishes the “factors of a stream-enterer” (sotāpannassa aṅgāni) from the “factors for/of stream-entry” (sotāpattiyaṅgāni), but elsewhere only the latter term is used (SN 12.42:3.1, AN 9.28:4.1). Nonetheless, I follow Bhikkhu Bodhi’s suggestion, citing this passage, to translate the former set “factors for stream-entry” and the latter “factors of stream-entry”. The Pali can be construed both ways. ↩

SN 45.35:1.8. ↩

MN 9:11.4, SN 12.11:1.5, etc. ↩

SN 22.53:21.3, SN 22.54:2.1, etc. ↩

AN 4.18, etc. ↩

AN 4.9. ↩

AN 4.163. ↩

AN 4.29. ↩

AN 9.5:1.1. ↩

MN 140:11.1. ↩

AN 3.67:2.2. ↩

By treating ethical decisions via a tetralemma, the Buddha rejects the “law of the excluded middle” and the consequent belief that acts must be either right or wrong. ↩

MN 57:7.1, AN 4.236. ↩

AN 4.189, but the order there is direct experience, recollection, vision, wisdom. ↩

SN 35.238:12.2, etc. ↩

This and the next at AN 4.10. ↩

SN 45.174. ↩

MN 12:32.1. The four describe the births of different kinds of nāga (SN 29.1) and phoenix (SN 30.1). ↩

DN 28:5.2. ↩

AN 4.171. ↩

AN 4.78, MN 142:9.1. ↩

AN 4.32. ↩

This and the next are found in AN 4.250, etc., but there defined, as below, in terms of speech about what you’ve seen, heard, thought, or known. ↩

AN 4.198. | “With self become divine” (brahmabhūtena attanā) deliberately echoes Upaniṣadic language. Pali is sometimes said to lack reference to the cosmic Brahman (in neuter), having only the personal Brahmā (in masculine). The grammatical case of brahma- in the compound here is undetermined, yet no scholar of Sanskrit would hesitate to interpret the common phrase brahmabhūtātmā in the sense “self become one with the cosmic divinity Brahman”. Surely the Pali draws from the same sense, using it to describe Nibbāna. ↩

AN 4.85, SN 3.21. ↩

AN 4.87, etc. ↩

For the distinction between “aggregates” and “grasping aggregates” see SN 22.48, SN 22.82, MN 109. ↩

Also at MN 12:35.3. Later the asura (“demon” or “titan”) realm was added as the sixth. The number and nature of different realms is always somewhat fluid. ↩

AN 5.255:1.3. ↩

AN 9.8:3.4, DN 29:26.8, MN 76:51.3. ↩

This and the next at AN 5.130. ↩

Also at AN 5.213, Ud 8.6:4.1, DN 16:1.23.2, and Kd 6:28.4.1. ↩

AN 5.167, AN 10.44. ↩

AN 5.53. ↩

See DN 14:3.31.1, MN 120:21–30.7, etc. ↩

SN 48.16:1.5, etc. ↩

AN 5.205; with the next, AN 10.14:1.1, MN 16. ↩

As above, also AN 5.206:1.1. ↩

AN 5.200. ↩

AN 5.26. ↩

These five are found at AN 5.72 and AN 5.305, and also as part of longer lists. They are not, however, called “perceptions that ripen in freedom”. ↩

As “roots of arguments” at AN 6.36:1.5 and MN 104:6.5 (see below), and as impossibilities for a stream-enterer at AN 6.92. ↩

As a cause for the long lasting of the dispensation at AN 6.40:2.2. ↩

At AN 3.61:12.1 and MN 140:10.1 these three sets of six are combined as the “eighteen mental preoccupations”. ↩

AN 6.11. ↩

This group of six is also found at MN 104:6.1, AN 6.36, and Kd 14:14.3.1. ↩

AN 6.13. ↩

AN 6.30. ↩

AN 4.195:10.1. ↩

In AN 6.57 this is a response to the doctrine of Pūraṇa Kassapa. ↩

At AN 6.142 and AN 6.35, but not called “perceptions that help penetration”. ↩

Ariyadhana appears to be constructed after ācariyadhana, “a teacher’s fee”, and hence ariya here would be a noun rather than verb. ↩

AN 7.45. ↩

AN 7.93. ↩

AN 7.94. ↩

At AN 7.68 dhamma in this context is shown to be “teachings”, not “qualities”. ↩

AN 7.20. ↩

At AN 7.616, but not called “seven perceptions”. ↩

AN 7.3, etc. ↩

AN 7.44. ↩

Primarily a Vinaya topic (Kd 14:14.16.1), but also found at AN 7.84 and explained at MN 104:13.1. ↩

This and the next at AN 8.80. ↩

These are just called “gifts” at AN 8.31. The “reasons to give” at AN 8.33 are different. ↩

See MN 120:3.4 and AN 8.35:1.8. ↩

“Settled for less” also occurs at AN 8.35:1.9. Readings vary between hīne vimuttaṁ (“released in what is inferior”, per MS) and hīne ’dhimuttaṁ (“resolved upon what is inferior”). This is an example of an ambiguity between vi + √muc (“release”) and adhi + √muc (“resolve”) that is sometimes seen in Pali texts. The subcommentary reads vimuttaṁ and offers two explanations: “‘Released’ (vimuttaṁ) means ‘resolved’ (adhimuttaṁ); the meaning is slants, slopes, and inclines. Or else ‘released’ means ‘set free’ (vissaṭṭhaṁ).” Given that it is clearly accepted in the commentarial tradition, and that it is the more difficult reading, it seems we must accept vimuttaṁ as the correct reading here. But from context, and from the subcommentary, it has the same sense as adhimutta, namely, “resolved upon”. This goes some way to explaining the ambiguity between the two words, as they not only have a similar form, but their meanings can overlap too. ↩

Notice that they have “seen” the well-to-do brahmins or aristocrats, but have only “heard of” the various deities. ↩

Previous rebirths required only ethics. Rebirth in the Brahmā realm, however, requires the freedom of the mind from hindrances through practicing absorption. ↩

AN 8.35. ↩

AN 8.69. ↩

AN 8.6. ↩

AN 8.65. ↩

AN 8.66. ↩

AN 9.29. ↩

AN 9.24. ↩

Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 1.3.10 warns that, because the knowledge of the gods have not reached them, the lands beyond the borders are the domain of death. ↩

Eight at AN 8.29 and DN 34:2.1.122; the ninth here is made by adding the asura rebirth. ↩

AN 9.33. ↩

Also at AN 9.31 and AN 9.61. Compare the “progressive cessation of conditions” at SN 36.11. ↩

This agrees with the pre-Buddhist sense of sati (Sanskrit smṛti, smara), “to remember, keep in mind” (Rig Veda 7.104.07, 10.61.4, 10.106.9; Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 13.8.1.2; Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 5.15.1; Chāndogya Upaniṣad 7.13–14, 8.12.3; Kena Upaniṣad 4.5). Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa 2.3.2.3–4 speaks of one who performs the fire ritual while understanding, “In me those gods reside” and thereby wins and traverses all the worlds (since the gods and their worlds = heavens exist inside them; see SN 2.26:5.2 and note there). When such a one leaves the ritual ground they continue to “attend” (upasthāna = Pali upaṭṭhāna) the sacred fire through remembering it (smara), and thus staying near it in their mind. “Memory” is critical to the practice of “remembering” scripture (Chāndogya Upaniṣad 6.7). A skilled reciter enters an uninterrupted flow state where the text is vividly present. In this sense, mindfulness can be understood as the element of continuity that knits consciousness together in a coherent stream. Thus when practicing “mindfulness of breathing” one pays continuous attention to the breaths, not “forgetting” what one is doing. ↩

AN 10.17, AN 10.18. ↩

AN 10.25. Kaṣina means “universal”, “totality”, and it refers to a measureless state of jhāna. In later usage it became a term for a physical object, such as a disk, on which a meditator focused, but it never has this meaning in early texts. Yājñavalkya says that, just as salt is “entirely” salty, the Self is an “entire mass of consciousness” (kṛtsnaḥ prajñānaghana eva, Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad 4.5.13). ↩

AN 10.19. ↩

AN 10.112. ↩

As in DN 4. ↩

This discourse is similar to DN 33; seventy items are shared between the two. Here Sāriputta teaches without prompting. The scheme is more rigorous; items listed according to a specific pattern, then the same pattern is amplified one by one. The constraints of this scheme mean that, while almost all the items listed here are found elsewhere, they are mostly not known by the name used here. This sutta seems a little later than DN 33, but such conclusions should be drawn cautiously; in at least one detail, the absence of the asura realm from the “lost opportunities”, the passage here is earlier. ↩

The use of a verse to introduce the teachings is unusual. ↩

This echoes Chāndogya Upaniṣad 7.26.2, sarvagranthīnāṁ vipramokṣaḥ. ↩

Each number from one to ten follows this same scheme. ↩

Compare SN 3.18:8.2. ↩

Compare SN 16.11:12.2. ↩

Compare SN 22.48:2.2, but this is the five aggregates rather than contact. ↩

This term is only found in the Ratanasutta (Snp 2.1:5.2). It means a kind of meditation that results in the realization of the Dhamma in this very life. ↩

See AN 4.254. ↩

Discussed at SN 22.60. ↩

The “unconditioned element” is Nibbāna, everything else is conditioned. ↩

With the addition of “rational application of mind” at AN 4.249. ↩

Iti 72. ↩

These three “portions” of knowledge are not found elsewhere, but compare eg. SN 12.34. ↩

AN 4.31. ↩

Described as four “perceptions” at AN 4.179. ↩

A different group of five factors of immersion is at AN 5.28; the final factor is the same in both. The first four factors, however, appear only as part of this same group in later texts (Ne 21:5.1, Ps 1.1:246.2, Vb 16:342.2). ↩

The expression “slants to seclusion” (vikekaninna) was adopted by Patañjali at Yogasūtra 4.26. ↩

AN 8.2. ↩

At this point, DN 33:3.2.53 has an extra possibility, rebirth among the titans, making nine in all. ↩

The negative is absent from the text due to abbreviation, so it is inferred from the parallel passage at DN 33:3.2.69. ↩

AN 8.30. | Read nippapañcārāmassāyaṁ per AN 8.30:3.11. ↩

Similar sequences are found throughout the suttas, but this exact sequence appears to be unique. ↩

Four are found at AN 4.194. Seven, phrased slightly differently, are found at MN 23. ↩

AN 9.23. ↩

SN 14.9. ↩

AN 9.93. ↩

AN 10.238. ↩

The sutta, and hence the Dīgha Nikāya as a whole, ends with the qualities of the arahant, the one who completes the path and practice of the Buddha. ↩